<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<html>
<head>
</head>
<body>
  <para id="0">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">1</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">1</se>
  </para>
  <para id="1">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">My first recollection of Timofey Pnin is connected with a speck of coal dust that entered my left eye on a spring Sunday in 1911.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Первое мое воспоминание о Тимофее Пнине связано с кусочком угля, залетевшим мне в левый глаз в весеннее воскресенье 1911 года.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="2">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">It was one of those rough, gusty, and lustrous mornings in St Petersburg, when the last transparent piece of Ladoga ice has been carried away to the gulf by the Neva, and her indigo waves heave and lap the granite of the embankment, and the tugboats and huge barges, moored along the quay, creak and scrape rhythmically, and the mahogany and brass of anchored steam yachts shine in the skittish sun.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Стояло одно из тех резких, ветренных, сияющих петербургских утр, когда последние прозрачные куски ладожского льда уже унесены Невою в залив, и индиговые волны ее, вздымаясь, плещут в береговой гранит, и причаленные к стенке огромные буксиры и барки мерно трутся и скрипят, и медь и красное дерево заякоренных паровых яхт сияют под изменчивым солнцем.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="3">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">I had been trying out a beautiful new English bicycle given me for my twelfth birthday, and, as I rode home to our rosy-stone house in the Morskaya, over parquet-smooth wooden pavements, the consciousness of having gravely disobeyed my tutor was less bothersome than the granule of smarting pain in the far north of my eyeball.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Я испытывал прекрасный новый английский велосипед, подаренный мне на двенадцатый день рождения, и пока я катил к нашему розоватого камня дому на Морской по гладкой, ровно паркет, деревянной панели, сознание того, что я серьезнейшим образом ослушался гувернера, терзало меня меньше, чем зернышко жгучей боли на крайнем севере моего глазного яблока.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="4">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Home remedies, such as the application of wads of cotton-wool soaked in cool tea and the tri-k-nosu (rub-noseward) device, only made matters worse; and when I awoke next morning, the object lurking under my upper eyelid felt like a solid polygon that became more deeply embedded at every watery wink.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Домашние средства вроде прикладывания ватки, смоченной в холодном чае, или примененья методы, называемой "три к носу", только ухудшили положение, и когда я назавтра проснулся, то, что засело под верхним веком, ощущалось как твердый многогранник, при каждом слезливом моргании погружавшийся на все большую глубину.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="5">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">In the afternoon I was taken to a leading ophthalmologist, Dr Pavel Pnin.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">В полдень меня свезли к лучшему окулисту, доктору Павлу Пнину.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="6">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">One of those silly incidents that remain forever in a child's receptive mind marked the space of time my tutor and I spent in Dr Pnin's sundust-and-plush waiting-room, where the blue dab of a window in miniature was reflected in the glass dome of an ormolu clock on the mantelpiece, and two flies kept describing slow quadrangles around the lifeless chandelier.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Глупое происшествие из тех, что навсегда застревают в восприимчивом детском сознании, размечает пространство времени, проведенного мною и гувернером в заполненной солнечной пылью и плюшем приемной д-ра Пнина, где голубой мазок окна миниатюрно отражался в стеклянном колпаке золоченых бронзовых часов на камине, и пара мух описывала медленные четырехугольники вокруг безжизненной люстры.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="7">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">A lady, wearing a plumed hat, and her dark-spectacled husband were sitting in connubial silence on the davenport; then a cavalry officer entered and sat near the window reading a newspaper; then the husband repaired to Dr Pnin's study; and then I noticed an odd expression on my tutor's face.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Дама в шляпе с плюмажем и ее муж в темных очках, храня супружеское безмолвие, сидели на диване; вошел кавалерийский офицер и присел с газетой к окну; затем муж удалился в кабинет д-ра Пнина; а затем я заметил странное выражение на лице моего гувернера.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="8">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">With my good eye I followed his stare.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Здоровым оком я проследил направление его взгляда.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="9">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">The officer was leaning toward the lady.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Офицер склонялся к даме.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="10">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">In rapid French he berated her for something she had done or not done the day before.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">По-французски он бегло корил ее за что-то, сделанное или не сделанное вчера.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="11">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">She gave him her gloved hand to kiss.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Она протянула ему для поцелуя руку в перчатке.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="12">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He glued himself to its eyelet вЂ” and forthwith left, cured of whatever had ailed him.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Он приник к перчаточному глазку - и ушел, излеченный от своего недуга, в чем бы тот ни заключался.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="13">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">In softness of features, body bulk, leanness of leg, apish shape of ear and upper lip, Dr Pavel Pnin looked very like Timofey, as the latter was to look three or four decades later.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Мягкостью черт, массивностью тела, тонкостью ног и обезьяньими очертаньями уха и верхней губы д-р Павел Пнин очень походил на Тимофея, каким тот стал через три-четыре десятка лет.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="14">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">In the father, however, a fringe of straw-coloured hair relieved a waxlike calvity; he wore a black-rimmed pince-nez on a black ribbon like the late Dr Chekhov; he spoke in a gentle stutter, very unlike his son's later voice.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Впрочем, у отца бахрома соломенных волос оживляла восковую плешь; он, подобно покойному доктору Чехову, носил пенсне в черной оправе на черном же шнурке; он говорил слегка заикаясь, голосом вовсе не похожим на будущий голос сына.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="15">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">And what a divine relief it was when, with a tiny instrument resembling an elf's drumstick, the tender doctor removed from my eyeball the offending black atom!</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">И какое божественное облегчение испытал я, когда с помощью крохотного инструмента, похожего на барабанную палочку эльфа, ласковый доктор удалил у меня из глаза преступный черный атом!</se>
  </para>
  <para id="16">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">I wonder where that speck is now?</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Интересно, где она теперь, эта соринка?</se>
  </para>
  <para id="17">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">The dull, mad fact is that it does exist somewhere.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Сводящий с ума, наводящий уныние факт, - где-то ведь она существует.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="18">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Perhaps because on my visits to schoolmates I had seen other middle-class apartments, I unconsciously retained a picture of the Pnin flat that probably corresponds to reality.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Возможно оттого, что посещая одноклассников, я видел и другие жилища людей среднего достатка, у меня безотчетно сложился образ квартиры Пнина, вернее всего, отвечающий истине.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="19">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">I can report therefore that as likely as not it consisted of two rows of rooms divided by a long corridor; on one side was the waiting-room, the doctor's office, presumably a dining-room and a drawing-room farther on; and on the other side were two or three bedrooms, a schoolroom, a bathroom, a maid's room, and a kitchen.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">А потому могу сообщить здесь, что она, возможно (а возможно и нет), состояла из двух порядков комнат, разделенных длинным коридором; по одной стороне - приемная, кабинет доктора, дальше, предположительно, столовая и гостиная; а по другой - две или три спальни, классная, ванная, комната прислуги и кухня.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="20">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">I was about to leave with a phial of eye lotion, and my tutor was taking the opportunity to ask Dr Pnin if eyestrain might cause gastric trouble, when the front door opened and shut.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Я уже уходил с флаконом глазной примочки, а мой гувернер, пользуясь случаем, выспрашивал у д-ра Пнина может ли перенапряжение глаз вызывать расстройство желудка, когда отворилась и затворилась входная дверь.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="21">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Dr Pnin nimbly walked into the passage, voiced a query, received a quiet answer, and returned with his son Timofey, a thirteen-year-old gimnazist (classical school pupil) in his gimnazicheskiy uniform вЂ” black blouse, black pants, shiny black belt (I attended a more liberal school where we wore what we liked).</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Д-р Пнин проворно вышел в переднюю, о чем-то спросил, получил тихий ответ и вернулся с сыном Тимофеем, гимназистом тринадцати лет, одетым в гимназическую форму: черная рубаха, черные штаны, глянцевый черный ремень (я учился в более либеральной школе, мы одевались там кто во что горазд).</se>
  </para>
  <para id="22">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Do I really remember his crew cut, his puffy pale face, his red ears?</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Действительно ли я помню его ежик, припухлое бледное лицо, красные уши?</se>
  </para>
  <para id="23">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Yes, distinctly.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Да, явственно.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="24">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">I even remember the way he imperceptibly removed his shoulder from under the proud paternal hand, while the proud paternal voice was saying: 'This boy has just got a Five Plus (A +) in the Algebra examination.' From the end of the corridor there came a steady smell of hashed-cabbage pie, and through the open door of the schoolroom I could see a map of Russia on the wall, books on a shelf, a stuffed squirrel, and a toy monoplane with linen wings and a rubber motor.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Я помню даже, как он неприметно вывернул плечо из-под гордой отцовской руки, когда гордый отцовский голос сказал: "Этот мальчик только что получил пять с плюсом на экзамене по алгебре". Из дальнего конца коридора несся сильный запах кулебяки с капустой, а за открытой дверью классной виднелась карта России на стене, книги на полке, чучело белки и игрушечный моноплан с полотняными крыльями и резиновым моторчиком.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="25">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">I had a similar one but twice bigger, bought in Biarritz.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">У меня был похожий, купленный в Биаррице, только в два раза крупней.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="26">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">After one had wound up the propeller for some time, the rubber would change its manner of twist and develop fascinating thick whorls which predicted the end of its tether.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Если долго вертеть пропеллер, резинка начинала навиваться по-иному, занятно скручиваясь, что предвещало близость ее конца.</se>
  </para>
</body>
</html>
