<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<html>
<head>
</head>
<body>
  <para id="0">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">4</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">4</se>
  </para>
  <para id="1">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">When half a dozen years later I revisited Paris, I learned that Timofey Pnin had married Liza Bogolepov soon after my departure.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Когда через полдюжины лет я вновь оказался в Париже, мне сказали, что вскоре после моего отъезда Тимофей Пнин женился на Лизе Боголеповой.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="2">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">She sent me a published collection of her poems Suhie GubГЇ (Dry Lips) with the inscription in dark-red ink: 'To a Stranger from a Stranger' (neznakomtsu ot neznakomki).</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Она прислала мне вышедший в свет сборник ее стихов "Сухие губы", надписав темно-красными чернилами: "Незнакомцу от Незнакомки".</se>
  </para>
  <para id="3">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">I saw Pnin and her at an evening tea in the apartment of a famous Г©migrГ©, a social revolutionary, one of those informal gatherings where old-fashioned terrorists, heroic nuns, gifted hedonists, liberals, adventurous young poets, elderly novelists and artists, publishers and publicists, free-minded philosophers and scholars would represent a kind of special knighthood, the active and significant nucleus of an exiled society which during the third of a century it flourished remained practically unknown to American intellectuals, for whom the notion of Russian emigration was made to mean by astute Communist propaganda a vague and perfectly fictitious mass of so-called Trotskiites (whatever these are), ruined reactionaries, reformed or disguised Cheka men, tided ladies, professional priests, restaurant keepers, and White Russian military groups, all of them of no cultural importance whatever.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Я встретился с ней и с Пниным в доме известного эмигранта, эсера, за вечерним чаем - на одном из тех непринужденных сборищ, где старомодные террористы, героические монахини, одаренные гедонисты, либералы, дерзновенные молодые поэты, пожилые писатели и художники, издатели и публицисты, вольнодумные философы и ученые являли род особого рыцарства, деятельное и значительное ядро сообщества изгнанников, треть столетия процветавшего, оставаясь практически неведомым американским интеллектуалам, у которых хитроумная коммунистическая пропаганда создавала об эмиграции туманное, целиком надуманное представление как о мутной и полностью вымышленной массе так называемых "троцкистов" (уж и не знаю, кто это), разорившихся реакционеров, чекистов (перебежавших или переодетых), титулованных дам, профессиональных священников, владельцев ресторанов, белогвардейских союзов, - массе, культурного значения не имеющей решительно никакого.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="4">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Taking advantage of Pnin's being engaged in a political discussion with Kerenski at the other end of the table, Liza informed me вЂ” with her usual crude candour вЂ” that she had 'told Timofey everything'; that he was' a saint' and had 'pardoned' me.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Воспользовавшись тем, что Пнин на другом конце стола погрузился в политические дебаты с Керенским, Лиза со всегдашней ее грубой прямотой сообщила мне, что она "обо всем рассказала Тимофею", что он "святой", и что он меня "простил".</se>
  </para>
  <para id="5">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Fortunately, she did not often accompany him to later receptions where I had the pleasure of sitting next to him, or opposite him, in the company of dear friends, on our small lone planet, above the black and diamond city, with the lamplight on this or that Socratic cranium and a slice of lemon revolving in the glass of stirred tea.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">По счастью, она не часто сопровождала его на поздние приемы, где я имел удовольствие сиживать с ним бок о бок или насупротив в обществе близких друзей, на нашей маленькой одинокой планете, над черным и бриллиантовым городом, и свет лампы падал на чье-нибудь сократовское чело, и ломтик лимона кружился в стакане помешиваемого чая.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="6">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">One night, as Dr Barakan, Pnin, and I were sitting at the Bolotovs, I happened to be talking to the neurologist about a cousin of his, Ludmila, now Lady DвЂ”, whom I had known in Yalta, Athens, and London, when suddenly Pnin cried to Dr Barakan across the table: 'Now, don't believe a word he says, Georgiy Aramovich.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Как-то ночью, когда доктор Баракан, Пнин и я сидели у Болотовых, я заговорил с невропатологом о его двоюродной сестре Людмиле, ныне леди Д., • мы встречались с ней в Ялте, Афинах и Лондоне, • как вдруг Пнин через стол крикнул д-ру Баракану: "Да не верьте вы не одному его слову, Георгий Арамович.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="7">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He makes up everything.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Он же все сочиняет.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="8">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He once invented that we were schoolmates in Russia and cribbed at examinations.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Он как-то выдумал, будто мы с ним в России учились в одном классе и сдували друг у друга на экзаменах.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="9">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He is a dreadful inventor (on uzhasnГЇy vГЇdumshchik).' Barakan and I were so astounded by this outburst that we just sat and looked at each other in silence.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Он ужасный выдумщик." Баракана и меня до того изумил этот внезапный порыв, что мы так и остались сидеть, молча уставясь один на другого.</se>
  </para>
</body>
</html>
