<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<html>
<head>
</head>
<body>
  <para id="0">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">6</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">6</se>
  </para>
  <para id="1">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">This being Tuesday, he could walk over to his favourite haunt immediately after lunch and stay there till dinner time.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Поскольку сегодня был вторник, он мог сразу после лэнча отправиться в свой любимый приют и остаться там до обеда.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="2">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">No gallery connected Waindell College Library with any other buildings, but it was intimately and securely connected with Pnin's heart.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Никакие галереи не соединяли библиотеку вайнделлского колледжа с другими строениями, но с сердцем Пнина она соединялась крепко и сокровенно.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="3">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He walked past the great bronze figure of the first president of the college, Alpheus Frieze, in sports cap and knickerbockers, holding by its horns the bronze bicycle he was eternally about to mount, judging by the position of his left foot, forever glued to the left pedal.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Он шел мимо огромной бронзовой фигуры первого президента колледжа Альфеуса Фриза - в спортивной кепке и бриджах, державшего за рога бронзовый велосипед, на который он, судя по положению его левой ноги, навеки прилипшей к левой педали, вечно пытался взобраться.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="4">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">There was snow on the saddle and snow in the absurd basket that recent pranksters had attached to the handle bars.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Снег лежал на седле, снег лежал и в нелепой корзинке, которую недавние шалуны прицепили к рулю.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="5">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'HuliganГЇ' fumed Pnin, shaking his head вЂ” and slipped slightly on a flag of the path that meandered down a turfy slope among the leafless elms.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">"Хулиганы", - пропыхтел Пнин, покачав головой, и слегка оскользнулся на одной из плиток дорожки, круто спускавшейся по травянистому скату между безлиственных ильмов.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="6">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Besides the big book under his right arm, he carried in his left hand his brief-case, an old, Central European-looking, black portfel', and this he swung rhythmically by its leathern grip as he marched to his books, to his scriptorium in the stacks, to his paradise of Russian lore.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Помимо большой книги под правой рукой, он нес в левой свой старый, европейского вида черный портфель и мерно помахивал им, держа за кожаную хватку и вышагивая к своим книгам, в свой скрипториум среди стеллажей, в рай российской премудрости.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="7">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">An elliptic flock of pigeons, in circular volitation, soaring grey, flapping white, and then grey again, wheeled across the limpid, pale sky, above the College Library.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Эллиптическая голубиная стая в круговом полете, серея на взлете, белея на хлопотливом спуске, и снова серея, прошла колесом по ясному бледному небу над библиотекой колледжа.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="8">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">A train whistled afar as mournfully as in the steppes.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Скорбно, будто в степи, свистнул далекий поезд.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="9">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">A skimpy squirrel dashed over a patch of sunlit snow, where a tree trunk's shadow, olive-green on the turf, became greyish blue for a stretch, while the tree itself, with a brisk, scrabbly sound, ascended, naked, into the sky, where the pigeons swept by for a third and last time.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Тощая белка метнулась через облитый солнцем снежный лоскут, где тень ствола, оливково-зеленая на мураве, становилась ненадолго серовато-голубой, само же дерево с живым скребущим звуком поднималось, голое, в небо, по которому в третий и в последний раз пронеслась голубиная стая.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="10">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">The squirrel, invisible now in a crotch, chattered, scolding the delinquents who would pot him out of his tree.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Белка, уже невидимая в развилке, залопотала, браня кознедеев, возмечтавших выжить ее с дерева.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="11">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Pnin, on the dirty black ice of the flagged path, slipped again, threw up one arm in an abrupt convulsion, regained his balance, and, with a solitary smile, stooped to pick up Zol.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Пнин опять поскользнулся на черном льду мощеной дорожки, махнул от внезапного встряха рукой и с улыбкой пустынника наклонился, чтобы поднять "Зол.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="12">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Fond Lit., which lay wide open to a snapshot of a Russian. pasture with Lyov Tolstoy trudging across it toward the camera and some long-maned horses behind him, their innocent heads turned toward the photographer too.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Фонд Лит.", который лежал, широко раскрывшись на снимке русского выгона с Львом Толстым, устало бредущим на камеру, и долгогривыми лошадьми за его спиной, тоже повернувшими к фотографу свои невинные головы.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="13">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">V boyu li, v stranstvii, v volnah?</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">"В бою ли, в странствии, в волнах"?</se>
  </para>
  <para id="14">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">In fight, in travel, or in waves?</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1"></se>
  </para>
  <para id="15">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Or on the Waindell campus?</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Иль в кампусе Вайнделла?</se>
  </para>
  <para id="16">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Gently champing his dentures, which retained a sticky layer of cottage cheese, Pnin went up the slippery library steps.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Слегка пошевеливая зубными протезами, на которые налипла пленочка творога, Пнин поднялся по скользким ступеням библиотеки.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="17">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Like so many ageing college people, Pnin had long ceased to notice the existence of students on the campus, in the corridors, in the library вЂ” anywhere, in brief, save in functional classroom concentrations.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Подобно многим пожилым преподавателям колледжа, Пнин давно уже перестал замечать студентов - в кампусе, в коридоре, в библиотеке, - словом, где бы то ни было, за вычетом их функциональных скоплений в классах.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="18">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">In the beginning, he had been much upset by the sight of some of them, their poor young heads on their forearms, fast asleep among the ruins of knowledge; but now, except for a girl's comely nape here and there, he saw nobody in the Reading Room.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Поначалу его сильно печалил вид кое-кого из них, крепко спавших среди развалин Знания, уронив бедные молодые головы на скрещенные руки; теперь он никого не видел в читальне, разве что попадались там и сям пригожие девичьи затылки.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="19">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Mrs Thayer was at the circulation desk.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">За абонементным столом сидела миссис Тейер.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="20">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Her mother and Mrs Clements' mother had been first cousins.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Ее матушка приходилась двоюродной сестрой матери миссис Клементс.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="21">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'How are you today, Professor Pnin?'</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">- Как поживаете, профессор Пнин?</se>
  </para>
  <para id="22">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'I am very well, Mrs Fire.'</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">- Очень хорошо, миссис Файр.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="23">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'Laurence and Joan aren't back yet, are they?'</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">- Лоренс и Джоан еще не вернулись?</se>
  </para>
  <para id="24">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'No.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">- Нет.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="25">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">I have brought this book back because I received this card вЂ” '</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Я принес назад эту книгу, потому что получил эту карточку...</se>
  </para>
  <para id="26">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'I wonder if poor Isabel will really get divorced.'</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">- Неужели бедняжка Изабель и вправду разводится?</se>
  </para>
  <para id="27">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'I have not heard.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">- Не слышал об этом.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="28">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Mrs Fire, permit me to ask вЂ” '</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Миссис Файр, позвольте мне спросить...</se>
  </para>
  <para id="29">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'I suppose we'll have to find you another room, if they bring her back with them.'</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">- Боюсь, если они вернутся с ней, нам придется искать для вас другую комнату.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="30">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'Mrs Fire, permit me to ask something or other.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">- Да позвольте же мне задать вопрос, миссис Файр.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="31">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">This card which I received yesterday вЂ” could you maybe tell me who is the other reader?'</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Эта карточка, которую я получил вчера, - может быть, вы мне скажете, кто этот другой читатель.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="32">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'Let me check.'</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">- Сейчас посмотрю.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="33">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">She checked.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Она посмотрела.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="34">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">The other reader proved to be Timofey Pnin; Volume 18 had been requested by him the Friday before.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Другим читателем оказался Тимофей Пнин: том 18 был им затребован в прошлую пятницу.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="35">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">It was also true that this Volume 18 was already charged to this Pnin, who had had it since Christmas and now stood with his hands upon it, like an ancestral picture of a magistrate.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Верно было также и то, что том 18 был уже выдан тому же Пнину, который держал его с Рождества и который стоял сейчас, возложив на него руки и напоминая судью с родового портрета.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="36">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'It can't be!' cried Pnin.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">- Не может быть! - вскричал Пнин.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="37">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'I requested on Friday Volume 19, year 1947, not 18, year 1940'</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">- В пятницу я заказывал том 19 за 1947 год, а не том 18 за 1940-й.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="38">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'But look вЂ” you wrote Volume 18. Anyway, 19 is still being processed.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">- Но посмотрите, вы написали "том 18". Во всяком случае, 19-й пока регистрируется.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="39">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Are you keeping this?'</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Этот вы оставите у себя?</se>
  </para>
  <para id="40">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'18, 19,' muttered Pnin.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">- 18-й, 19-й, - бормотал Пнин.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="41">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'There is not great difference!</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">- Велика разница!</se>
  </para>
  <para id="42">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">I put the year correctly, that is important!</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Год-то я правильно написал, вот что важно!</se>
  </para>
  <para id="43">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Yes, I still need 18 вЂ” and send to me a more effishant card when 19 available.'</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Да, 18-й мне еще нужен, и пришлите мне открытку потолковее, когда получите 19-й.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="44">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Growling a little, he took the unwieldy, abashed book to his favourite alcove and laid it down there, wrapped in his muffler.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Негромко ворча, он отнес громоздкий, сконфуженный том в свой альков и сложил его там, обернув шарфом.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="45">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">They can't read, these women.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Они просто читать не умеют, эти женщины.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="46">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">The year was plainly inscribed.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Год же был ясно указан.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="47">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">As usual he marched to the Periodicals Room and there glanced at the news in the latest (Saturday, February 12 вЂ” and this was Tuesday, O Careless Reader!) issue of the Russian-language daily published, since 1918, by an Г©migrГ© group in Chicago.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Как обычно, он отправился в зал периодики и просмотрел новости в последнем (суббота, 12 февраля, - а нынче вторник, о небрежный читатель!) номере русской газеты, с 1918 года ежедневно выпускаемой в Чикаго русскими эмигрантами.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="48">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">As usual, he carefully scanned the advertisements.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Как обычно, он внимательно изучил объявления.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="49">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Dr Popov, photographed in his new white smock, promised elderly people new vigour and joy.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Доктор Попов, сфотографированный в новом белом халате, сулил пожилым людям новые силы и радости.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="50">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">A music corporation listed Russian phonograph records for sale, such as 'Broken Life, a Waltz' and 'The Song of a Front-Line Chauffeur'.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Музыкальная фирма перечисляла поступившие в продажу русские граммофонные записи, например, "Разбитая жизнь. Вальс" и "Песенка фронтового шофера".</se>
  </para>
  <para id="51">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">A somewhat Gogolian mortician praised his hearses de luxe, which were also available for picnics.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Отчасти припахивающий Гоголем гробовщик расхваливал свои катафалки de luxe1, пригодные также для пикников.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="52">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Another Gogolian person, in Miami, offered 'a two-room apartment for non-drinkers (dlya trezvГЇh), among fruit trees and flowers', while in Hammond a room was wistfully being let' in a small quiet family' вЂ” and for no special reason the reader suddenly saw, with passionate and ridiculous lucidity, his parents, Dr Pavel Pnin and Valeria Pnin, he with a medical journal, she with a political review, sitting in two armchairs, facing each other in a small, cheerfully lighted drawing room on Galernaya Street, St Petersburg, forty years ago.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Другой гоголевский персонаж, из Майями, предлагал "двухкомнатную квартиру для трезвых среди цветов и фруктовых деревьев", тогда как в Хэммонде комната мечтательно предлагалась "в небольшой тихой семье", - и без какой-либо особой причины читающий вдруг с пылкой и смехотворной ясностью увидел своих родителей - доктора Павла Пнина и Валерию Пнину, его с медицинским журналом, ее с политическим обзором, - сидящими в креслах друг к дружке лицом в маленькой, весело освещенной гостиной на Галерной, в Петербурге, сорок лет тому назад.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="53">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He also perused the current item in a tremendously long and tedious controversy between three Г©migrГ© factions.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Изучил он и очередной кусок страшно длинного и скучного препирательства между тремя эмигрантскими фракциями.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="54">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">It had started by Faction A's accusing Faction B of inertia and illustrating it by the proverb.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Началось все с того, что фракция А обвинила фракцию Б в инертности и проиллюстрировала обвинение пословицей </se>
  </para>
  <para id="55">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'He wishes to climb the fir tree but is afraid to scrape his shins.' This had provoked an acid Letter to the Editor from' An Old Optimist', entitled 'Fir Trees and Inertia' and beginning: 'There is an old American saying "He who lives in a glass house should not try to kill two birds with one stone".' In the present issue, there was a two-thousand-word feuilleton contributed by a representative of Faction C and headed 'On Fir Trees, Glass Houses, and Optimism', and Pnin read this with great interest and sympathy.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">В ответ появилось ядовитое письмо к редактору от "Старого Оптимиста", озаглавленное "Елки и инертность" и начинавшееся так: "Есть старая американская пословица, гласящая: 'Тому, кто живет в стеклянном доме, не стоит пытаться убить одним камнем двух птиц'". Теперешний номер газеты содержал фельетон на две тысячи слов - вклад представителя фракции В, - названный "О елках, стеклянных домах и оптимизме", и Пнин прочитал его с большим интересом и сочувствием.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="56">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He then returned to his carrell for his own research.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Затем он вернулся в свою кабинку, к собственным изысканиям.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="57">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He contemplated writing a Petite Histoire of Russian culture, in which a choice of Russian Curiosities, Customs, Literary Anecdotes, and so forth would be presented in such a way as to reflect in miniature la Grande Histoire вЂ” Major Concatenations of Events.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Он замыслил написать "Малую историю" русской культуры, в которой российские несуразицы, обычаи, литературные анекдоты и тому подобное были бы подобраны так, чтобы отразить в миниатюре "Большую историю" - основное сцепление событий.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="58">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He was still at the blissful stage of collecting his material; and many good young people considered it a treat and an honour to see Pnin pull out a catalogue drawer from the comprehensive bosom of a card cabinet and take it, like a big nut, to a secluded corner and there make a quiet mental meal of it, now moving his lips in soundless comment, critical, satisfied, perplexed, and now lifting his rudimentary eyebrows and forgetting them there, left high upon his spacious brow where they remained long after all trace of displeasure or doubt had gone.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Пока он находился на благословенной стадии сбора материала, и многие достойные молодые люди почитали для себя за честь и удовольствие наблюдать, как Пнин вытягивает каталожный ящик из обширной пазухи картотеки, несет его, словно большой орех, в укромный уголок и там тихо вкушает духовную пищу, то шевеля губами в безгласных комментариях - критических, озадаченных, удовлетворенных, - то подымая рудиментарные брови и забывая их опустить, и они остаются на просторном челе еще долгое время после того, как теряются все следы неудовольствия и сомнения.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="59">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He was lucky to be at Waindell.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">С Вайнделлом ему повезло.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="60">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Sometime in the nineties the eminent bibliophile and Slavist John Thurston Todd (his bearded bust presided over the drinking fountain) had visited hospitable Russia, and after his death the books he had amassed there quietly chuted into a remote stack.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Превосходный библиофил и славист Джон Тэрстон Тодд (чей бородатый бронзовый бюст возвышался над питьевым фонтанчиком) навестил в девяностых годах гостеприимную Россию, а после его смерти книги, которые он во множестве вывез оттуда, тихо спланировали на дальние стеллажи.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="61">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Wearing rubber gloves so as to avoid being stung by the amerikanski electricity in the metal of the shelving, Pnin would go to those books and gloat over them: obscure magazines of the Roaring Sixties in marbled boards; century-old historical monographs, their somnolent pages foxed with fungus spots; Russian classics in horrible and pathetic cameo bindings, whose moulded profiles of poets reminded dewy-eyed Timofey of his boyhood, when he could idly palpate on the book cover Pushkin's slightly chafed side whisker or Zhukovski's smudgy nose.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Натянув резиновые перчатки, дабы его не ужалило скрытое в металлических полках американское электричество, Пнин приходил к этим книгам и вожделенно их созерцал: малоизвестные журналы ревущих шестидесятых в мрамористых обложках, исторические монографии столетней давности с бурыми пятнами плесени на усыпительных страницах, русские классики в ужасных и трогательных камеевых переплетах с тиснеными профилями поэтов, напоминавшими влажноочитому Тимофею о детстве, в котором праздные пальцы его блуждали по книжной обложке со слегка потертой пушкинской бакенбардой или запачканным носом Жуковского.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="62">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Today from Kostromskoy's voluminous work (Moscow, 1855) on Russian myths вЂ” a rare book, not to be removed from the library вЂ” Pnin, with a not unhappy sigh, started to copy out a passage referring to the old pagan games that were still practised at the time, throughout the woodlands of the Upper Volga, in the margins of Christian ritual.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Сегодня он начал (с отнюдь не горестным вздохом) выписывать из посвященного русским сказаниям объемистого труда Костромского (Москва, 1855), - редкая книга, из библиотеки не выдается, - место, где говорится о старинных языческих игрищах, которые все еще совершались о ту пору по дремучим верховьям Волги в дополнение к христианским обрядам.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="63">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">During a festive week in May вЂ” the so-called Green Week which graded into Whitsuntide вЂ” peasant maidens would make wreaths of buttercups and frog orchises; then, singing snatches of ancient love chants, they hung these garlands on riverside willows; and on Whit Sunday the wreaths were shaken down into the river, where, unwinding, they floated like so many serpents while the maidens floated and chanted among them.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Во всю праздничную неделю мая - так называемую Зеленую Неделю, потом уже ставшую неделей Пятидесятницы, - сельские девушки плели венки из лютиков и жабника и, распевая обрывки древних любовных заклинаний, вешали эти венки на прибрежные ивы, а в Троицын день венки стряхивались в реку и, расплетаясь, плыли, словно змеи, и девушки плавали среди них и пели.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="64">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">A curious verbal association struck Pnin at this point; he could not catch it by its mermaid tail but made a note on his index card and plunged back into Kostromskoy.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Тут странное словесное сходство поразило Пнина, он не успел ухватить его за русалочий хвост, но сделал пометку в справочной карточке и вновь нырнул в Костромского.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="65">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">When Pnin raised his eyes again, it was dinner-time.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Когда Пнин снова поднял глаза, наступил уже час обеда.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="66">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Doffing his spectacles, he rubbed with the knuckles of the hand that held them his naked and tired eyes and, still in thought, fixed his mild gaze on the window above, where, gradually, through his dissolving meditation, there appeared the violet-blue air of dusk, silver-tooled by the reflection of the fluorescent lights of the ceiling, and, among spidery black twigs, a mirrored row of bright book spines.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Сняв очки, он протер костяшками державшей их руки свои голые, усталые глаза и, все еще погруженный в мысли, уставил кроткий взгляд на окно вверху, где постепенно проступал, размывая его размышления, фиалковый сумеречный воздух с серебристым оттиском потолочных флуоресцентных ламп, и среди черных паучьих сучьев отражалась шеренга ярких книжных корешков.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="67">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Before leaving the library, he decided to look up the correct pronunciation of 'interested', and discovered that Webster, or at least the battered 1930 edition lying on a table in the Browsing Room, did not place the stress accent on the third syllable, as he did.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Прежде чем покинуть библиотеку, он решил проверить, как произносится слово "interested", и обнаружил, что Уэбстер или по крайней мере его потрепанное издание 1930 года, лежавшее на столе в справочном зале, помещает ударение не на третий слог, - в отличие от него.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="68">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He sought a list of errata at the back, failed to find one, and, upon closing the elephantine lexicon, realized with a pang that he had immured somewhere in it the index card with notes that he had been holding all this time.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Пнин поискал в конце список опечаток, не нашел такового и, закрыв слоноподобный словарь, с внезапным страхом сообразил, что где-то внутри его осталась в заточении справочная карточка с заметками, которую он так и держал в руке.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="69">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Must now search and search through 2,500 thin pages, some torn!</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Теперь придется искать и искать - среди 2500 тонких страниц, из которых иные разорваны!</se>
  </para>
  <para id="70">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">On hearing his interjection, suave Mr Case, a lank, pink-faced librarian with sleek white hair and a bow-tie, strolled up, took up the colossus by both ends, inverted it, and gave it a slight shake, whereupon it shed a pocket comb, a Christmas card, Pnin's notes, and a gauzy wraith of tissue paper, which descended with infinite listlessness to Pnin's feet and was replaced by Mr Case on the Great Seals of the United States and Territories.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Услышав его восклицание, учтивый м-р Кейс - долговязый, розоволицый библиотекарь с прилизанными белыми волосами и в галстуке-бабочкой - приблизился, приподнял колосса за обложки, перевернул и слегка встряхнул, отчего тот извергнул карманный гребешок, рождественскую открытку, заметки Пнина и призрачно-прозрачный листок папиросной бумаги, который с бесконечной медлительностью ниспал к ногам Пнина и был затем водворен м-ром Кейсом поверх Больших Печатей Соединенных Штатов и Их Территорий.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="71">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Pnin pocketed his index card and, while doing so, recalled without any prompting what he had not been able to recall a while ago:</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Пнин уложил справочную карточку в карман и при этом безо всякой подсказки вспомнил то, чего не сумел припомнить недавно:</se>
  </para>
  <para id="72">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">...plГЇla i pela, pela i plГЇla...</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">"... плыла и пела, пела и плыла..."</se>
  </para>
  <para id="73">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">...she floated and she sang, she sang and floatedвЂ¦</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1"></se>
  </para>
  <para id="74">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Of course!</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Конечно!</se>
  </para>
  <para id="75">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Ophelia's death!</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Смерть Офелии!</se>
  </para>
  <para id="76">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Hamlet!</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">"Гамлет"!</se>
  </para>
  <para id="77">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">In good old Andrey Kroneberg's Russian translation, 1844 вЂ” the joy of Pain's youth, and of his father's and grandfather's young days!</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">В добром старом русском переводе Андрея Кронеберга 1844 года, бывшем отрадой юности Пнина, и его отца и деда!</se>
  </para>
  <para id="78">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">And here, as in the Kostromskoy passage, there is, we recollect, also a willow and also wreaths.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">И здесь, так же как в пассаже Костромского, присутствуют, как помнится, ивы и венки.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="79">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">But where to check properly?</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Где бы, однако, это проверить как следует?</se>
  </para>
  <para id="80">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Alas, 'Gamlet' Vil'yama Shekspira had not been acquired by Mr Todd, was not represented in Waindell College Library, and whenever you were reduced to look up something in the English version, you never found this or that beautiful, noble, sonorous line that you remembered all your life from Kroneberg's text in Vengerov's splendid edition.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Увы, "Гамлет" Вильяма Шекспира не был приобретен мистером Тоддом, он отсутствовал в библиотеке вайнделлского колледжа, а сколько бы раз вы не выискивали что-либо в английской версии, вам никогда не приходилось встречать той или другой благородной, прекрасной, звучной строки, которая на всю жизнь врезалась в вашу память при чтении текста Кронеберга в великолепном издании Венгерова.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="81">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Sad!</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Печально!</se>
  </para>
  <para id="82">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">It was getting quite dark on the sad campus.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Уже совсем стемнело в печальном кампусе.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="83">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Above the distant, still sadder hills there lingered, under a cloud bank, a depth of tortoise-shell sky.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Над дальними, еще более печальными холмами замешкалось под кучами туч небо густого черепашьего цвета.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="84">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">The heart-rending lights of Waindellville, throbbing in a fold of those dusky hills, were putting on their usual magic, though actually, as Pnin well knew, the place, when you got there, was merely a row of brick houses, a service station, a skating rink, a supermarket.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Душераздирающие огни Вайнделлвилля дрожали в складке этих сумеречных холмов и, по обыкновению, притворялись волшебными, хотя в действительности, как хорошо знал Пнин, городок, ежели до него добраться, окажется всего лишь шеренгой кирпичных домов, с заправочной станцией, катком и супермаркетом.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="85">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">As he walked to the little tavern in Library Lane for a large portion of Virginia ham and a good bottle of beer, Pnin suddenly felt very tired.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Шагая к маленькой таверне на Лайбрери-лэйн, к большой порции виргинской ветчины и доброй бутылке пива, Пнин внезапно ощутил ужасную усталость.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="86">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Not only had the Zol.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Не только том "Зол.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="87">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Fond tome become even heavier after its unnecessary visit to the library, but something that Pnin had half heard in the course of the day, and had been reluctant to follow up, now bothered and oppressed him, as does, in retrospection, a blunder we have made, a piece of rudeness we have allowed ourselves, or a threat we have chosen to ignore.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Фонда" отяжелел после ненужного посещения библиотеки, но и что-то еще, днем пропущенное Пниным мимо ушей, теперь томило и тяготило его, как тяготят нас задним числом глупости, которые мы совершили, грубости, до которых себя допустили, или угрозы, которыми предпочли пренебречь.</se>
  </para>
</body>
</html>
