<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<html>
<head>
</head>
<body>
  <para id="0">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">13</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">13</se>
  </para>
  <para id="1">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">From the sideboard and dining-room table Pnin removed to the kitchen sink the used china and silverware.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">С буфета и из гостиной Пнин перенес в кухонную раковину грязную посуду и столовое серебро.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="2">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He put away what food remained into the bright Arctic light of the refrigerator.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Он поместил оставшуюся снедь в холодильник, под яркий арктический свет.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="3">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">The ham and tongue had all gone, and so had the little sausages; but the vinaigrette had not been a success, and enough caviare and meat tarts were left over for a meal or two tomorrow.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Ветчину и язык съели начисто, также и маленькие сосиски, но винегрет успеха не имел, сохранилось, кроме того, довольно икры и мясных пирожков, чтобы завтра можно было перекусить раз-другой.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="4">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'Boom-boom-boom,' said the china closet as he passed by.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">"Бум-бум-бум", - сказал буфет, когда он проходил мимо. </se>
  </para>
  <para id="5">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He surveyed the living-room and started to tidy it up.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1"></se>
  </para>
  <para id="6">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">A last drop of Pnin's Punch glistened in its beautiful bowl Joan had crooked a lipstick-stained cigarette butt in her saucer; Betty had left no trace and had taken all the glasses back to the kitchen.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Последняя капля Пнин-пунша сверкала в прекрасной чаше. Джоан раздавила в тарелке вымазанный губной помадой сигаретный окурок. Бетти следов не оставила и даже снесла все бокалы на кухню.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="7">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Mrs Thayer had forgotten a booklet of pretty multi-coloured matches on her plate, next to a bit of nougat.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Миссис Тейер забыла на тарелке, рядом с кусочком нуги, хорошенький буклет разноцветных спичек.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="8">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Mr Thayer had twisted into all kinds of weird shapes half a dozen paper napkins; Hagen had quenched a messy cigar in an uneaten bunchlet of grapes.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Мистер Тейер скрутил с полдюжины бумажных салфеток, придав им самые прихотливые очертания. Гаген загасил растрепанную сигару о несъеденную кисть винограда.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="9">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">In the kitchen, Pnin prepared to wash up the dishes.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Перейдя в кухню, Пнин изготовился мыть посуду.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="10">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He removed his silk coat, his tie, and his dentures.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Он снял шелковую куртку, галстук и челюсти.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="11">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">To protect his shirt front and tuxedo trousers, he donned a soubrette's dappled apron.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Для защиты рубашки и смокинговых брюк он надел субреточный пятнистый передник.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="12">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He scraped various titbits off the plates into a brown paper bag, to be given eventually to a mangy little white dog, with pink patches on its back, that visited him sometimes in the afternoon вЂ” there was no reason a human's misfortune should interfere with a canine's pleasure.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Он соскоблил с тарелок в бумажный мешок лакомые кусочки, чтобы после отдать их белой чесоточной собачонке с розовыми пятнами на спине, которая иногда заходила к нему под вечер, - ибо не существует причин, по которым несчастье человека должно лишать радости собаку.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="13">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He prepared a bubble bath in the sink for the crockery, glass, and silverware, and with infinite care lowered the aquamarine bowl into the tepid foam.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Он приготовил в мойке мыльную ванну для тарелок, бокалов и серебра и с бесконечной осторожностью опустил аквамариновую чашу в тепловатую пену.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="14">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Its resonant flint glass emitted a sound full of muffled mellowness as it settled down to soak.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Оседая и набирая воду, звучный флинтглас запел приглушенно и мягко.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="15">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He rinsed the amber goblets and the silverware under the tap, and submerged them in the same foam.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Пнин ополоснул под краном янтарные бокалы и серебро и погрузил их туда же.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="16">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Then he fished out the knives, forks, and spoons, rinsed them, and began to wipe them.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Затем извлек ножи, вилки, ложки, промыл их и стал вытирать.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="17">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He worked very slowly, with a certain vagueness of manner that might have been taken for a mist of abstraction in a less methodical man.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Работал он очень медленно, с некоторой размытостью движений, которая в человеке менее обстоятельном могла бы показаться рассеянностью.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="18">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He gathered the wiped spoons into a posy, placed them in a pitcher which he had washed but not dried, and then took them out one by one and wiped them all over again.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Собрав протертые ложки в букетик, он поместил его в вымытый, но не вытертый кувшин, а затем стал доставать их оттуда и протирать одну за одной.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="19">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He groped under the bubbles, around the goblets, and under the melodious bowl, for any piece of forgotten silver вЂ” and retrieved a nutcracker.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">В поисках забытого серебра он пошарил под пузырями, среди бокалов и под мелодичной чашей, и выудил щипцы для орехов.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="20">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Fastidious Pnin rinsed it, and was wiping it, when the leggy thing somehow slipped out of the towel and fell like a man from a roof.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Привередливый Пнин обмыл их и принялся вытирать, как вдруг ногастая штука каким-то образом вывернулась из полотенца и рухнула вниз, точно человек, свалившийся с крыши.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="21">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He almost caught it вЂ” his fingertips actually came into contact with it in mid-air, but this only helped to propel it into the treasure-concealing foam of the sink, where an excruciating crack of broken glass followed upon the plunge.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Пнин почти поймал щипцы, пальцы коснулись их на лету, но лишь протолкнули в укрывшую сокровище пену и за нырком оттуда донесся мучительный клекот бьющегося стекла.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="22">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Pnin hurled the towel into a comer and, turning away stood for a moment staring at the blackness beyond the threshold of the open back door.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Пнин швырнул полотенце в угол и, отвернувшись, с минуту простоял, глядя в темноту за порогом распахнутой задней двери.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="23">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">A quiet, lacy-winged little green insect circled in the glare of a strong naked lamp above Pnin's glossy bald head.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Зеленое насекомое, крохотное и беззвучное, кружило на кружевных крыльях в сиянии яркой голой лампы, висевшей над лоснистой лысой головою Пнина.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="24">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He looked very old, with his toothless mouth half open and a film of tears dimming his blank, unblinking eyes.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Он выглядел очень старым - с приоткрытым беззубым ртом и пеленою слез, замутившей пустые, немигающие глаза.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="25">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Then, with a moan of anguished anticipation, he went back to the sink and, bracing himself, dipped his hand deep into the foam.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Наконец, застонав от мучительного предчувствия, он повернулся к раковине и, собравшись с силами, глубоко погрузил в воду руку.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="26">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">A jagger of glass stung him.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Осколок стекла укусил его в палец.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="27">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Gently he removed a broken goblet.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Он осторожно вынул разбитый бокал.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="28">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">The beautiful bowl was intact.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Прекрасная чаша была невредима.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="29">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He took a fresh dish towel and went on with his household work.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Взяв свежее кухонное полотенце, Пнин продолжил хозяйственные труды.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="30">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">When everything was clean and dry, and the bowl stood aloof and serene on the safest shelf of a cupboard, and the little bright house was securely locked up in the large dark night. Pnin sat down at the kitchen table and, taking a sheet of yellow scrap paper from its drawer, unclipped his fountain pen and started to compose the draft of a letter:</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Когда все было вымыто и вытерто, и чаша, отчужденная и безмятежная, стояла на самой надежной полке буфета, и маленький яркий дом был накрепко заперт в огромной ночи, Пнин присел за кухонный стол и, достав из его ящика листок желтоватой макулатурной бумаги, расцепил автоматическое перо и принялся составлять черновик письма:</se>
  </para>
  <para id="31">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'Dear Hagen,' he wrote in his clear firm hand, 'permit me to recaputilate (crossed out) recapitulate the conversation we had tonight.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">"Дорогой Гаген, - писал он ясным и твердым почерком, позвольте мне ремюзировать (зачеркнуто) резюмировать разговор, состоявшийся нынче ночью.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="32">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">It, I must confess, somewhat astonished me.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Должен признаться, он отчасти меня поразил.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="33">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">If I had the honour to correctly understand you, you said вЂ” '</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Если я имел честь правильно вас понять, вы сказали..."</se>
  </para>
</body>
</html>
