<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<html>
<head>
</head>
<body>
  <para id="0">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">9</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">9</se>
  </para>
  <para id="1">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">By ten o'clock, Pnin's Punch and Betty's Scotch were causing some of the guests to talk louder than they thought they did.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">К десяти часам Пнин-пунш и Бетти-скотч вынудили кое-кого из гостей разговаривать громче, чем они о себе полагали.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="2">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">A carmine flush had spread over one side of Mrs Thayer's neck, under the little blue star of her left ear-ring, and, sitting very straight, she regaled her host with an account of the feud between two of her co-workers at the library.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Алое зарево разливалось с одной стороны по шее миссис Тейер • под синей звездой ее левой серьги; сидя навытяжку, она потчевала хозяина рассказом о распре между двумя ее сослуживцами.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="3">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">It was a simple office story, but her changes of tone from Miss Shrill to Mr Basso, and the consciousness of the soiree going on so nicely, made Pain bend his head and guffaw ecstatically behind his hand.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Это была простенькая конторская история, однако тональные переходы от мисс Визг к мистеру Бассо и сознание того, как замечательно протекает вечер, заставляли Пнина пригибаться и восторженно гоготать, прикрываясь ладонью.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="4">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Roy Thayer was weakly twinkling to himself as he looked into his Punch, down his grey porous nose, and politely listened to Joan Cements who, when she was a little high as she was now, had a fetching way of rapidly blinking, or even completely dosing her black-lashed blue eyes, and of interrupting her sentences, to punctuate a clause or gather new momentum, by deep hawing pants: 'But don't you think вЂ” haw вЂ” that what he is trying to do вЂ” haw вЂ” practically in all his novels вЂ” haw вЂ” is вЂ” haw вЂ” to express the fantastic recurrence of certain situations?' Betty remained her controlled little self, and expertly looked after the refreshments.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Рой Тейер слабо помаргивал, глядя вдоль серого пористого носа в свой пунш и вежливо слушая Джоан Клементс, у которой, когда она бывала, как нынче, навеселе, появлялась соблазнительное обыкновение перемаргивать, а то и совсем закрывать синие в черных ресницах глаза и прерывать свои речи, - дабы выделить оговорку или собраться с мыслями, - глубокими придыханиями ("хо-о-о"): "Но не кажется ли вам - хо-о-о - что то, что он пытается сделать - хо-о-о - практически во всех своих романах - хо-о-о - это - хо-о-о - выразить фантасмагорическую повторяемость определенных положений?". Бетти сохранила свое управляемое маленькое "я" и со знанием дела пеклась о закусках.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="5">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">In the bay end of the room, Clements kept morosely revolving the slow globe as Hagen, carefully avoiding the traditional intonations he would have used in more congenial surroundings, told him and grinning Thomas the latest story about Mrs Idelson, communicated by Mrs Blorenge to Mrs Hagen.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">В том конце комнаты, где помещалась ниша, Клементс угрюмо вращал неповоротливый глобус, а Гаген, старательно избегая традиционных интонаций, к которым он прибегнул бы в более свойской компании, рассказывал ему и ухмылявшемуся Томасу свежий анекдот о мадам Идельсон, слышанный миссис Гаген от миссис Блорендж.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="6">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Pnin came up with a plate of nougat.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Подошел Пнин с тарелкой нуги.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="7">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'This is not quite for your chaste ears, Timofey,' said Hagen to Pnin, who always confessed he never could see the point of any' scabrous anecdote'. 'However вЂ” '</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">- Это не вполне для ваших непорочных ушей, Тимофей, сказал Гаген Пнину, который всегда признавался, что не видит соли ни в одном из "скабрезных анекдотов", - однако...</se>
  </para>
  <para id="8">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Clements moved away to rejoin the ladies.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Клементс перебрался поближе к дамам.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="9">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Hagen began to retell the story, and Thomas began to re-grin.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Гаген начал рассказывать историю заново, Томас • заново ухмыляться.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="10">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Pnin waved a hand at the raconteur in a Russian disgusted 'oh-go-on-with-you' gesture and said:</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Пнин ладонью брезгливо отмахнулся от рассказчика - "да ну вас" - и сказал:</se>
  </para>
  <para id="11">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'I have heard quite the same anecdote thirty-five years ago in Odessa, and even then I could not understand what is comical in it.'</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">- Я слышал этот же самый анекдот лет тридцать пять назад в Одессе и даже тогда не смог понять, что в нем смешного.</se>
  </para>
</body>
</html>
