<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<html>
<head>
</head>
<body>
  <para id="0">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">6</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">6</se>
  </para>
  <para id="1">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">When I decided to accept a professorship at Waindell, I stipulated that I could invite whomever I wanted for teaching in the special Russian Division I planned to inaugurate.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Решившись принять профессорство в Вайнделле, я оговорил возможность пригласить кого сочту необходимым для преподавания в особом русском отделении, которое я собирался учредить.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="2">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">With this confirmed, I wrote to Timofey Pain offering him, in the most cordial terms I could muster, to assist me in any way and to any extent he desired.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Получив согласие, я написал Тимофею Пнину в самых сердечных выражениях, какие смог подобрать, предлагая ему помочь мне любым способом и в любой степени, для него удобных.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="3">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">His answer surprised me and hurt me.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Его ответ удивил и обидел меня.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="4">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Curtly he wrote that he was through with teaching and would not even bother to wait till the end of the spring term. Then he turned to other subjects.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Он коротко написал, что покончил с преподаванием и не намерен даже дожидаться конца весеннего семестра, - после чего обратился к иным предметам.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="5">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Victor (about whom I had politely inquired) was in Rome with his mother; she had divorced her third husband and married an Italian art dealer.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Виктор (о котором я из учтивости справился) живет с матерью в Риме; она развелась с третьим мужем и вышла за итальянского торговца картинами.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="6">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Pain concluded his letter by saying that to his great regret he would be leaving Waindell two or three days before the public lecture that I was to give there Tuesday, February the fifteenth.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Пнин закончил письмо сообщением, что к его величайшему сожалению ему придется покинуть Вайнделл за два-три дня до публичной лекции, которую мне предстояло прочесть во вторник пятнадцатого февраля.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="7">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He did not specify his destination.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Места своего назначения он не назвал.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="8">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">The Greyhound that brought me to Waindell on Monday the fourteenth arrived after nightfall.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">"Грейхаунд", который привез меня в Вайнделл в понедельник четырнадцатого, пришел туда уже затемно.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="9">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">I was met by the Cockerells, who treated me to a late supper at their house, where I discovered I was to spend the night, instead of sleeping at a hotel as I had hoped.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Меня встретили Кокереллы и пригласили на поздний ужин к себе домой, и получилось, что я заночевал у них - вместо того, чтобы отоспаться в отеле, каково было первоначальное мое намерение.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="10">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Gwen Cockerell turned out to be a very pretty woman in her late thirties, with a kitten's profile and graceful limbs.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Гвен Кокерелл оказалась очень хорошенькой женщиной сильно за тридцать, с профилем котенка и с грациозными членами.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="11">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Her husband, whom I had once met in New Haven and remembered as a rather limp, moon-faced, neutrally blond Englishman, had acquired an unmistakable resemblance to the man he had now been mimicking for almost ten years.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Ее муж, с которым я однажды уже встречался в Нью-Хейвене и которого запомнил как довольно вялого, луноликого, невыразительного и белесого англичанина, приобрел с тех пор безошибочное сходство с человеком, которого он передразнивал почти уже десять лет.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="12">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">I was tired and not over-anxious to be entertained throughout the supper with a floor show, but I must admit that Jack Cockerell impersonated Pnin to perfection.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Я устал и не был особенно склонен развлекаться застольным спектаклем, однако должен признать, что Джек Кокерелл изображал Пнина в совершенстве.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="13">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He went on for at least two hours, showing me everything вЂ” Pnin teaching, Pain eating, Pnin ogling a co-ed, Pain narrating the epic of the electric fan which he had imprudently set going on a glass shelf right above the bathtub into which its own vibration had almost caused it to fall; Pnin trying to convince Professor Wynn, the ornithologist who hardly knew him, that they were old pals, Tim and Tom вЂ” and Wynn leaping to the conclusion that this was somebody impersonating Professor Pnin.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Его хватило чуть не на два часа, он показал мне все - Пнина на лекции, Пнина за едой, Пнина, строящего глазки студентке, Пнина, излагающего эпопею с электрическим вентилятором, который он неосмотрительно водрузил на стеклянную полку над ванной, в которую тот едва не слетел, потрясенный собственными вибрациями; Пнина, пытающегося убедить профессора Уинна, орнитолога, едва с ним знакомого, что они - старые друзья, Том и Тим, и Уинна, приходящего к заключению, что он имеет дело с кем-то, изображающим профессора Пнина.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="14">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">It was all built, of course, around the Pninian gesture and the Pninian wild English, but Cockerell also managed to imitate such things as the subtle degree of difference between the silence of Pnin and the silence of Thayer, as they sat motionlessly ruminating in adjacent chairs at the Faculty Club.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Все это строилось, разумеется, на жестикуляции и диком английском Пнина, впрочем, Кокерелл ухитрялся передавать и такие тонкости, как различие между молчанием Пнина и молчанием Тейера, когда они сидят, погрузившись в раздумья, в соседних креслах преподавательского клуба.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="15">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">We got Pnin in the Stacks, and Pnin on the Campus Lake.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Мы получили Пнина в книгохранилище и Пнина на озере в кампусе.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="16">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">We heard Pnin criticize the various rooms he had successively rented.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Мы услышали, как Пнин порицает различные комнаты, которые он поочередно снимал.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="17">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">We listened to Pnin's account of his learning to drive a car, and of his dealing with his first puncture on the way back from' the chicken farm of some Privy Counsellor of the Tsar', where Cockerell supposed Pnin spent the summers.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Мы выслушали рассказ Пнина о том, как он учился водить машину, а также о его действиях при первом проколе шины - на пути с "птицефермы какого-то Тайного Советника Царя", где, как полагал Кокерелл, Пнин проводил летние отпуска.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="18">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">We arrived at last at Pnin's declaration one day that he had been' shot', by which, according to the impersonator, the poor fellow meant 'fired' вЂ” (a mistake I doubt my friend could have made).</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Мы добрались, наконец, до сделанного Пниным заявления о том, что его "выстрелили" (shot), под чем, согласно имитатору, бедняга разумел "выставили" (fired), - я сомневаюсь, чтобы мой бедный друг мог впасть в такую ошибку.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="19">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Brilliant Cockerell also told of the strange feud between Pnin and his compatriot Komarov вЂ” the mediocre muralist who had kept adding fresco portraits of faculty members in the college dining hall to those already depicted there by the great Lang.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Блестящий Кокерелл поведал нам также о странной распре между Пниным и его соплеменником Комаровым - посредственным стенописцем, продолжавшим добавлять фресковые портреты преподавателей колледжа к тем, что уже были когда-то написаны на стенах университетской столовой великим Лангом.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="20">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Although Komarov belonged to another political faction than Pnin, the patriotic artist had seen in Pnin's dismissal an anti-Russian gesture and had started to delete a. sulky Napoleon that stood between young, plumpish (now gaunt) Blorenge and young, moustached (now shaven) Hagen, in order to paint in Pnin; and there was the scene between Pnin and President Poore at lunch вЂ” an enraged, spluttering Pnin losing all control over what English he had, pointing a shaking forefinger at the preliminary outlines of a ghostly muzhik on the wall, and shouting that he would sue the college if his face appeared above that blouse; and there was his audience, imperturbable Poore, trapped in the dark of his total blindness, waiting for Pnin to peter out and then asking at large: 'Is that foreign gentleman on our staff?' Dh, the impersonation was deliciously funny, and although Gwen Cockerell must have heard the programme many times before, she laughed so loud that their old dog Sobakevich, a brown cocker with a tear-stained face, began to fidget and sniff at me.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Хотя Комаров принадлежал к иному, нежели Пнин, политическому течению, художник-патриот усмотрел в удалении Пнина антирусский выпад и принялся соскребать хмурого Наполеона, стоявшего между молодым, полнотелым (ныне костлявым) Блоренджем и молодым, усатым (ныне бритым) Гагеном, намереваясь вписать туда Пнина; была показана и сцена во время ленча между Пниным и ректором Пуром: разгневанный, пузырящийся Пнин, утративший всякий контроль над тем английским, каким он владел, тыкал трясущимся пальцем в зачаточный очерк призрачного мужика на стене и вопил, что будет судиться с колледжем, если его лицо появится над этой косовороткой; здесь была и его аудитория - непроницаемый Пур, объятый тьмой своей слепоты, ожидающий, когда Пнин иссякнет, чтобы громко спросить: "А этот иностранный господин тоже у нас работает?". О, имитация была бесподобно смешной, и хоть Гвен Кокерелл, надо полагать, слышала программу множество раз, она хохотала так громко, что старый пес Собакевич, коричневый кокер с залитым слезами лицом, принялся ерзать и принюхиваться ко мне.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="21">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">The performance, I repeat, was magnificent, but it was too long.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Представление, повторяю, было блестящим, но чрезмерно затянутым.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="22">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">By midnight the fun began to thin; the smile I was keeping afloat began to develop, I felt, symptoms of labial cramp.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">К полуночи веселье выдохлось; улыбка, которую я держал на плаву, приобретала, чувствовал я, признаки губной спазмы.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="23">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Finally, the whole thing grew to be such a bore that I fell wondering if by some poetical vengeance this Pnin business had not become with Cockerell the kind of fatal obsession which substitutes its own victim for that of the initial ridicule.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">В конце концов, все выродилось в такую скуку, что я уже начал гадать, не стало ль для Кокерелла его занятие Пниным - в силу некоего поэтического возмездия - своего рода роковым помешательством, замещающим исходное посмешище собственной жертвой.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="24">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">We had been having a good deal of Scotch, and sometime after midnight Cockerell made one of those sudden decisions that seem so bright and gay at a certain stage of intoxication.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Мы выпили порядочное количество виски, и где-то после полуночи Кокерелл принял одно из тех внезапных решений, которые - в определенном градусе опьянения - кажутся столь осмысленными и смешными.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="25">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He said he was sure foxy old Pnin had not really left yesterday, but was lying low.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Он объявил о своей уверенности в том, что старая лиса Пнин никуда вчера не уехал, а забился поглубже в нору.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="26">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">So why not telephone and find out?</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Так отчего бы не позвонить и не проверить?</se>
  </para>
  <para id="27">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He made the call, and although there was no answer to the series of compelling notes which simulate the far sound of actual ringing in an imaginary hallway, it stood to reason that this perfectly healthy telephone would have been probably disconnected, had Pnin really vacated the house.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Он и позвонил, и хоть ответа на вереницу настойчивых нот, изображающих действительный звон в воображаемой далекой прихожей, не последовало, представлялось разумным, что этот совершенно нормальный телефон, уж верно, отключили бы, если бы Пнин и вправду освободил дом.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="28">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">I was foolishly eager to say something friendly to my good Timofey Pahlich, and so after a little while I attempted to reach him too.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Я по-дурацки рвался сказать что-то дружеское моему доброму Тимофей Палычу, так что, спустя несколько времени, тоже попробовал дозвониться.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="29">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Suddenly there was a click, a sonic vista, the response of a heavy breathing, and then a poorly disguised voice said: 'He is not at home, he has gone, he has quite gone' вЂ” after which the speaker hung up; but none save my old friend, not even his best imitator, could rhyme so emphatically 'at' with the German 'hat', 'home' with the French 'homme', and 'gone' with the head of 'Goneril'.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Внезапно раздался щелчок, открылась звуковая перспектива, отзвук тяжелого дыхания, и неумело искаженный голос сказал: "He is not at home, he has gone, he has quite gone" ("Его нет дома, он ушел, он совсем ушел"), - и трубку повесили; однако, это не спасло моего старого друга, ибо и лучший его подражатель не смог бы столь подчеркнуто срифмовать "at" с немецким "hat", "home" с французским "homme" и "gone" с началом "Гонерильи".</se>
  </para>
  <para id="30">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Cockerell then proposed driving over to 999 Todd Road and serenading its burrowed tenant, but here Mrs Cockerell intervened; and after an evening that somehow left me with the mental counterpart of a bad taste in the mouth, we all went to bed.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Кокерелл предложил подъехать к дому 999 по Тодд-роуд и спеть окопавшемуся там Пнину серенаду, но тут уж вмешалась миссис Кокерелл, и после вечера, почему-то оставившего в моей душе подобие дрянного привкуса во рту, мы отправились спать.</se>
  </para>
</body>
</html>
