<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<html>
<head>
</head>
<body>
  <para id="0">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">3</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">3</se>
  </para>
  <para id="1">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">The organs concerned in the production of English speech sounds are the larynx, the velum, the lips, the tongue {that punchinello in the troupe), and, last but not least, the lower jaw; mainly upon its over-energetic and somewhat ruminant motion did Pnin rely when translating in class passages in the Russian grammar or some poem by Pushkin.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Органами, отвечающими за порождение звуков английской речи, являются: гортань, небо, губы, язык (пульчинелла этой труппы) и последнее (по порядку, но не по значению) - нижняя челюсть; на ее-то сверхэнергические и отчасти жевательные движения и полагался главным образом Пнин, переводя на занятиях куски из русской грамматики или какое-нибудь стихотворение Пушкина.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="2">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">If his Russian was music, his English was murder.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Если его русский язык был музыкой, то английский - убийством.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="3">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He had enormous difficulty ('dzeefeecooltsee' in Pninian English) with depalatization, never managing to remove the extra Russian moisture from t's and d's before the vowels he so quaintly softened.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Особые затруднения ("дзи-ифи-икультси-и" на пниновском английском) были у него связаны со смягчением звуков, ему никак не удавалось устранить дополнительную русскую смазку из t и d, стоящих перед гласными, которые он столь причудливо умягчал.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="4">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">His explosive 'hat' ('I never go in a hat even in winter') differed from the common American pronunciation of 'hot' (typical of Waindell townspeople, for example) only by its briefer duration, and thus sounded very much like the German verb hat (has).</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Его взрывное "hat" ("I never go in hat even in winter")1 отличалось от общеамериканского выговора "hot" (типичного, скажем, для обитателей Вайнделла) лишь большей краткостью и оттого более походило на немецкий глагол "hat" (имеет).</se>
  </para>
  <para id="5">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Long o's with him inevitably became short ones: his 'no' sounded positively Italian, and this was accentuated by his trick of triplicating the simple negative ('May I give you a lift, Mr Pnin?' 'No-no-no, I have only two paces from here').</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Долгие "o" у него неукоснительно становились короткими: "no"2 звучало просто по-итальянски, что усиливалось его манерой утраивать это простое отрицание ("May I give you a lift, Mr Pnin?" - "No-no-no, I have only two paces from here"1).</se>
  </para>
  <para id="6">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He did not possess (nor was he aware of this lack) any long oo: all he could muster when called upon to utter 'noon' was the lax vowel of the German 'nun' ('I have no classes in afternun on Tuesday.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Он не умел (и не догадывался об этом) хоть как-то произносить долгое "у": единственное, что он мог смастерить, когда приходилось сказать "noon", это вялую гласную немецкого "nun" ("I have no classes in afternun on Tuesday.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="7">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Today is Tuesday.')</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Today is Tuesday"2).</se>
  </para>
  <para id="8">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Tuesday вЂ” true; but what day of the month, we wonder.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Вторник, верно; однако какое же сегодня число, вот что хотелось бы знать?</se>
  </para>
  <para id="9">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Pnin's birthday for instance fell on February 3, by the Julian calendar into which he had been born in St Petersburg in 1898. He never celebrated it nowadays, partly because, after his departure from Russia, it sidled by in a Gregorian disguise (thirteen вЂ” no, twelve days late), and partly because during the academic year he existed mainly on a motuweth frisas basis.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">День рождения Пнина, например, приходился на 3 февраля - по юлианскому календарю, в полном согласии с коим он в 1898 году родился в Петербурге. Теперь Пнин его больше не праздновал - отчасти потому, что после разлуки с Россией день этот как-то бочком проскакивал под григорианской личиной (тринадцатью, нет, двенадцатью днями позже), отчасти же потому, что на протяжении учебного года он жил в основном от понедельника до пятницы.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="10">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">On the chalk-clouded blackboard, which he wittily called the greyboard, he now wrote a date.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">На затуманенной мелом классной доске Пнин выписал дату.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="11">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">In the crook of his arm he still felt the bulk of Zol.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Сгиб его руки еще помнил тяжесть "ЗФЛ'а".</se>
  </para>
  <para id="12">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Fond Lit. The date he wrote had nothing to do with the day this was in Waindell:</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Дата, записанная им, ничего не имела общего с днем, ныне стоявшим в Вайнделле:</se>
  </para>
  <para id="13">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">December, 26, 1829</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">26 декабря 1829 года</se>
  </para>
  <para id="14">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He carefully drilled in a big white full stop, and added underneath:</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Он старательно навертел большую белую точку и прибавил пониже:</se>
  </para>
  <para id="15">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">3.03 p.m. St Petersburg</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">3.03 пополудни, Санкт-Петербург</se>
  </para>
  <para id="16">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Dutifully this was taken down by Frank Backman, Rose Balsamo, Frank Carroll, Irving D. Herz, beautiful, intelligent Marilyn Hohn, John Mead, Jr, Peter Volkov, and Allan Bradbury Walsh.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Все это усердно записывали: Фрэнк Бэкман, Роз Бальзамо, Фрэнк Кэрролл, Ирвинг Д. Герц, прекрасная и умная Мэрилин Хон, Джон Мид младший, Питер Волков и Аллен Брэдбери Уолш.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="17">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Pain, rippling with mute mirth, sat down again at his desk: he had a tale to tell.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Пнин, зыблясь в безмолвном веселье, вновь уселся за стол: у него имелась в запасе история.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="18">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">That line in the absurd Russian grammar, 'Brozhu li ya vdol' ulits shumnГЇh (Whether I wander along noisy streets),' was really the opening of a famous poem.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Эта строчка из дурацкой русской грамматики: "Брожу ли я вдоль улиц шумных" ("Whether I wander along noisy streets"), является на самом деле первой строкой знаменитого стихотворения.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="19">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Although Pain was supposed in this Elementary Russian class to stick to language exercises ('Mama, telefon!</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Хоть и предполагалось, что Пнин на занятиях по начальному русскому курсу должен придерживаться простых языковых упражнений ("Мама, телефон!</se>
  </para>
  <para id="20">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Brozhu li ya vdol' ulits shumnГЇh.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Брожу ли я вдоль улиц шумных.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="21">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Ot Vladivostoka do Vashingtona 5000 mil'.'), he took every opportunity to guide his students on literary and historical tours.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">От Владивостока до Вашингтона 5000 миль"), он не упускал случая увлечь своих студентов на литературную и историческую экскурсию.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="22">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">In a set of eight tetrametric quatrains Pushkin described the morbid habit he always had вЂ” wherever he was, whatever he was doing вЂ” of dwelling on thoughts of death and of closely inspecting every passing day as he strove to find in its cryptogram a certain 'future anniversary': the day and month that would appear, somewhere, sometime upon his tombstone.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">В восьми четырехстопных четверостишиях Пушкин описал болезненную привычку, не покидавшую его никогда, - где бы он ни был, что бы ни делал, - привычку сосредоточенно размышлять о смерти, пристально вглядываясь в каждый мимолетящий день, стараясь угадать в его тайнописи некую "грядущую годовщину": день и месяц, которые обозначатся когда-нибудь и где-нибудь на его гробовом камне.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="23">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">"And where will fate send me", imperfective future, "death",' declaimed inspired Pain, throwing his head back and translating with brave literality, '"in fight, in travel, or in waves?</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">- "And where will fate send me", несовершенное будущее, "death"3, - декламировал вдохновенный Пнин, откидывая голову и переводя с отважным буквализмом, - "in fight, in travel or in waves?</se>
  </para>
  <para id="24">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Or will the neighbouring dale" вЂ” dolina, same word, "valley" we would now say вЂ” "accept my refrigerated ashes", poussiГЁre, "cold dust" perhaps more correct.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Or will the neighbouring dale"4 - то же, что "долина", теперь мы сказали бы "valley", - "accept my refrigerated ashes"5, poussiиre, "cold dust"6, возможно, вернее.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="25">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">And though it is indifferent to the insensible bodyвЂ¦"'</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">"And though it is indifferent to the insensible body"7...</se>
  </para>
  <para id="26">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Pnin went on to the end and then, dramatically pointing with the piece of chalk he still held, remarked how carefully Pushkin had noted the day and even the minute of writing down that poem.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Пнин добрался до конца и тогда, театрально ткнув в доску куском мела, который продолжал держать в руке, отметил, с какой тщательностью Пушкин указал день и даже минуту, когда было записано это стихотворение.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="27">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'But,' exclaimed Pnin in triumph, 'he died on a quite, quite different day!</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">- Однако, - вскричал Пнин, - он умер совсем, совсем в другой день! Он умер...</se>
  </para>
  <para id="28">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He died вЂ” ' The chair back against which Pnin was vigorously leaning emitted an ominous crack, and the class resolved a pardonable tension in loud young laughter.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">- Спинка стула, на которую с силой налег Пнин зловеще треснула, и вполне понятное напряжение класса разрядилось в молодом громком смехе.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="29">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">(Sometime, somewhere вЂ” Petersburg? Prague? вЂ” one of the two musical clowns pulled out the piano stool from under the other, who remained, however, playing on, in a seated, though seatless, position, with his rhapsody unimpaired.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">(Когда-то, где-то - в Петербурге, в Праге? - один из двух музыкальных клоунов вытянул из-под другого рояльный стул, а тот, все играл в сидячей, хоть и лишенной сидения позе, не попортив своей рапсодии.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="30">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Where?</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Где же?</se>
  </para>
  <para id="31">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Circus Busch, Berlin!)</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Цирк Буша в Берлине!)</se>
  </para>
</body>
</html>
