<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<html>
<head>
</head>
<body>
  <para id="0">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">4</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">4</se>
  </para>
  <para id="1">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">For Pnin, who was totally unaware of his protector's woes, the new Fall Term began particularly well: he had never had so few students to bother about, or so much time for his own research.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Для Пнина, ничего не ведавшего о печалях своего покровителя, новый осенний семестр начался очень удачно: у него никогда еще не было ни столь малого числа студентов на попечении, ни столь большого количества времени для собственных изысканий.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="2">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">This research had long entered the charmed stage when the quest overrides the goal, and a new organism is formed, the parasite so to speak of the ripening fruit.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Изыскания эти давно уже вошли в ту чудесную стадию, когда они достигают поставленной прежде цели и уходят дальше, и формируется новый организм, так сказать, паразитирующий на созревающем плоде.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="3">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Pnin averted his mental gaze from the end of his work, which was so clearly in sight that one could make out the rocket of an asterisk, the flare of a 'sic!' This line of land was to be shunned as the doom of everything that determined the rapture of endless approximation.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Пнин отвращал умственный взор от конца работы, который был виден настолько ясно, что различалась даже звездчатая шутиха, воспламененное "sic!"1. Этого берега следовало избегать, как места, гибельного для восторгов бесконечного приближения.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="4">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Index cards were gradually loading a shoe box with their compact weight.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Справочные карточки постепенно плотной массой утяжеляли обувную коробку.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="5">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">The collation of two legends; a precious detail in manners or dress; a reference checked and found to be falsified by incompetence, carelessness, or fraud; the spine thrill of a felicitous guess; and all the innumerable triumphs of bezkorГЇstnГЇy (disinterested, devoted) scholarship вЂ” this had corrupted Pnin, this had made of him a happy, footnote-drugged maniac who disturbs the book mites in a dull volume, a foot thick, to find in it a reference to an even duller one.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Сопоставление двух преданий; драгоценные частности нравов или нарядов; ссылка, проверенная и оказавшаяся извращенной неведеньем, небрежностью или обманом; дрожь в хребте от счастливой догадки; все эти бесчисленные триумфы бескорыстной учености растлили Пнина, обратив его в упоенного, опоенного сносками маниака, что возмущает покой книжных клещей, мирно живущих в унылом томе в фут толщиной, единственно для того, чтобы сыскать в нем ссылку на том, еще пуще унылый.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="6">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">And on another, more human, plane there was the little brick house that he had rented on Todd Road, at the comer of Cliff Avenue.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">А на ином, более человеческом уровне, помещался кирпичный домик, снятый им на Тодд-роуд, угол Клифф-авеню.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="7">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">It had lodged the family of the late Martin Sheppard, an uncle of Pnin's previous landlord in Creek Street and for many years the caretaker of the Todd property, which the town of Waindell had now acquired for the purpose of turning its rambling mansion into a modem nursing home.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Прежде этот дом населяло семейство покойного Мартина Шеппарда, дядюшки предыдущего домохозяина Пнина на Крик-стрит, в течение многих лет управлявшего землями Тодда, которые город Вайнделл ныне скупил, дабы оборудовать в стоящей на них разбросанной усадьбе современную лечебницу.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="8">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Ivy and spruce muffled its locked gate, whose top Pnin could see on the far side of Cliff A venue from a north window of his new home.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Ели и плющ укутали запертые ворота усадьбы, верхушку которых Пнин мог видеть в конце Клифф-авеню из северного окна своего нового дома.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="9">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">This avenue was the crossbar of a T, in the left crotch of which he dwelt.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Авеню составляла поперечину буквы "Т", в левой развилке которой и обитал Пнин.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="10">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Opposite the front of his house, immediately across Todd Road (the upright of the T), old elms screened the sandy shoulder of its patched-up asphalt from a cornfield east of it, while along its west side a regiment of young fir trees, identical upstarts, walked, campusward, behind a fence, for almost the whole distance to the next residence вЂ” the Varsity Football Coach's magnified cigar box; which stood half a mile south from Pnin's house.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Насупротив его фронтона прямо через Тодд-роуд (образовавшей ножку "Т") старые ильмы отгораживали песчаную закраину ее латанного асфальта от кукурузного поля, лежащего к востоку, а вдоль западной обочины, за изгородью, подразделение молодых елей, одинаковых выскочек, маршировало к кампусу, немного не доходя до следующего дома - отстоящего почти на полмили к югу от дома Пнина увеличенного сигарного ящика, в котором жил тренер университетской футбольной команды.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="11">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">The sense of living in a discrete building all by himself was to Pnin something singularly delightful and amazingly satisfying to a weary old want of his innermost self, battered and stunned by thirty-five years of homelessness.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Ощущение жизни в отдельном доме и притом совершенно самостоятельной было для Пнина чем-то необычайно упоительным и поразительно утоляющим старую, усталую потребность его сокровенного "я", забитую и оглушенную почти тридцатью пятью годами бездомья.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="12">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">One of the sweetest things about the place was the silence вЂ” angelic, rural, and perfectly secure, thus in blissful contrast to the persistent cacophonies that had surrounded him from six sides in the rented rooms of his former habitations.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Одной из самых сладостных особенностей жилища была тишина - ангельская, деревенская, совершенно безмятежная, являющая, стало быть, благодатный контраст непрестанной какофонии, с шести сторон окружавшей его в наемных комнатах прежних пристанищ.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="13">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">And the tiny house was so spacious!</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">И как просторен казался маленький дом!</se>
  </para>
  <para id="14">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">With grateful surprise, Pnin thought that had there been no Russian Revolution, no exodus, no expatriation in France, no naturalization in America, everything вЂ” at the best, at the best, Timofey! вЂ” would have been much the same: a professorship in Kharkov or Kazan, a suburban house such as this, old books within, late blooms without.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">С благодарным изумлением Пнин думал, что не будь революции, бегства из России, экспатриации во Франции, натурализации в Америке, все - и это в лучшем случае, в лучшем, Тимофей! - все могло бы сложиться почти что так же: профессорство в Харькове или в Казани, такой же домик в предместье, старые книги внутри, запоздалые цветы снаружи.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="15">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">It was вЂ” to be more precise вЂ” a two-storey house of cherry-red brick, with white shutters and a shingle roof.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Дом, чтобы быть совсем уже точным, был двухэтажный, из вишнево-красного кирпича, с белыми ставнями и драночной кровлей.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="16">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">The green plat on which it stood had a frontage of about fifty arshins and was limited at the back by a vertical stretch of mossy cliff with tawny shrubs on its crest.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Зеленый лужок, посреди которого он стоял, образовал перед ним палисадник аршин в пятьдесят шириной, а за домом граничил с отвесным мшистым утесом, увенчанным изжелта-бурой порослью.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="17">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">A rudimentary driveway along the south side of the house led to a small whitewashed garage for the poor man's car Pnin owned.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Вдоль южной стороны дома рудиментарная подъездная дорожка вела к беленому гаражу, где разместился принадлежащий Пнину автомобиль "для бедных".</se>
  </para>
  <para id="18">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">A curious basketlike net, somewhat like a glorified billiard pocket вЂ” lacking, however, a bottom вЂ” was suspended for some reason above the garage door, upon the white of which it cast a shadow as distinct as its own weave but larger and in a bluer tone.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Странная сетчатая корзинка, чем-то смахивающая на увеличенную бильярдную лузу - только без дна, - висела неизвестно зачем над дверью гаража, на белизну которой она отбрасывала тень, столь же ясно очерченную, как ее собственное плетение, но покрупнее и в голубых тонах.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="19">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Pheasants visited the weedy ground between the garden and the cliff.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Травянистую площадку между садиком и утесом навещали фазаны.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="20">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Lilacs вЂ” those Russian garden graces, to whose spring-time splendour, all honey and hum, my poor Pnin greatly looked forward вЂ” crowded in sapless ranks along one wall of the house.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Сирень - краса русских садов, - чье весеннее великолепие, в меду и гудении, с нетерпеньем предвкушал мой бедный друг, безжизненно теснилась вдоль одной из стен дома.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="21">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">And a tall deciduous tree, which Pnin, a birch-lime-willow-aspen-poplar-oak man, was unable to identify, cast its large, heart-shaped, rust-coloured leaves and Indian-summer shadows upon the wooden steps of the open porch.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">И высокое листопадное дерево, которое Пнин (береза-липа-ива-тополь-дуб-осина) не умел обозначить, роняло большие, сердцевидные ржавые листья и тени бабьего лета на деревянные ступени открытого крыльца.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="22">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">A cranky-looking oil furnace in the basement did its best to send up its weak warm breath through registers in the floors.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Расхлябанного вида нефтяная подвальная печь старалась что было сил, слабо выдыхая тепло через отдушины в полах.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="23">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">The kitchen looked healthy and gay, and Pnin had a great time with all kinds of cookware, kettles and pans, toasters and skillets, all of which came with the house.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Кухня глядела нарядно и весело, и Пнин чудесно проводил время, возясь со всякого рода кухонной утварью - с кастрюлями и противнями, с тостерами и сковородками, доставшимися ему вместе с домом.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="24">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">The living-room was scantily and dingily furnished, but had a rather attractive bay harbouring a huge old globe, where Russia was painted a pale blue, with a discoloured or scrubbled patch all over Poland.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Мебель в гостиной стояла скудная, выцветшая, зато там имелась довольно милая ниша с огромным старым глобусом, на котором Россия была голубой, а Польшу частью обесцветили, а частью соскребли.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="25">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">In a very small dining-room, where Pnin contemplated arranging a buffet supper for his guests, a pair of crystal candlesticks with pendants was responsible in the early mornings for iridescent reflections, which glowed charmingly on the sideboard and reminded my sentimental friend of the stained-glass casements that coloured the sunlight orange and green and violet on the verandas of Russian country houses.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">В крохотной столовой, где Пнин намеревался устроить для гостей ужин "а-ля фуршет", пара хрустальных шандалов с подвесками разбрасывала по утрам радужные переливы, очаровательно тлевшие на буфете, напоминая моему сентиментальному другу о витражных переплетах, что окрашивали солнечный свет в оранжевые, зеленые и фиолетовые тона на русских дачных верандах.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="26">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">A china closet, every time he passed by it, went into a rumbling act that also was somehow familiar from dim back rooms of the past.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Посудный шкап, принимавшийся погромыхивать всякий раз, что Пнин проходил мимо, тоже был знаком ему по тусклым задним комнатам прошлого.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="27">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">The second floor consisted of two bedrooms, both of which had been the abode of many small children, with incidental adults.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Второй этаж состоял из двух спален, в обеих обитало когда-то множество малых детей и от случая к случаю - взрослых.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="28">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">The floors were chafed by tin toys.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Полы оказались изодраны оловянными игрушками.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="29">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">From the wall of the chamber Pnin decided to sleep in he had untacked a pennant-shaped red cardboard with the enigmatic word 'Cardinals' daubed on it in white; but a tiny rocker for a three-year-old Pnin, painted pink, was allowed to remain in its comer.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Со стены комнаты, в которой Пнин решил почивать, он снял красный картонный вымпел с загадочным словом "Кардиналы", намалеванным по нему белой краской, но маленькому красному креслу-качалке для трехлетнего Пнинчика дозволено было остаться в углу.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="30">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">A disabled sewing machine occupied a passageway leading to the bathroom, where the usual short tub, made for dwarfs by a nation of giants, took as long to fill as the tanks and basins of the arithmetic in Russian school books.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Недееспособная швейная машина загораживала коридор, ведущий в ванную комнату; стоявшая там всегдашняя куцая ванна из тех, что производит для карликов нация великанов, требовала для ее заполнения такого же долгого времени, как арифметические цистерны и бассейны русских задачников.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="31">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He was now ready to give that party.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Теперь он мог устроить прием.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="32">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">The living-room had a sofa that could seat three, there were two wing-back chairs, an overstuffed easy chair, a chair with a rush seat, one hassock, and two footstools.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">В гостиной имелась софа, на которой уместятся трое, имелась там также чета покойных кресел, кресло глубокое, набитое слишком туго, кресло с камышовым сиденьем, один пуфик и скамеечки под ноги.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="33">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">All of a sudden he experienced an odd feeling of dissatisfaction as he checked the little list of his guests.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Просматривая короткий список гостей, он вдруг ощутил странную неудовлетворенность.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="34">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">It had body but it lacked bouquet.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">В списке была крепость, но недоставало букета.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="35">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Of course, he was tremendously fond of the Clementses (real people вЂ” not like most of the campus dummies), with whom he had had such exhilarating talks in the days when he was their roomer; of course, he felt very grateful to Herman Hagen for many a good turn, such as that raise Hagen had recently arranged; of course, Mrs Hagen was, in Waindell parlance, 'a lovely person'; of course, Mrs Thayer was always so helpful at the library, and her husband had such a soothing capacity for showing how silent a man could be if he strictly avoided comments on the weather.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Конечно, он очень привязан к Клементсам (настоящие люди - не истуканы, коих в кампусе большинство), с которыми он вел такие восхитительные беседы в те дни, когда снимал у них комнату; конечно, он испытывал огромную благодарность к Герману Гагену за массу добрых услуг, взять хоть прибавку, устроенную им совсем недавно; конечно, миссис Гаген была, как выражались в Вайнделле, "милейшей особой"; конечно, миссис Тейер всегда помогала ему в библиотеке, а муж ее обладал утешительной способностью демонстрировать, насколько немногословным может быть человек, если он безусловно избегает говорить о погоде.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="36">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">But there was nothing extraordinary, nothing original, about this combination of people, and old Pnin recalled those birthday parties in his boyhood вЂ” the half a dozen children invited who were somehow always the same, and the pinching shoes, and the aching temples, and the kind of heavy, unhappy, constraining dullness that would settle on him after all the games had been played and a rowdy cousin had started putting nice new toys to vulgar and stupid uses; and he also recalled the lone buzz in his ears when, in the course of a protracted hide-and-seek routine, after an hour of uncomfortable concealment, he emerged from a dark and stuffy wardrobe in the maid's chamber, only to find that all his playmates had already gone home.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Однако в этом подборе людей не хватало чего-то необычайного, оригинального, и старый Пнин вспомнил о днях рождения своего детства - о полудюжине приглашенных детей, всегда почему-то одних и тех же, о тесных туфлях, ноющих висках, тяжкой, вязкой, безотрадной скуке, которая нападала на него после того, как было уже переиграно во все игры, и буйный двоюродный братец принимался третировать красивые новые игрушки самым дурацким и пошлым образом; он вспомнил и об одиноком гуде в ушах, когда во время предлинной игры в прятки, битый час просидев в неудобном укрытии, он вылез из душного и темного шкапа в комнате прислуги только затем, чтобы узнать, что все игроки давно разошлись по домам.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="37">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">While visiting a famous grocery between Waindellville and Isola, he ran into Betty Bliss, asked her, and she said she still remembered Turgenev's prose poem about roses, with its refrain 'Kak horoshi, kak svezhi (How fair, how fresh)', and would certainly be delighted to come.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Навещая популярную бакалейную лавку, расположенную между Вайнделлом и Изолой, он столкнулся с Бетти Блисс, пригласил и ее, и она сказала, что все еще помнит стихотворение в прозе о розах Тургенева с его рефреном "как хороши, как свежи" и, конечно, с радостью придет.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="38">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He asked the celebrated mathematician, Professor Idelson, and his wife, the sculptress, and they said they would come with joy but later telephoned to say they were tremendously sorry вЂ” they had overlooked a previous engagement.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Он пригласил знаменитого математика профессора Идельсона с женой-скульпторшей, и они ответили, что придут с удовольствием, но потом позвонили, чтобы сказать, что им страшно жаль, - они позабыли о более раннем приглашении.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="39">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He asked young Miller, by now an Associate Professor, and Charlotte, his pretty, freckled wife, but it turned out she was on the point of having a baby.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Он пригласил молодого Миллера, уже доцента, и Шарлотту, его хорошенькую веснущатую жену, но выяснилось, что ей вот-вот предстояло родить.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="40">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He asked old Carrol, the Frieze Hall head janitor, with his son Frank, who had been my friend's only talented student and had written a brilliant doctor's thesis for him on the relationship between Russian, English, and German iambics; but Frank was in the army, and old Carrol confessed that 'the missus and I do not mix much with the profs.' He rang up the residence of President Poore, whom he had once talked to (about improving the curriculum) at a lawn function, until it started to rain, and asked him to come, but President Poore's niece answered that her uncle nowadays' never visits with anybody except a few personal friends,' He was about to give up the notion of enlivening his list, when a perfectly new and really admirable idea occurred to him.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Он пригласил старика Кэррола, начальствующего над уборщиками Фриз-Холла, и его сына Фрэнка, который был единственным одаренным студентом моего друга и написал блестящую докторскую работу о соотношениях русских, английских и немецких ямбов; но Фрэнк оказался в армии, а старик Кэррол признался, что "мы с хозяйкой не очень водимся с профи". Пнин позвонил президенту Пуру, с которым однажды беседовал во время приема в саду (пока не пошел дождь) об усовершенствовании учебного плана, - и попросил его прийти, однако племянница президента ответила на приглашение, что дядя "никого теперь не навещает, за исключением нескольких близких друзей". Пнин уже было отказался от надежд оживить список гостей, как вдруг совершенно новая и действительно превосходная мысль пришла ему в голову.</se>
  </para>
</body>
</html>
