<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<html>
<head>
</head>
<body>
  <para id="0">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">2</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">2</se>
  </para>
  <para id="1">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Whitchurch materialized as scheduled.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Уитчерч материализовался по расписанию.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="2">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">A hot, torpid expanse of cement and sun lay beyond the geometrical solids of various clean-cut shadows.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Горячее, оцепенелое цементное пространство и солнце, лежащее за геометрическими телами разнообразно и чисто вырезанных теней.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="3">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">The local weather was unbelievably summery for October.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Погода здесь стояла для октября невероятно летняя.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="4">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Alert, Pnin entered a waiting-room of sorts, with a needless stove in the middle, and looked around.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Настороженный Пнин вошел в подобие ожидательной залы с ненужной печкой посередине и огляделся.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="5">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">In a solitary recess, one could make out the upper part of a perspiring young man who was filling out forms on the broad wooden counter before him.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Единственная ниша в стене позволяла увидеть верхнюю половину потного молодого человека, который заполнял какие-то ведомости, разложенные перед ним на широкой деревянной конторке.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="6">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'Information, please,' said Pnin.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">- Информацию, пожалуйста, - сказал Пнин.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="7">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'Where stops four o'clock bus to Cremona?'</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">- Где останавливается четырехчасовой автобус в Кремону?</se>
  </para>
  <para id="8">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'Right across the street,' briskly answered the employee without looking up.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">- Прямо через улицу, - не поднимая глаз, отрывисто ответил служитель.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="9">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'And where possible to leave baggage?'</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">- А где возможно оставить багаж?</se>
  </para>
  <para id="10">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'That bag?</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">- Этот саквояж?</se>
  </para>
  <para id="11">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">I'll take care of it.'</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Я за ним присмотрю.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="12">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">And with the national informality that always nonplussed Pnin, the young man shoved the bag into a corner of his nook.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">И с национальной небрежностью, всегда приводившей Пнина в замешательство, молодой человек затолкал саквояж в угол своего укрытия.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="13">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'Quittance?' queried Pnin, Englishing the Russian for 'receipt' (kvtantsiya).</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">- Квиттэнс? - поинтересовался Пнин, заменяя английский "receipt"1 англизированной русской "квитанцией".</se>
  </para>
  <para id="14">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'What's that?'</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">- А что это?</se>
  </para>
  <para id="15">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'Number?' tried Pnin.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">- Номерок? - попытал счастья Пнин.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="16">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'You don't need a number,' said the fellow, and resumed his writing.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">- Да на что он вам, - сказал молодой человек и возвратился к своим занятиям.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="17">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Pnin left the station, satisfied himself about the bus stop, and entered a coffee shop.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Пнин оставил станцию, удостоверился в существовании автобусной остановки и вошел в кофейню.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="18">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He consumed a ham sandwich, ordered another, and consumed that too.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Он поглотил сэндвич с ветчиной, спросил другой и его поглотил тоже.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="19">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">At exactly five minutes to four, having paid for the food but not for an excellent toothpick which he carefully selected from a neat little cup in the shape of a pine cone near the cash register, Pnin walked back to the station for his bag.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Ровно без пяти четыре, уплатив за еду, но не за превосходную зубочистку, тщательно выбранную им из стоявшей у кассы миленькой чашки, изображавшей сосновую шишку, Пнин воротился на станцию за багажом.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="20">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">A different man was now in charge.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Теперь на посту был другой человек.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="21">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">The first had been called home to drive his wife in all haste to the maternity hospital.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Первого позвали домой, чтобы он срочно отвез жену в родильное заведение.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="22">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He would be back in a few minutes.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">С минуты на минуту вернется.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="23">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'But I must obtain my valise!' cried Pnin.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">- Но я должен получить мой чемодан! - вскричал Пнин.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="24">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">The substitute was sorry but could not do a thing.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Сменщику было очень жаль, но он ничего не мог поделать.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="25">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'It is there!' cried Pnin, leaning over and pointing.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">- Да вот же он! - возопил Пнин, перегибаясь и указывая.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="26">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">This was unfortunate.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Жест вышел не самый удачный.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="27">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He was still in the act of pointing when he realized that he was claiming the wrong bag.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Еще продолжая указывать, он осознал, что предъявляет права не на тот саквояж.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="28">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">His index finger wavered.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Указательный палец его заколебался.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="29">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">That hesitation was fatal.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Колебание было фатальным.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="30">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'My bus to Cremona!' cried Pnin.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">- У меня автобус на Кремону! - кричал Пнин.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="31">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'There is another at eight,' said the man.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">- В восемь будет другой, - сказал служитель.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="32">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">What was our poor friend to do?</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Что оставалось делать нашему бедному другу?</se>
  </para>
  <para id="33">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Horrible situation!</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Ужасное положение!</se>
  </para>
  <para id="34">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He glanced streetward.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Он глянул через улицу.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="35">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">The bus had just come.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Автобус только что подкатил.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="36">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">The engagement meant an extra fifty dollars.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Лекция даст ему пятьдесят добавочных долларов.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="37">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">His hand flew to his right side.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Его рука вспорхнула к правой стороне груди.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="38">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">It was there, slava Bogu (thank God)!</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Слава Богу, она здесь!</se>
  </para>
  <para id="39">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Very well!</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Очень хорошо!</se>
  </para>
  <para id="40">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He would not wear his black suit вЂ” vot i vsyo (that's all).</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Он не наденет черного костюма - вот и все!</se>
  </para>
  <para id="41">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He would retrieve it on his way back.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Он прихватит его он на обратном пути.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="42">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He had lost, dumped, shed many more valuable things in his day.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">В свое время он терял, бросал, вообще лишался куда более ценных вещей.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="43">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Energetically, almost light-heartedly, Pnin boarded the bus.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Энергично, почти беззаботно Пнин взобрался в автобус.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="44">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He had endured this new stage of his journey only for a few city blocks when an awful suspicion crossed his mind.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">На этой новой стадии своего путешествия, он проехал всего лишь несколько городских кварталов, когда разум его посетило ужасное подозрение.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="45">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Ever since he had been separated from his bag, the tip of his left forefinger had been alternating with the proximal edge of his right elbow in checking a precious presence in ru8 inside coat pocket.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">С того самого времени, как он расстался с саквояжем, его левый указательный палец попеременно с внутренним краем правого локтя проверял присутствие бесценного груза во внутреннем кармане пиджака.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="46">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">All of a sudden he brutally yanked it out.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Одним махом он выдрал его оттуда.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="47">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">It was Betty's paper.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Это была работа Бетти.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="48">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Emitting what he thought were international exclamations of anxiety and entreaty, Pnin lurched out of his seat.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Испустив то, что представлялось ему международным выражением мольбы и испуга, Пнин выкарабкался из кресла.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="49">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Reeling, he reached the exit.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Раскачиваясь, добрался до выхода.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="50">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">With one hand the driver grimly milked out a handful of coins from his little machine, refunded him the price of the ticket, and stopped the bus.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Водитель одной рукой хмуро выдоил из машинки пригоршню центов, возместил ему стоимость билета и остановил автобус.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="51">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Poor Pnin landed in the middle of a strange town.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Бедный Пнин высадился посреди чужого города.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="52">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He was less strong than his powerfully puffed-out chest might imply, and the wave of hopeless fatigue that suddenly submerged his top-heavy body, detaching him, as it were, from reality, was a sensation not utterly unknown to rum.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Не так уж он был и крепок, как позволяла думать его мощно выпяченная грудь, и волна безнадежной усталости, которая внезапно накрыла его тяжеловатый в верхней части корпус, как бы относя его от реальности, была для него ощущением не вполне незнакомым.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="53">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He found himself in a damp, green, purplish park, of the formal and funereal type, with the stress laid on sombre rhododendrons, glossy laurels, sprayed shade trees and closely clipped lawns; and hardly had he turned into an alley of chestnut and oak, which the bus driver had curtly told him led back to the railway station, than that eerie feeling, that tingle of unreality overpowered him completely.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Он сознавал, что бредет по сырому, зеленому и лиловатому парку строгого, отчасти кладбищенского пошиба, с преобладанием мрачных рододендронов, лоснистых лавров, раскидистых тенистых деревьев и стриженных газонов; и едва свернул он в аллею дубов и каштанов, которая, по кратким словам водителя, вела обратно к вокзалу, как это жутковатое ощущение, этот холодок нереальности полностью им овладел.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="54">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Was it something he had eaten?</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Было ли тому виной что-то из съеденного?</se>
  </para>
  <para id="55">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">That pickle with the ham?</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Те пикули с ветчиной?</se>
  </para>
  <para id="56">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Was it a mysterious disease that none of his doctors had yet detected?</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Или то была загадочная болезнь, которой до сей поры не смог обнаружить ни один из его докторов?</se>
  </para>
  <para id="57">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">My friend wondered, and I wonder, too.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Мой друг терялся в догадках, теряюсь в них и я.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="58">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">I do not know if it has ever been noted before that one of the main characteristics of life is discreteness.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Не знаю, отмечал ли уже кто-либо, что главная характеристика жизни - это отъединенность?</se>
  </para>
  <para id="59">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Unless a film of flesh envelops us, we die.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Не облекай нас тонкая пленка плоти, мы бы погибли.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="60">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Man exists only insofar as he is separated from his surroundings.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Человек существует лишь пока он отделен от своего окружения.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="61">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">The cranium is a spacetraveller's helmet.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Череп - это шлем космического скитальца.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="62">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Stay inside or you perish.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Сиди внутри, иначе погибнешь.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="63">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Death is divestment, death is communion.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Смерть -разоблачение, смерть - причащение.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="64">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">It may be wonderful to mix with the landscape, but to do so is the end of the tender ego.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Слиться с ландшафтом - дело, может быть, и приятное, однако, тут-то и конец нежному эго.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="65">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">The sensation poor Pnin experienced was something very like that divestment, that communion.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Чувство, которое испытывал бедный Пнин, чем-то весьма походило и на это разоблачение, и на это причащение.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="66">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He felt porous and pregnable.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Он казался себе пористым, уязвимым.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="67">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He was sweating.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Он потел.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="68">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He was terrified.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Его пронизывал страх.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="69">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">A stone bench among the laurels saved him from collapsing on the sidewalk.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Каменная скамья под лаврами спасла его от падения на дорожку.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="70">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Was his seizure a heart attack?</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Был ли этот приступ сердечным припадком?</se>
  </para>
  <para id="71">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">I doubt it.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Сомневаюсь.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="72">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">For the nonce I am his physician, and let me repeat, I doubt it.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">В данном случае я - его доктор, и позвольте мне повторить еще раз: сомневаюсь.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="73">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">My patient was one of those singular and unfortunate people who regard their heart ('a hollow, muscular organ,' according to the gruesome definition in Webster's New Collegiate Dictionary, which Pnin's orphaned bag contained) with a queasy dread, a nervous repulsion, a sick hate, as if it were some strong slimy untouchable monster that one had to be parasitized with, alas.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Мой пациент принадлежал к тем редким и злополучным людям, что относятся к своему сердцу ("полому, мускулистому органу" - по зловещему определению "Webster's New Collegiate Dictionary"1, лежавшего в осиротевшем саквояже Пнина) с тошным страхом, с нервическим омерзением, с болезненной ненавистью, словно к могучему, слизистому чудищу, паразиту, к которому противно притронуться и с которого, увы, приходится мириться.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="74">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Occasionally, when puzzled by his tumbling and tottering pulse, doctors examined him more thoroughly, the cariograph outlined fabulous mountain ranges and indicated a dozen fatal diseases that excluded one another.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Время от времени доктора, озадаченные его шатким и валким пульсом проводили тщательное обследование, кардиограф выписывал баснословные горные цепи и указывал на дюжину смертельных недугов, исключавших один другого.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="75">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He was afraid of touching his own wrist.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Он боялся притронуться к собственному запястью.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="76">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He never attempted to sleep on his left side, even in those dismal hours of the night when the insomniac longs for a third side after trying the two he has.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Он никогда не пытался заснуть на левом боку, даже в те гнетущие часы, когда жертва бессонницы томится по третьему боку, испробовав два наличных.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="77">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">And now, in the park of Whitchurch, Pnin felt what he bad felt already on August 10, 1942, and February 15 (his birthday), 1937, and May 18, 1929, and July 4, 1920 вЂ” that the repulsive automaton he lodged had developed a consciousness of its own and not only was grossly alive but was causing him pain and panic.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">И вот теперь, в уитчерчском парке, Пнин испытывал то, что он уже испытал 10 августа 1942 года и 15 февраля (в свой день рождения) 1937 года, и 18 мая 1929 года, и 4 июля 1920-го, ощущение, что отвратный автомат, обитающий в нем, обзавелся собственным разумом и не просто живет своей животной жизнью, но насылает на него боль и боязнь.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="78">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He pressed his poor bald head against the stone back of the bench and recalled all the past occasions of similar discomfort and despair.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Прижимая бедную лысую голову к каменной спинке скамьи, он вспоминал все прежние приступы такой же немощи и отчаяния.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="79">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Could it be pneumonia this time?</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Может быть, на этот раз - пневмония?</se>
  </para>
  <para id="80">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He had been chilled to the bone a couple of days before in one of those hearty American draughts that a host treats his guests to after the second round of drinks on a windy night.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Дня два назад он продрог до костей на одном из тех дружеских американских сквозняков, которыми хозяин дома угощает ветренной ночью своих гостей после второго круга выпивки.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="81">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">And suddenly Pnin (was he dying?) found himself sliding back into his own childhood.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Внезапно Пнин почувствовал (уж не умирает ли он?), что соскальзывает в детство.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="82">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">This sensation had the sharpness of retrospective detail that is said to be the dramatic privilege of drowning individuals, especially in the former Russian Navy вЂ” a phenomenon of suffocation that a veteran psychoanalyst, whose name excapes me, has explained as being the subconsciously evoked shock of one's baptism which causes an explosion of intervening recollections between the first immersion and the last.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Это чувство обладало резкостью ретроспективных деталей, составляющей, как уверяют, драматическое достояние утопающих, - особенно на прежнем Русском флоте, - феномен удушья, которое бывалый психоаналитик, забыл его имя, объяснял подсознательным возрождением шока крещения, вызывающим как бы взрыв воспоминаний, промежуточных между первым погружением и последним.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="83">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">It all happened in a flash but there is no way of rendering it in less than so many consecutive words.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Все случилось мгновенно, - нет, однако, иного способа описать случившееся, как прибегая к нижеследующему многословию.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="84">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Pnin came from a respectable, fairly well-to-do, St Petersburg family.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Пнин происходил из почтенной, вполне состоятельной петербургской семьи.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="85">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">His father, Dr Pavel Pnin, an eye specialist of considerable repute, had once had the honour of treating Leo Tolstoy for a case of conjunctivitis.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Отец его, доктор Павел Пнин, глазной специалист с солидной репутацией, имел однажды честь лечить от конъюнктивита Льва Толстого.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="86">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Timofey's mother, a frail, nervous little person with a waspy waist and bobbed hair, was the daughter of the once famous revolutionary Umov (rhymes with' zoom off') and of a German lady from Riga.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Мать Тимофея - хрупкая, нервная маленькая женщина с осиной талией и короткой стрижкой - была дочерью знаменитого некогда революционера по фамилии Умов (рифмуется с "zoom off"1) и немки из Риги.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="87">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Through his half swoon, he saw his mother's approaching eyes.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">В полуобмороке он видел приближающиеся глаза матери.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="88">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">It was a Sunday in mid winter.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Воскресенье, середина зимы.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="89">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He was eleven.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Ему одиннадцать лет.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="90">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He had been preparing lessons for his Monday classes at the First Gymnasium when a strange chill pervaded his body.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Он готовил уроки на понедельник - к занятиям в Первой гимназии, как вдруг его тело пронизал непонятный озноб.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="91">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">His mother took his temperature, looked at her child with a kind of stupefaction, and immediately called her husband's best friend, the paediatrician Belochkin.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Мать смерила температуру, посмотрела на него с оторопелым недоумением и немедленно послала за ближайшим друга отца, педиатром Белочкиным.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="92">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He was a small, beetle-browed man, with a short beard and cropped hair.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">То был насупленный человечек с кустистыми бровями, короткой бородкой и коротким же бобриком.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="93">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Easing the skirts of his frock coat, he sat down on the edge of Timofey's bed.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Откинув полы сюртука, он опустился на край тимофеевой кровати.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="94">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">A race was run between the doctor's fat golden watch and Timofey's pulse (an easy winner).</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Понеслись взапуски докторские пузатые золотые часы и пульс Тимофея (легко победивший).</se>
  </para>
  <para id="95">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Then Timofey's torso was bared, and to it Belochkin pressed the icy nudity of his ear and the sandpapery side of his head.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Затем оголили торс Тимофея, и доктор припал к нему ледяным голым ухом и наждачным виском.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="96">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Like the flat sole of some monopode, the ear ambulated all over Timofey's back and chest, gluing itself to this or that patch of skin and stomping on to the next.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Подобно плоской ступне некоего одноногого существа, ухо бродило по груди и спине Тимофея, прилипая к тому или этому участку кожи и перетопывая на следующий.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="97">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">No sooner had the doctor left than Timofey's mother and a robust servant girl with safety-pins between her teeth encased the distressed little patient in a straitjacket-like compress.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Доктор ушел не раньше, чем мать Тимофея и дюжая служанка, державшая английские булавки в зубах, заковали приунывшего маленького пациента в похожий на смирительную рубашку компресс.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="98">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">It consisted of a layer of soaked linen, a thicker layer of absorbent cotton, and another of tight flannel, with a sticky diabolical oilcloth вЂ” the hue of urine and fever вЂ” coming between the clammy pang of the linen next to his skin and the excruciating squeak of the cotton around which the outer layer of flannel was wound.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Компресс состоял из слоя влажного холста, слоя потолще, образованного гигроскопической ватой, еще одного - плотной фланели и противно липучей клеенки (цвета мочи и горячки), залегавшей между болезненно льнущим к коже холстом и мучительно повизгивающей ватой, окруженной внешним слоем фланели.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="99">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">A poor cocooned pupa, Timosha (Tim) lay under a mass of additional blankets; they were of no avail against the branching chill that crept up his ribs from both sides of his frozen spine.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Будто бедная куколка в коконе, лежал Тимоша под кучей добавочных одеял, но они ничего не могли поделать с ветвистой стужей, ползшей в обе стороны по ребрам от заиндевелой спины.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="100">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He could not close his eyes because his eyelids stung so.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Веки саднили, не позволяя закрыться глазам.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="101">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Vision was but oval pain with oblique stabs of light; familiar shapes became the breeding places of evil delusions.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">От зрения осталась лишь овальная боль с косыми проколами света; привычные очертания стали питомниками жутких видений.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="102">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Near his bed was a four-section screen of polished wood, with pyrographic designs representing a bridle path felted with fallen leaves, a lily pond, an old man hunched up on a bench, and a squirrel holding a reddish object in its front paws.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Вблизи кровати стояла четырехстворчатая ширма полированного дерева с выжженными по нему картинками, изображавшими устланную войлоком палой листвы верховую тропу, пруд в кувшинках, согбенного старика на скамье и белку, державшую в передних лапках какой-то красноватый предмет.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="103">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Timosha, a methodical child, had often wondered what that object could be (a nut? a pine cone?), and now that he had nothing else to do, he set himself to solve this dreary riddle, but the fever that hummed in his head drowned every effort in pain and panic.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Тимоша, обстоятельный мальчик, нередко гадал, что бы это такое было (орех? сосновая шишка?), и вот теперь, не имея иного занятья, он решил попробовать разгадать эту сумрачную тайну, но жар гудел в голове, потопляя любое усилие в боязни и боли.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="104">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Still more oppressive was his tussle with the wallpaper.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Еще пуще угнетало его боренье с обоями.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="105">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He had always been able to see that in the vertical plane a combination made up of three different clusters of purple flowers and seven different oak leaves was repeated a number of times with soothing exactitude; but now he was bothered by the undismissible fact that he could not find what system of inclusion and circumscription governed the horizontal recurrence of the pattern; that such a recurrence existed was proved by his being able to pick out here and there, all along the wall from bed to wardrobe and from stove to door, the reappearance of this or that element of the series, but when he tried travelling right or left from any chosen set of three inflorescences and seven leaves, he forthwith lost himself in a meaningless tangle of rhododendron and oak.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Он всегда без труда обнаруживал, что сочетание трех различных лиловатых соцветий и семи разновидных дубовых листьев раз за разом с успокоительной точностью повторяется по вертикали; сейчас, однако, его беспокоило то непреклонное обстоятельство, что ему никак не удается понять, какой же порядок включения и отбора управляет повтореньем рисунка по горизонтали; существование порядка доказывалось тем, что он ухватывал там и сям - на протяженьи стены от кровати до шкапа и от печки до двери - повторное появление того или иного члена последовательности, но стоило ему попытаться уйти вправо или влево от выбранного наугад сочетания трех соцветий с семью листками, как он немедля запутывался в бессмысленном переплетении дубов и рододендронов.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="106">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">It stood to reason that if the evil designer вЂ” the destroyer of minds, the friend of fever вЂ” had concealed the key of the pattern with such monstrous care, that key must be as precious as life itself and, when found, would regain for Timofey Pnin his everyday health, his everyday world; and this lucid вЂ” alas, too lucid вЂ” thought forced him to persevere in the struggle.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Здравый смысл подсказывал, что если злокозненный художник - губитель рассудка и друг горячки - упрятывал ключ к узору с таким омерзительным тщанием, то ключ этот должен быть так же бесценен, как самая жизнь, и найденный, он возвратит Тимофею Пнину его повседневное здравие и повседневный мир; вот эта-то ясная - увы, слишком ясная - мысль и заставляла его упорствовать в борьбе.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="107">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">A sense of being late for some appointment as odiously exact as school, dinner, or bedtime added the discomfort of awkward haste to the difficulties of a quest that was grading into delirium.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Ощущение, что он запаздывает к какому-то сроку, отвратительно точно назначенному, вроде начала уроков, обеда или времени отхода ко сну, отягощало неловкой поспешностью его затруднительный поиск, понемногу сползавший в бред.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="108">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">The foliage and the flowers, with none of the intricacies of their warp disturbed, appeared to detach themselves in one undulating body from their pale-blue background which, in its turn, lost its papery flatness and dilated in depth till the spectator's heart almost burst in response to the expansion.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Цветы и листья, ничуть не теряя их извращенной запутанности, казалось, одним волнообразным целым отделялись от бледно-синего фона, а фон, в свой черед, утрачивал бумажную плосковатость и раскрывался в глубину до того, что сердце зрителя почти разрывалось, отвечая этому расширению.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="109">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He could still make out through the autonomous garlands certain parts of the nursery more tenacious of life than the rest, such as the lacquered screen, the gleam of a tumbler, the brass knobs of his bedstead, but these interfered even less with the oak leaves and rich blossoms than would the reflection of an inside object in a window-pane with the outside scenery perceived through the same glass.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Он еще мог различить сквозь отделившиеся гирлянды кое-какие частности детской, оказавшиеся поживучей, к примеру, лаковую ширму, блик на стакане, латунные шишечки на спинке кровати, впрочем, они мешали дубовым листьям и пышным цветам даже меньше, чем внутреннее отраженье предмета в оконном стекле мешает пейзажу снаружи, видимому сквозь это стекло.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="110">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">And although the witness and victim of these phantasms was tucked up in bed, he was, in accordance with the twofold nature of his surroundings, simultaneously seated on a bench in a green and purple park.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">И хоть свидетель и жертва этих фантазмов лежал, укутанный, в постели, он же, - в согласии с двойственной природой внешнего мира, - одновременно сидел на скамье в лиловато-зеленом парке.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="111">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">During one melting moment, he had the sensation of holding at last the key he had sought; but, coming from very far, a rustling wind, its soft volume increasing as it ruffled the rhododendrons вЂ” now blossomless, blind вЂ” confused whatever rational pattern Timofey Pnin's surroundings had once had.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">В один ускользающий миг ему показалось, что он, наконец-то, держит искомый ключ в руках, но, налетая издалека, зашелестел ветер, мягкий шум его рос, пока он ерошил рододендроны, - уже отцветшие, ослепшие, - ветер спутал разумный узор, присущий некогда миру вокруг Тимофея Пнина.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="112">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He was alive and that was sufficient.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Что же, он жив - и довольно.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="113">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">The back of the bench against which he still sprawled felt as real as his clothes, or his wallet, or the date of the Great Moscow Fire вЂ” 1812.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Прислон скамейки, к которому он привалился, так же реален, как одежда на нем или бумажник, или дата Великого Московского Пожара - 1812 год.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="114">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">A grey squirrel sitting on comfortable haunches on the ground before him was sampling a peach stone.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Дымчатая белка, на удобных калачиках сидевшая перед ним на земле, покусывала косточку персика.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="115">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">The wind paused, and presently stirred the foliage again.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Ветер притих и тут же вновь зашебуршился в листве.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="116">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">The seizure had left him a little frightened and shaky, but he argued that had it been a real heart attack, he would have surely felt a good deal more unsettled and concerned, and this roundabout piece of reasoning completely dispelled his fear.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Приступ оставил его немного напуганным и ослабелым, но он сказал себе, что, будь это настоящий сердечный припадок, он бы наверняка испытывал куда большие тревогу и озабоченность, и этот окольный резон изгнал испуг окончательно.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="117">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">It was now four-twenty.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Четыре часа, двадцать минут.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="118">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He blew his nose and trudged to the station.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Он высморкался и потащился к станции.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="119">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">The initial employee was back.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Прежний служитель вернулся.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="120">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'Here's your bag,' he said cheerfully.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">"Вот вам ваш саквояж, - весело сказал он.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="121">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'Sorry you missed the Cremona bus.'</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">- Сожалею, что вы пропустили кремонский автобус."</se>
  </para>
  <para id="122">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'At least' вЂ” and what dignified irony our unfortunate friend tried to inject into that 'at least' вЂ” 'I hope everything is good with your wife?'</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">- По крайности, - и сколько достойной иронии постарался вложить наш невезучий друг в это "по крайности", - с вашей женой все в порядке, надеюсь?</se>
  </para>
  <para id="123">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'She'll be all right.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">- Будет в порядке.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="124">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Have to wait till tomorrow, I guess.'</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Похоже, придется ждать до утра.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="125">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'And now,' said Pnin, 'where is located the public telephone?'</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">- А теперь, - сказал Пнин, - где расположен публичный телефон?</se>
  </para>
  <para id="126">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">The man pointed with his pencil as far out and sideways as he could without leaving his lair.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Служитель махнул карандашом вдаль и вбок, насколько достал, не вылезая из логова.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="127">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Pnin, bag in hand, started to go, but he was called back.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Пнин пошел с саквояжем в руке, но был окликнут.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="128">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">The pencil was now directed streetward.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Теперь карандаш торчал поперек улицы.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="129">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'Say, see those two guys loading that truck?</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">- Слушайте, видите, там двое парней грузят фургон?</se>
  </para>
  <para id="130">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">They're going to Cremona right now.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Они прямо сейчас едут в Кремону.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="131">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Just tell them Bob Horn sent you.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Скажите им, что вы от Боба Горна.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="132">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">They'll take you.'</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Они вас возьмут.</se>
  </para>
</body>
</html>
