<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<html>
<head>
</head>
<body>
  <para id="0">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">9</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">9</se>
  </para>
  <para id="1">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">It still rained.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Все еще шел дождь.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="2">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">All the lights in the Sheppard house were out.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">В доме Шеппарда погасли огни.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="3">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">The brook in the gully behind the garden, a trembling trickle most of the time, was tonight a loud torrent that tumbled over itself in its avid truckling to gravity, as it carried through corridors of beech and spruce last year's leaves, and some leafless twigs, and a brand-new, unwanted soccer ball that had recently rolled into the water from the sloping lawn after Pnin disposed of it by defenestration.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Ручей, обычно трепетной струйкой сочившийся по оврагу за садом, этой ночью обратился в шумный поток, который кувыркался, истово пресмыкаясь перед силой тяжести, и нес по буковым и еловым проходам прошлогодние листья, какие-то безлистые ветки и новенький, ненужный ему футбольный мяч, недавно скатившийся вдоль пологой лужайки после того, как Пнин казнил его на старинный манер - выбрасываньем из окна.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="4">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He had fallen asleep at last, despite the discomfort in his back, and in the course of one of those dreams that still haunt Russian fugitives, even when a third of a century has elapsed since their escape from the Bolsheviks, Pnin saw himself fantastically cloaked, fleeing through great pools of ink under a cloud-barred moon from a chimerical palace, and then pacing a desolate strand with his dead friend Ilya Isidorovich Polyanski as they waited for some mysterious deliverance to arrive in a throbbing boat from beyond the hopeless sea.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Пнин заснул, наконец, несмотря на ощущение неудобства в спине, и в одном из тех сновидений, что по-прежнему преследуют русских изгнанников, хоть со времени их бегства от большевиков прошла уже треть столетия, увидел себя в несуразном плаще, несущимся прочь из химерического дворца по огромным чернильным лужам, под затянутой облаками луной, а после шагающим вдоль пустынной полоски берега со своим покойным другом Ильей Исидоровичем Полянским, ожидая стука моторной лодки, в которой явится за ними из безнадежного моря их загадочный спаситель.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="5">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">The Sheppard brothers were both awake in their adjacent beds, on their Beautyrest mattresses, the younger listened in the dark to the rain and wondered if after ill they should sell the house with its audible roof and wet garden; the elder lay thinking of silence, of a green damp churchyard, of an old farm, of a poplar that years ago lightning had struck, killing John Head, a dim, distant relation.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Братья Шеппарды не спали в смежных кроватях, на матрацах "Прекрасный Отдых", - младший слушал дождь, идущий во тьме, и раздумывал, не продать ли им все же этот дом с его гулкой кровлей и волглым садом; старший лежал, думая о тишине, о влажном зеленом кладбище, о старой ферме, о тополе, в который много лет назад ударила молния и убила Джона Хеда, смутного дальнего родича.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="6">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Victor had, for once, fallen asleep as soon as he put his head under his pillow вЂ” a recently evolved method about which Dr Eric Wind (sitting on a bench, near a fountain, in Quito, Ecuador) would never learn.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Виктор на сей раз заснул мгновенно, едва засунув голову под подушку, - недавно изобретенный способ, о котором д-р Эрик Винд (сидящий сейчас на скамье у фонтана в Кито, Эквадор) никогда не узнает.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="7">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Around half past one the Sheppards started to snore, the deaf one doing it with a rattle at the end of each exhalation and many volumes louder than the other, a modest and melancholy wheezer.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Около половины второго Шеппарды захрапели, глухой погромыхивал после каждого вздоха и вообще звучал куда солиднее брата, высвистывавшего сдержанно и печально.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="8">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">On the sandy beach where Pnin was still pacing (his worried friend had gone home for a map), there appeared before him a set of approaching footprints, and he awoke with a gasp.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">На песчаном берегу, по которому продолжал расхаживать Пнин (его встревоженный друг пошел домой, за картой), появились и пошли на него чередой отпечатки чьих-то ступней, и он проснулся, хватая ртом воздух.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="9">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">His back hurt.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Ныла спина.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="10">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">It was now past four.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Пятый час уже.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="11">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">The rain had stopped.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Дождь перестал.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="12">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Pnin sighed a Russian 'okh-okh-okh' sigh, and sought a more comfortable position.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Пнин вздохнул русским вздохом ("ох-хо-хо") и поискал положение поудобней.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="13">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Old Bill Sheppard trudged to the downstairs bathroom, brought down the house, then trudged back.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Старый Билл Шеппард протащился вниз, в уборную, сокрушая за собою дом, потом поплелся назад.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="14">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Presently all were asleep again.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Вот и опять все уснули.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="15">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">It was a pity nobody saw the display in the empty street, where the auroral breeze wrinkled a large luminous puddle, making of the telephone wires reflected in it illegible lines of black zigzags.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Жаль, что никто не видал представления, разыгранного на пустынной улице, - там рассветный ветер наморщил большую, светозарную лужу, превратив отраженные в ней телефонные провода в неразборчивые строки черных зигзагов.</se>
  </para>
</body>
</html>
