<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<html>
<head>
</head>
<body>
  <para id="0">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">4</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">4</se>
  </para>
  <para id="1">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Cook's Castle was a three-storey brick-and-timber mansion built around 1860 and partly rebuilt half a century later, when Susan's father purchased it from the Dudley-Greene family in order to make of it a select resort hotel for the richer patrons of the curative Onkwedo Springs.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">"Замок Кука" представлял собой трехэтажный особняк, выстроенный из бревен и кирпича около 1860 года и частью перестроенный полвека спустя, когда отец Сюзан купил его у семейства Дадли-Грин, чтобы превратить в аристократический курортный отель для наиболее богатых посетителей целебных источников Онкведо.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="2">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">It was an elaborate and ugly building in a mongrel style, with the Gothic bristling through remnants of French and Florentine, and when originally designed might have belonged to the variety which Samuel Sloan, an architect of the time, classified as An Irregular Northern Villa 'well adapted to the highest requirements of social life' and called' Northern' because of 'the aspiring tendency of its roof and towers'.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Это было затейливое строение смешанного покроя, в котором готика щетинилась сквозь пережитки флорентийского и французского стилей. При начальном проектировании оно, вероятно, относилось к той разновидности, которую Сэмюель Слоун, архитектор тех времен, определял как "Неправильную Северную Виллу, отвечающую высшим запросам светской жизни", и называемую "северной" по причине "восходящей тенденции ее кровель и башен".</se>
  </para>
  <para id="3">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">The piquancy of these pinnacles and the merry, somewhat even inebriated air the mansion had of having been composed of several smaller Northern Villas, hoisted into mid air and knocked together anyhow, with parts of unassimilated roofs, half-hearted gables, cornices, rustic quoins, and other projections sticking out on all sides, had, alas, but briefly attracted tourists.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Увы, недолго завлекали туристов шик этих шпилей и веселый, отчасти даже разгульный облик, приобретенный особняком оттого, что его составляли несколько "северных вилл" поменьше, поднятых на воздух и каким-то образом сколоченных воедино, так что недопереваренные куски кровель, неуверенные фронтоны, карнизы, неотесанные угловые камни и прочие выступы торчали во все стороны.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="4">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">By 1920, the Onkwedo waters had mysteriously lost whatever magic they had contained, and after her father's death Susan had vainly tried to sell The Pines, since they had another more comfortable house in the residential quarter of the industrial city where her husband worked.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">К 1920 году воды Онкведо загадочным образом утратили все свое волшебство, и по смерти отца Сюзан тщетно пыталась продать "Сосны", поскольку у нее с мужем имелся иной дом, поудобнее, в богатом квартале того промышленного города, где муж работал.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="5">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">However, now that they had got accustomed to use the Castle for entertaining their numerous friends, Susan was glad that the meek beloved monster had found no purchaser.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Впрочем, теперь, когда они привыкли использовать "Замок" для увеселения своих многочисленных друзей, Сюзан даже радовалась, что это любимое ею кроткое чудище не нашло покупателя.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="6">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Within, the diversity was as great as without.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Внутреннее разнообразие дома не уступало наружному.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="7">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Four spacious rooms opened from the large hall that retained something of its hostelic stage in the generous dimensions of the grate.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">В просторный вестибюль, сохранивший в щедрых размерах камина нечто от гостиничного периода, открывались четыре большие комнаты.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="8">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">The hand rail of the stairs, and at least one of its spindles, dated from 1720, having been transferred to the house, while it was being built, from a far older one, whose very site was no longer exactly known.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Лестничные перила и по крайности одна из балясин датировались 1720 годом, - их перенесли в строящийся дом из другого, гораздо более старого, самое местоположение коего ныне уже утратилось.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="9">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Very ancient, too, were the beautiful sideboard panels of game and fish in the dining-room.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Очень старыми были и прекрасные, украшенные изображеньями дичи и рыб филенки стоящего в обеденной зале буфета.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="10">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">In the half a dozen rooms of which each of the upper floors consisted, and in the two wings in the rear, one could discover, among disparate pieces of furniture, some charming satinwood bureau, some romantic rosewood sofa, but also all kinds of bulky and miserable articles, broken chairs, dusty marble-topped tables, morose Г©tagГЁres with bits of dark-looking glass in the back as mournful as the eyes of old apes.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">В полудюжине комнат, из которых состоял каждый верхний этаж, и в двух крыльях тыльной части здания среди разрозненных предметов обстановки обнаруживалось какое-нибудь обаятельное бюро атласного дерева или романтическая софа красного, но также и разного рода поделки, жалкие и громоздкие, - ломанные кресла, пыльные столы с мраморными столешницами, мрачные этажерки с темными стеклышками в задней стене, скорбными, словно глаза пожилых обезьян.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="11">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">The chamber Pnin got was a pleasant south-east one on the upper floor: it had remnants of gilt paper on the walls, an army cot, a plain washstand, and all kinds of shelves, brackets, and scrollwork mouldings.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Комната наверху, доставшаяся Пнину, не без приятности выглядывала на юго-восток и вмещала: остатки золоченых обоев по стенам, армейскую койку, простой умывальник и всякие полки, бра и лепные завитки.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="12">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Pnin shook open the casement, smiled at the smiling forest, again remembered a distant first day in the country, and presently walked down, clad in a new navy-blue bathrobe and wearing on his bare feet a pair of ordinary rubber over-shoes, a sensible precaution if one intends to walk through damp and, perhaps, snake-infested grass.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Пнин, подергав, открыл створку окна, улыбнулся улыбчивому лесу, снова вспомнил далекий первый день в деревне, - и скоро уже сошел вниз, облаченный в новый темно-синий купальный халат и пару обыкновенных резиновых галош на босу ногу - предосторожность вполне разумная, когда предстоит идти по сырой и, возможно, кишащей гадами траве.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="13">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">On the garden terrace he found Chateau.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">На садовой террасе он встретил Шато.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="14">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Konstantin Ivanich Chateau, a subtle and charming scholar of pure Russian lineage despite his surname (derived, I am told, from that of a Russianized Frenchman who adopted orphaned Ivan), taught at a large New York university and had not seen his very dear Pnin for at least five years.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Константин Иваныч Шато, тонкий и очаровательный ученый чисто русских кровей, несмотря на фамилию (полученную, как меня уверяли, от обруселого француза, который усыновил Ивана-сироту), преподавал в большом нью-йоркском университете и не виделся со своим дражайшим Пниным самое малое пять лет.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="15">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">They embraced with a warm rumble of joy.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Они обнялись, тепло урча от радости.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="16">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">I confess to have been myself, at one time, under the spell of angelic Konstantin Ivanich, namely, when we used to meet every day in the winter of 1935 or 1936 for a morning stroll under the laurels and nettle trees of Grasse, southern France, where he then shared a villa with several other Russian expatriates.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Должен признаться, я и сам когда-то подпал под обаяние ангельского Константина Иваныча • а именно, в ту пору, как мы ежедневно сходились зимой 35-го не то 36-го года для утренней прогулки под лаврами и цельтисами Грассе, что на юге Франции, (он делил там виллу с несколькими русскими экспатриантами).</se>
  </para>
  <para id="17">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">His soft voice, the gentlemanly St Petersburgan burr of his r's, his mild, melancholy caribou eyes, the auburn goatee he continuously twiddled, with a shredding motion of his long, frail fingers вЂ” everything about Chateau (to use a literary formula as old-fashioned as he) produced a rare sense of well-being in his friends.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Мягкий голос его, рафинированный петербургский раскат его "р", спокойные глаза грустного карибу, рыжеватая козлиная бородка, которую он все теребил крошащими движениями длинных, хрупких пальцев, - все в Шато (пользуясь литературным оборотом, столь же старомодным, как он сам) порождало у его друзей чувство редкой приятности.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="18">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Pnin and he talked for a while, comparing notes.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Несколько времени он и Пнин разговаривали, делясь впечатлениями.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="19">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">As not unusual with firm-principled exiles, every time they met after a separation they not only endeavoured to catch up with a personal past, but also to sum up by means of a few rapid passwords вЂ” allusions, intonations impossible to render in a foreign language вЂ” the course of recent Russian history, thirty-five years of hopeless injustice following a century of struggling justice and glimmering hope.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Как нередко случается с держащимися твердых принципов изгнанниками, они всякий раз, сызнова встречаясь после разлуки, не только стремились встать вровень с личным прошлым друг друга, но и, обмениваясь несколькими быстрыми паролями, - намеками, интонациями, которые невозможно передать на чужом языке, - подводили итог последним событиям русской истории: тридцати пяти годам беспросветной несправедливости, что последовали за столетием борьбы за справедливость и мерцающих вдали надежд.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="20">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Next, they switched to the usual shop talk of European teachers abroad, sighing and shaking heads over the ' typical American college student' who does not know geography, is immune to noise, and thinks education is but a means to get eventually a remunerative job.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Затем они перешли к обычному профессиональному разговору преподавателей-европейцев, оказавшихся вне Европы: вздыхали и качали головами по адресу "типичного американского студента", который не знает географии, наделен иммунитетом к шуму и почитает образование всего лишь за средство для получения в дальнейшем хорошо оплачиваемой должности.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="21">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Then they inquired about each other's work in progress, and both were extremely modest and reticent about their respective researches.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">После того, каждый осведомился у другого, как подвигается его работа, и каждый был до чрезвычайности скромен и сдержан, касаясь своих занятий.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="22">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Finally, as they walked along a meadow path, brushing against the golden rod, toward the wood where a rocky river ran, they spoke of their healths: Chateau, who looked so jaunty, with one hand in the pocket of his white flannel trousers and his lustring coat rather rakishly opened on a flannel waistcoat, cheerfully said that in the near future he would have to undergo an exploratory operation of the abdomen, and Pnin said, laughing, that every time he was X-rayed, doctors vainly tried to puzzle out what they termed' a shadow behind the heart'.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Наконец, уже шагая обросшей канадским златотысячником луговой тропкой к лесу, через который пробегала по каменистому руслу речушка, они заговорили о здоровье: Шато, выглядевший столь беспечным с рукой в кармане белых фланелевых брюк и в щегольски распахнутом поверх фланелевого жилета люстриновом пиджаке, весело сообщил, что в скором будущем ему предстоит сложная полостная операция, а Пнин сказал, смеясь, что всякий раз, как он проходит рентген, доктора тщетно пытаются разобраться в том, что они именуют "тенью за сердцем".</se>
  </para>
  <para id="23">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'Good title for a bad novel,' remarked Chateau.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">- Хорошее название для плохого романа, - заметил Шато.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="24">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">As they were passing a grassy knoll just before entering the wood, a pink-faced venerable man in a seersucker suit, with a shock of white hair and a tumefied purple nose resembling a huge raspberry, came striding toward them down the sloping field, a look of disgust contorting his features.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Перейдя муравчатый пригорок и почти уж войдя в лес, они приметили машисто шагавшего к ним по покатому полю краснолицего, почтенного господина в легком полосатом костюме, с копной седых волос и с лиловатым припухлым носом, похожим на большую малинину; черты его искажала недовольная гримаса.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="25">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'I have to go back for my hat,' he cried dramatically as he drew near.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">- Вот, приходится ворочаться за шляпой, - театрально вскричал он, приблизившись.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="26">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'Are you acquainted?' murmured Chateau, fluttering his hands introductively 'Timofey Pavlich Pnin, Ivan Ilyich Gramineev.'</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">- Вы не знакомы? - промурлыкал Шато и вскинул руки в жесте представления. - Тимофей Павлыч Пнин, Иван Ильич Граминеев.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="27">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'Moyo pochtenie (My respects),' said both men, bowing to each other over a powerful handshake.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">- Мое почтение, - сказали оба, крепко пожимая друг другу руки и кланяясь.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="28">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'I thought,' resumed Gramineev, a circumstantial narrator, 'that the day would continue as overcast as it had begun.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">- Я думал, - продолжал Граминеев, обстоятельный повествователь, - что оно как с утра пошло, так и будет весь день хмурится.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="29">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">By stupidity (po gluposti) I came out with an unprotected head.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">По глупости вылез с непокрытой головой.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="30">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Now the sun is' roasting my brains.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Теперь мне солнце выжигает мозги.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="31">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">I have to interrupt my work.'</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Пришлось прервать работу.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="32">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He gestured toward the top of the knoll.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">И он указал на вершину холма.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="33">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">There his easel stood in delicate silhouette against the blue sky.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Там - тонким силуэтом на фоне синего неба - стоял его мольберт.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="34">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">From that crest he had been painting a view of the valley beyond, complete with quaint old barn, gnarled apple tree, and kine.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">С этого возвышения он писал вид лежащей за ним долины, дополненный причудливым старым амбаром, кривой яблонькой и буренкой.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="35">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'I can offer you my panama,' said kind Chateau, but Pnin had already produced from his bathrobe pocket a large red handkerchief: he expertly twisted each of its corners into a knot.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">- Могу предложить вам мою панаму, - сказал добрый Шато, но Пнин, уже достав из кармана халата большой красный носовой платок, сноровисто вязал узлы на каждом из четырех его уголков.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="36">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'Admirable....</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">- Очаровательно...</se>
  </para>
  <para id="37">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Most grateful,' said Gramineev, adjusting this headgear.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Премного благодарен, - сказал Граминеев, прилаживая этот головной убор.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="38">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'One moment,' said Pnin.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">- Одну минуту, - сказал Пнин.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="39">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'You must tuck in the knots.'</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">- Вы узлы подоткните.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="40">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">This done, Gramineev started walking up the field toward his easel.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Проделав это, Граминеев двинулся полем вверх, к своему мольберту.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="41">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He was a well-known, frankly academic painter, whose soulful oils вЂ” 'Mother Volga', 'Three Old Friends' (lad, nag, dog), 'April Glade', and so forth-still graced a museum in Moscow.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Он был известным, строго академического толка живописцем, чьи задушевные полотна - "Волга-матушка ", "Неразлучная троица" (мальчик, собачка и кляча), "Апрельская прогалина" и тому подобные - по-прежнему украшали московский музей.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="42">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'Somebody told me,' said Chateau, as he and Pnin continued to progress riverward, 'that Liza's boy has an extraordinary talent for painting.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">- Кто-то мне говорил, - сказал Шато, когда они с Пниным подходили к реке, - что у лизиного сына редкий дар к живописи.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="43">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Is that correct?'</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Это правда?</se>
  </para>
  <para id="44">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'Yes,' answered Pnin.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">- Да, - ответил Пнин.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="45">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'All the more vexing (tem bolee obidno) that his mother, who I think is about to marry a third time, took Victor suddenly to California for the rest of the summer, whereas if he had accompanied me here, as had been planned, he would have had the splendid opportunity of being coached by Gramineev.'</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">- Тем более обидно, что его мать, которая, по-моему, вот-вот в третий раз выскочит замуж, вдруг на все лето забрала его в Калифорнию, - а если бы он приехал со мной сюда, как предполагалось, у него была бы великолепная возможность поучиться у Граминеева.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="46">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'You exaggerate the splendour,' softly rejoined Chateau.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">- Вы преувеличиваете ее великолепие, - мягко возразил Шато.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="47">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">They reached the bubbling and glistening stream.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Они достигли пузырящегося, мерцающего потока.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="48">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">A concave ledge between higher and lower diminutive cascades formed a natural swimming pool under the alders and pines.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Вогнутая плита, уместившаяся меж двух водопадиков, верхнего с нижним, образовала естественный плавательный бассейн под соснами и ольхой.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="49">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Chateau, a non-bather, made himself comfortable on a boulder.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Не любитель купаться, Шато с удобством устроился на валуне.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="50">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Throughout the academic year Pnin had regularly exposed his body to the radiation of a sun lamp; hence when he stripped down to his bathing trunks, he glowed in the dappled sunlight of the riverside grove with a rich mahogany tint.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Во весь учебный год Пнин регулярно подставлял свое тело лучам солнечной лампы, поэтому когда он разделся до купальных трусов, оно засветилось под солнцем, пробивающимся сквозь приречные заросли, сочными оттенками красного дерева.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="51">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He removed his cross and his rubbers.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Он снял крест и галоши.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="52">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'Look, how pretty,' said observant Chateau.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">- Взгляните, как мило, - сказал склонный к созерцательности Шато.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="53">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">A score of small butterflies, all of one kind, were settled on a damp patch of sand, their wings erect and closed, showing their pale undersides with dark dots and tiny orange-rimmed peacock spots along the hindwing margins; one of Pnin's shed rubbers disturbed some of them and, revealing the celestial hue of their upper surface, they fluttered around like blue snow-flakes before settling again.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Десятка два мелких бабочек, все одного вида, сидели на влажном песке, приподняв и сложив крылья, так что виднелся их бледный испод в темных точках и крохотных павлиньих глазках с оранжевыми обводами, идущими вдоль кромки задних крыльев; одна из сброшенных Пниным галош вспугнула нескольких бабочек, и обнаружив небесную синеву лицевой стороны крыльев, они запорхали вокруг, как голубые снежинки, и снова опали.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="54">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'Pity Vladimir Vladimirovich is not here,' remarked Chateau.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">- Жаль, нет здесь Владимира Владимировича, - заметил Шато.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="55">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'He would have told us all about these enchanting insects.'</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">- Он рассказал бы нам все об этих чарующих насекомых.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="56">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'I have always had the impression that his entomology was merely a pose.'</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">- Мне всегда казалось, что эта его энтомология - просто поза.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="57">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'Oh no,' said Chateau.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">- О нет, - сказал Шато.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="58">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'You will lose it some day,' he added, pointing to the Greek Catholic cross on a golden chainlet that Pnin had removed from his neck and hung on a twig.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">- Когда-нибудь вы его потеряете, - добавил он, указывая на православный крест на золотой цепочке, снятый Пниным с шеи и повешенный на сучок.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="59">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Its glint perplexed a cruising dragonfly.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Его блеск озадачил пролетавшую стрекозу.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="60">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'Perhaps I would not mind losing it,' said Pnin.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">- Да я, может быть, и не прочь его потерять,- сказал Пнин.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="61">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'As you well know, I wear it merely from sentimental reasons.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">- Вы же знаете, я ношу его лишь по сентиментальным причинам.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="62">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">And the sentiment is becoming burdensome.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">А сантименты становятся обременительны.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="63">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">After all, there is too much of the physical about this attempt to keep a particle of one's childhood in contact with one's breast bone.'</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">В конце концов, в этой попытке удержать, прижимая к груди, частицу детства слишком много телесного.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="64">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'You are not the first to reduce faith to a sense of touch,' said Chateau, who was a practising Greek Catholic and deplored his friend's agnostic attitude.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">- Вы не первый, кто сводит веру к осязанию, - сказал Шато; он был усердным приверженцем православия и сожалел об агностическом расположении друга.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="65">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">A horsefly applied itself, blind fool, to Pnin's bald head, and was stunned by a smack of his meaty palm.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Слепень, подслеповатый олух, уселся Пнину на лысину и был оглушен шлепком его мясистой ладони.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="66">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">From a smaller boulder than the one upon which Chateau was perched, Pnin gingerly stepped down into the brown and blue water.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">С валуна, меньшего, чем тот, на котором расположился Шато, Пнин осмотрительно сошел в коричневую и синюю воду.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="67">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He noticed he still had his wrist-watch вЂ” removed it and left it inside one of his rubbers.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Он заметил, что на руке его остались часы, снял их и положил в галошу.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="68">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Slowly swinging his tanned shoulders, Pnin waded forth, the loopy shadows of leaves shivering and slipping down his broad back.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Медленно поводя загорелыми плечьми, Пнин тронулся вперед, петлистые тени листьев трепетали, скользя по его широкой спине.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="69">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He stopped and, breaking the glitter and shade around him, moistened his inclined head, rubbed his nape with wet hands, soused in turn each armpit, and then, joining both palms, glided into the water, his dignified breast-stroke sending off ripples on either side.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Он остановился и, разбивая блеск и тени вокруг, намочил склоненную голову, протер мокрыми ладонями шею, увлажнил каждую из подмышек и после, сложив ладоши, скользнул в воду. Гонимая благородными жестами стиля брасс, вода струилась по сторонам от него.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="70">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Around the natural basin, Pnin swam in state.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Пнин торжественно плыл вдоль окаема естественного бассейна.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="71">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He swam with a rhythmical splutter вЂ” half gurgle, half puff.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Он плыл, издавая размеренный шум, - полужурчание, полупыхтение.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="72">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Rhythmically he opened his legs and widened them out at the knees while flexing and straightening out his arms like a giant frog.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Он мерно выбрасывал ноги, разводя их в коленях, одновременно складывая и распрямляя руки, похожий на большую лягушку.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="73">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">After two minutes of this, he waded out and sat on the boulder to dry.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Проплавав так две минуты, он вылез из воды и присел на валун - пообсохнуть.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="74">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Then he put on his cross, his wrist-watch, his rubbers, and his bathrobe.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Затем он надел крест, часы, галоши и халат.</se>
  </para>
</body>
</html>
