<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<html>
<head>
</head>
<body>
  <para id="0">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">2</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">2</se>
  </para>
  <para id="1">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Five years later, after spending the beginning of the summer on our estate near St Petersburg, my mother, my young brother, and I happened to visit a dreary old aunt at her curiously desolate country seat not far from a famous resort on the Baltic coast.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Через пять лет, проведя начало лета в нашем поместье под Петербургом, мама, младший брат и я приехали погостить к скучнейшей старой тетке в ее удивительно запущенную усадьбу, расположенную невдалеке от знаменитого балтийского курорта.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="2">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">One afternoon, as in concentrated ecstasy I was spreading, underside up, an exceptionally rare aberration of the Paphia Fritillary, in which the silver stripes ornamenting the lower surface of its hindwings had fused into an even expanse of metallic gloss, a footman came up with the information that the old lady requested my presence.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Как-то после полудня, когда я, испытывая сосредоточенный восторг, расправлял исподом вверх исключительно редкую аберрацию большой перламутровки, у которой серебристые полосы, украшающие изнанку задних крыльев, соединялись, придавая им ровный металлический отлив, вошел слуга с сообщением, что старая госпожа призывает меня к себе.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="3">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">In the reception hall I found her talking to two self-conscious youths in university student uniforms.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Я нашел ее в гостиной за разговором с двумя сконфуженными молодыми людьми в студенческих тужурках.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="4">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">One, with the blond fuzz, was Timofey Pnin, the other with the russet down, was Grigoriy Belochkin.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Один, покрытый светлым пушком, был Тимофеем Пниным, другой, с рыжеватой челкой, - Григорием Белочкиным.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="5">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">They had come to ask my grand-aunt the permission to use an empty barn on the confines of her property for the staging of a play.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Они пришли испросить у моей двоюродной бабушки разрешения использовать стоящую на границе ее владений пустую ригу для постановки пьесы.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="6">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">This was a Russian translation of Arthur Schnitzler's three-act Liebelei.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Ставился русский перевод трехактной "Liebelei" Артура Шницлера.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="7">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Ancharov, a provincial semi-professional actor, with a reputation consisting mainly of faded newspaper clippings, was helping to rig up the thing.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Справиться с этой затеей им помогал Анчаров, полупрофессиональный провинциальный актер, репутация которого зиждилась по-преимуществу на поблеклых газетных вырезках.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="8">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Would I participate?</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Не приму ли и я участия?</se>
  </para>
  <para id="9">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">But at sixteen I was as arrogant as I was shy, and declined to play the anonymous gentleman in Act One.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Однако в шестнадцать лет я был столь же заносчив, сколь и застенчив, - и отверг роль безымянного Господина в акте первом.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="10">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">The interview ended in mutual embarrassment, not alleviated by Pnin or Belochkin overturning a glass of pear kvas, and I went back to my butterfly.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Переговоры закончились общим замешательством, отнюдь не разряженным тем, что Пнин или Белочкин опрокинул стакан грушевого квасу, - и я вернулся к моим бабочкам.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="11">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">A fortnight later I was somehow or other compelled to attend the performance.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Две недели спустя меня каким-то образом уговорили посетить представление.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="12">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">The barn was full of dachniki (vacationists) and disabled soldiers from a nearby hospital.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Ригу заполняли дачники и раненные солдаты из ближнего лазарета.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="13">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">I came with my brother, and next to me sat the steward of my aunt's estate, Robert Karlovich Horn, a cheerful plump person from Riga with bloodshot, porcelain-blue eyes, who kept applauding heartily at the wrong moments.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Я пришел вместе с братом, а с нами рядом сидел эконом бабушкина именья Роберт Карлович Горн, веселый толстяк из Риги с налитыми кровью фарфоровыми глазами, от всей души хлопавший в самых неподходящих местах.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="14">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">I remember the odour of decorative fir branches, and the eyes of peasant children glistening through the chinks in the walls.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Помню запах украсившей ригу хвои, и глаза деревенских детей, поблескивавшие сквозь щели в стенах.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="15">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">The front seats were so close to the stage that when the betrayed husband produced a packet of love-letters written to his wife by Fritz Lobheimer, dragoon and college student, and flung them into Fritz's face, you could see perfectly well that they were old postcards with the stamp corners cut off.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Первые ряды стояли так близко к помосту, что когда обманутый муж выхватил пачку любовных писем, написанных его жене Фрицем Лобгеймером, студентом и драгуном, и швырнул их Фрицу в лицо, было с полной ясностью видно, что это - старые почтовые открытки с отрезанными марочными уголками.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="16">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">I am perfectly sure that the small role of this irate Gentleman was taken by Timofey Pain (though, of course, he might also have appeared as somebody else in the following acts); but a buff overcoat, bushy mustachios, and a dark wig with a median parting disguised him so thoroughly that the minuscule interest I took in his existence might not have warranted any conscious assurance on my part.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Я совершенно убежден, что небольшую роль этого гневного Господина сыграл Тимофей Пнин (хотя, разумеется, в дальнейших актах он мог появляться в иных ролях); впрочем, желтое пальто, пушистые усы и темный парик, посередке разделенный пробором, так преображали его, что микроскопический интерес, возбуждавшийся во мне его существованием, вряд ли может служить порукой какой-либо сознательной уверенности с моей стороны.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="17">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Fritz, the young lover doomed to die in a duel, not only has that mysterious affair backstage with the Lady in Black Velvet, the Gentleman's wife, but toys with the heart of Christine, a naГЇve Viennese maiden.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Фриц, молодой любовник, обреченный пасть на дуэли, не только завел за сценой загадочную интрижку с Дамой в Черном Бархате, женой Господина, он играл также сердцем Христины, наивной венской девушки.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="18">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Fritz was played by stocky, forty-year-old Ancharov, who wore a warm-taupe make-up, thumped his chest with the sound of rug beating, and by his impromptu contributions to the role he had not deigned to learn almost paralysed Fritz's pal, Theodor Kaiser (Grigoriy Belochkin).</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Роль Фрица исполнял плотный сорокалетний Анчаров в жгуче-коричневом гриме, он ударял себя в грудь с таким звуком, будто ковер выбивал, а его импровизированные усовершенствования роли, до заучивания которой он не снизошел, почти парализовали приятеля Фрица - Теодора Кайзера (Григорий Белочкин).</se>
  </para>
  <para id="19">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">A moneyed old maid in real life, whom Ancharov humoured, was miscast as Christine Weiring, the violinist's daughter.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Особа, бывшая в подлинной жизни состоятельной старой девой, которую обхаживал Анчаров, весьма неумело изображала Христину Вейринг, дочь скрипача.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="20">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">The role of the little milliner, Theodor's amoretta, Mizi Schlager, was charmingly acted by a pretty, slender-necked, velvet-eyed girl, Belochkin's sister, who got the greatest ovation of the night.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Роль модисточки Мизи Шлягер, возлюбленной Теодора, очаровательно исполнила хорошенькая девушка с нежной шеей и бархатными глазами, сестра Белочкина, она и заслужила в тот вечер самые долгие рукоплескания.</se>
  </para>
</body>
</html>
