<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<html>
<head>
</head>
<body>
  <para id="0">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">4</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">4</se>
  </para>
  <para id="1">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">In planning her boy's education, Liza had been torn between two libidos: to endow him with the latest benefits of Modern Child Psychotherapy, and to find, among American frames of religious reference, the nearest approach to the melodious and wholesome amenities of the Greek Catholic Church, that mild communion whose demands on one's conscience are so small in comparison with the comforts it offers.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Планируя образование своего сына, Лиза разрывалась между двух либидо: потребностью оделить его новейшими благами современной детской психотерапии и стремлением найти среди американских систем религиозного отсчета наилучшее приближение к мелодическим и благотворным радостям Православия, этого кроткого исповедания, чьи требования к личной совести столь малы в сравнении с утешениями, которые оно предлагает.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="2">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Little Victor at first went to a progressive kindergarten in New Jersey, and then, upon the advice of some Russian friends, attended a day-school there.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Сначала маленький Виктор попал в прогрессивный детский сад в Нью-Джерси, потом, по совету одних русских друзей он посещал там же школу.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="3">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">The school was directed by an Episcopal clergyman who proved to be a wise and gifted educator, sympathetic to superior children, no matter how bizarre or rowdy they might be; Victor was certainly a little peculiar, but on the other hand very quiet.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Управлял школой священник епископальной церкви, зарекомендовавший себя благоразумным и способным учителем, снисходительным к одаренным детям, как бы ни были они чудачливы и скандальны; Виктор определенно был несколько странен, но зато очень тих.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="4">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">At twelve, he went to St Bartholomew's.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">В двенадцать лет он перешел в школу Св.Варфоломея. </se>
  </para>
  <para id="5">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Physically, St Bart's was a great mass of self-conscious red brick, erected in 1869 on the outskirts of Cranton, Massachusetts.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Внешне "Сен-Барт" представлял собой большую массу претенциозного красного кирпича, воздвигнутую в пригороде Крэнтона, штат Массачусетс, в 1869 году.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="6">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Its main building formed three sides of a large quadrangle, the fourth being a cloistered passage.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Главное здание образовывало три стороны большого прямоугольника, четвертую составляла сводчатая галерея.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="7">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Its gabled gatehouse was glossily coated on one side with American ivy and tipped somewhat top-heavily with a Celtic cross of stone.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Островерхую башенку над воротами, покрытую с одного боку лоснистым пятилистным плющом, несколько тяжеловесно венчал каменный кельтский крест.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="8">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">The ivy rippled in the wind like the back skin of a horse.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Ветер рябью бежал по плющу, как по конской спине.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="9">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">The hue of red brick is fondly supposed to grow richer with time; that of good old St Bart's had only grown dirty.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Напрасно считают, что со временем тон красного кирпича становится более сочным, - в добром старом Сен-Барте он становился лишь более грязным.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="10">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Under the cross and immediately over the sonorous-looking but really echo-less arc of the entrance was carved a dagger of sorts, an attempt to represent the butcher's knife so reproachfully held (in the Vienna Missal) by St Bartholomew, one of the Apostles вЂ” the one, namely, who had been flayed alive and exposed to the flies in the summer of A.D. 65 or thereabouts, in Albanopolis, now Derbent, south-eastern Russia.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Ниже креста и прямо над звучной на вид, но на деле совершенно лишенной эха входной аркой было изваяно что-то вроде кинжала, - попытка изобразить мясницкий нож, который так неодобрительно держит (в "Венском Требнике") святой Варфоломей, один из Апостолов, - а именно тот, с которого содрали заживо кожу, оставив его на съедение мухам летом 65 года по Рождеству Христову или около того, в городе Албанополисе, ныне Дербенте, на юго-востоке России.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="11">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">His coffin, when cast by a furious king into the Caspian Sea, had blandly sailed all the way to Lipari Island off the coast of Sicily вЂ” probably a legend, seeing that the Caspian had been strictly an inland affair ever since the Pleistocene.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Гроб его, выброшенный гневливым царем в Kаспийское море, мирно приплыл на остров Липари, что у берегов Сицилии, - последнее, видимо, следует счесть легендой, особенно если принять во внимание, что Каспийское море еще со времен плейстоцена оставалось морем исключительно внутренним.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="12">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Beneath this heraldic weapon вЂ” which rather resembled a carrot pointing upward вЂ” an inscription in burnished church text read: 'Sursum'. Two gentle English shepherd dogs belonging to one of the masters and greatly attached to each other could generally be found drowsing in their private Arcadia on a lawn before the gate.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Под этим геральдическим орудием, напоминавшим скорее нацеленную ввысь морковку, отполированные буквы английской готики выводили "Sursum"1. На мураве перед воротами обыкновенно дремали в своей приватной Аркадии две смирных английских овчарки, принадлежавших одному из учителей и нежно друг к дружке привязанных.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="13">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Liza on her first visit to the school had greatly admired everything about it from the fives courts and the chapel to the plaster casts in the corridors and the photographs of cathedrals in the classrooms.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Лизе при первом посещении школы все здесь очень понравилось, - от площадок для игры в "файвс" и часовни до гипсовых слепков по коридорам и снимков соборов в классных.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="14">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">The three lower forms were assigned to dormitories with windowed alcoves; there was a master's room at the end.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Спальни трех младших классов были поделены на ниши, в каждой свое окно; в конце спальни располагалась комната воспитателя.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="15">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Visitors could not help admiring the fine gymnasium.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Не мог посетитель не восхититься и прекрасным гимнастическим залом.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="16">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Very evocative, too, were the oaken seats and hammer-beamed roof of the chapel, a Romanesque structure that had been donated half a century ago by Julius Schonberg, wool manufacturer, brother of the world-famous Egyptologist Samuel Schonberg who perished in the Messina earthquake.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Весьма также поражали воображение дубовые скамьи и подбалочный свод часовни, полстолетия назад сооруженной в романском стиле на средства Джулиуса Шонберга, шерстяного фабриканта и брата всемирно известного египтолога Сэмюеля Шонберга, погибшего при землетрясении в Мессине.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="17">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">There were twenty-five masters and the headmaster, the Reverend Archibald Hopper, who on warm days wore elegant clerical grey and performed his duties in radiant ignorance of the intrigue that was on the point of dislodging him.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">В школе служили двадцать пять преподавателей и ректор - преподобный Арчибальд Хоппер, облачавшийся в теплые дни в элегантно-серое священническое одеяние и выполнявший свои обязанности в лучезарном неведении интриги, которая вот-вот грозила завершиться его низвержением.</se>
  </para>
</body>
</html>
