<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<html>
<head>
</head>
<body>
  <para id="0">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">8</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">8</se>
  </para>
  <para id="1">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Theoretically, the simplest way to reach Waindell from Cranton was to get by taxi to Framingham, catch a fast train to Albany, and then a local for a shorter stretch in a north-western direction; actually, the simplest way was also the most unpractical one.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Теоретически из Крэнтона проще всего добраться до Вайнделла, взяв такси до Фреймингема, там сев в скорый поезд на Олбани, а в Олбани пересев в местный и проехав немного к северо-западу; на деле же этот простейший способ был также и наименее удобным.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="2">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Whether there was some old solemn feud between those railways, or whether both had united to grant a sporting chance to other means of conveyance, the fact remained that no matter how you juggled with timetables, a three-hour wait at Albany between trains was the briefest you could hope to achieve.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">То ли между двумя железными дорогами существовала застарелая феодальная распря, то ли они сговорились предоставить честный спортивный шанс иным средствам передвижения, факт остается фактом: сколько бы вы ни тасовали расписания, трехчасовое ожидание в Олбани оставалось наикратчайшим из возможных.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="3">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">There was a bus leaving Albany at 11 a.m. and arriving at Waindell at around 3 p.m. but that meant taking the 6.31 a.m. train from Framingham; Victor felt he could not get up in time; he took, instead, a slightly later and considerably slower train that allowed him to catch at Albany the last bus to Waindell, which deposited him there at half past eight in the evening.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Имелся еще автобус, уходивший из Олбани в 11 утра и приходивший в Вайнделл в 3 часа дня, но, чтобы попасть на него, пришлось бы выехать из Фреймингема поездом в 6.31, а Виктор знал, что так рано ему не подняться; вместо этого он отправился чуть более поздним и значительно более медленным поездом, позволявшим попасть в Олбани на последний автобус до Вайнделла; этот автобус и доставил его туда в половине девятого вечера.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="4">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">It rained all the way.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">На всем пути шел дождь.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="5">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">It was raining when he arrived at the Waindell terminal.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Дождь шел и на подступах к вайнделлскому вокзалу.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="6">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Because of a streak of dreaminess and a gentle abstraction in his nature, Victor in any queue was always at its very end.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Из-за присущей его натуре мечтательной и мягкой рассеянности Виктор во всякой очереди неизменно оказывался последним.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="7">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He had long since grown used to this handicap, as one grows used to weak sight or a limp.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Он давно уже свыкся с этим изъяном, как свыкаешься с хромотой или слабым зрением.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="8">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Stooping a little because of his height, he followed without impatience the passengers that filed out through the bus on to the shining asphalt: two lumpy old ladies in semitransparent raincoats, like potatoes in cellophane; a small boy of seven or eight with a crew cut and a frail, hollowed nape; a many-angled, diffident, elderly cripple, who declined all assistance and came out in parts; three rosy-kneed Waindell coeds in shorts; the small boy's exhausted mother; a number of other passengers; and then вЂ” Victor, with a grip in his hand and two magazines under his arm.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Слегка ссутулясь из-за своего роста, он без нетерпения следовал за гуськом вытекавшими из автобуса на сверкающий асфальт пассажирами: две грузные старые дамы в полупрозрачных плащах, похожие на картофелины в целлофане, семи-восьмилетний стриженный ежиком мальчик с хрупкой, украшенной ямочкой шеей, многоугольный, стеснительный пожилой калека, который отверг постороннюю помощь и выбирался из автобуса по частям, троица румяных вайнделлских студенточек в брючках, доходивших до розовых коленок, измаянная мать мальчугана и еще пассажиры, а уж за ними - Виктор с саквояжем в руке и двумя журналами подмышкой.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="9">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">In an archway of the bus station a totally bald man with a brownish complexion, wearing dark glasses and carrying a black brief-case, was bending in amiable interrogatory welcome over the thin-necked little boy, who, however, kept shaking his head and pointing to his mother, who was waiting for her luggage to emerge from the Greyhound's belly.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Под аркой автобусной станции совершенно лысый мужчина, смугловатый, в темных очках и с черным портфелем, склонился в дружелюбных приветственных расспросах к мальчику с тонкой шеей, тот, однако, упрямо качал головой и указывал на мать, ожидавшую когда из чрева "Грейхаунда" появится багаж.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="10">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Shyly and gaily Victor interrupted the quid pro quo. The brown-domed gentleman took off his glasses and, unbending himself, looked up, up, up at tall, tall, tall Victor, at his blue eyes and reddish-brown hair.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Весело и застенчиво Виктор прервал это quid pro quo1. Господин с коричневой лысиной снял очки и, разогнувшись, посмотрел вверх-вверх-вверх на долгого-долгого-долгого Виктора, на его голубые глаза и рыжевато-русые волосы.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="11">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Pnin's well-developed zygomatic muscles raised and rounded his tanned cheeks; his forehead, his nose, and even his large beautiful ears took part in the smile.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Развитые скуловые мускулы Пнина приподнялись, округлив загорелые щеки: лоб, нос, даже крупные красивые уши - все приняло участие в улыбке.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="12">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">All in all, it was an extremely satisfactory meeting.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">В общем и целом, встреча получилась весьма удовлетворительной.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="13">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Pnin suggested leaving the luggage and walking one block вЂ” if Victor was not afraid of the rain (it was pouring hard, and the asphalt glistened in the darkness, tarnlike, under large, noisy trees).</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Пнин предложил оставить багаж и пройтись один квартал, если Виктор не боится дождя (дождь лил, и асфальт, как каровое озеро, блестел в темноте под большими, шумливыми деревами).</se>
  </para>
  <para id="14">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">It would be, Pnin conjectured, a treat for the boy to have a late meal in a diner.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Поздний обед, рассудил Пнин, - это целый праздник для мальчика.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="15">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'You arrived well?</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">- Ты хорошо доехал?</se>
  </para>
  <para id="16">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">You had no disagreeable adventures?'</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Неприятных приключений не было?</se>
  </para>
  <para id="17">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'None, sir.'</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">- Никаких, сэр.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="18">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'You are very hungry?'</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">- Ты очень голоден?</se>
  </para>
  <para id="19">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'No, sir.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">- Нет, сэр.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="20">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Not particularly.'</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Не особенно.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="21">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'My name is Timofey,' said Pnin, as they made themselves comfortable at a window table in the shabby old diner, 'Second syllable pronounced as "muff", ahksent on last syllable, "ey" as in "prey" but a little more protracted.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">- Меня зовут Тимофей, - сказал Пнин, когда они поудобнее уселись перед окном захудалого старого ресторанчика. - Второй слог произносится как "muff"1, а ударение - на последнем слоге, "эй", как в слове "prey"2, но немного протяжнее.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="22">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">"Timofey Pavlovich Pnin ", which means "Timothy the son of Paul."</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">"Тимофей Павлович Пнин", что означает "Тимоти, сын Пола".</se>
  </para>
  <para id="23">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">The pahtronymic has the ahksent on the first syllable and the rest is sloored вЂ” Timofey Pahlch.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">В отчестве ударение на первом слоге, а все остальное глотается, - Тимофей Палыч.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="24">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">I have a long time debated with myself вЂ” let us wipe these knives and forks вЂ” and have concluded that you must call me simply Mr Tim or, even shorter, Tim, as do some of my extremely sympathetic colleagues.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Я долго сам с собой обсуждал этот вопрос, - давай протрем ножи и вилки, - и решил, что ты должен называть меня просто м-р Тим, или еще короче - Тим, как делает кое-кто из моих чрезвычайно симпатичных коллег.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="25">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">It is вЂ” what do you want to eat?</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Это - ты что будешь есть?</se>
  </para>
  <para id="26">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Veal cutlet?</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Телячью отбивную?</se>
  </para>
  <para id="27">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">O.K., I will also eat veal cutlet вЂ” it is naturally a concession to America, my new country, wonderful America which sometimes surprises me but always provokes respect.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">О-кей, я тоже съем телячью отбивную, - это, разумеется, уступка Америке, моей новой родине, чудесной Америке, которая порой поражает меня, но всегда внушает почтение.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="28">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">In the beginning I was greatly embarrassed вЂ” '</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Поначалу я сильно смущался...</se>
  </para>
  <para id="29">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">In the beginning Pnin was greatly embarrassed by the ease with which first names were bandied about in America: after a single party, with an iceberg in a drop of whisky to start and with a lot of whisky in a little tap water to finish, you were supposed to call a grey-templed stranger 'Jim', while he called you' Tim' for ever and ever.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Поначалу Пнин сильно смущался легкостью, с которой в Америке перескакивают на манеру обращаться друг к дружке по именам: после одной-единственной вечеринки с айсбергом в капле виски для начала и со множеством виски, сдобренного каплей водопроводной воды, под конец, ожидается, что ты теперь вечно будете называть незнакомца с седыми висками "Джимом", а он тебя "Тимом".</se>
  </para>
  <para id="30">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">If you forgot and called him next morning Professor Everett (his real name to you) it was (for him) a horrible insult.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Если же ты забывался и наутро обращался к нему "профессор Эверет" (его настоящее имя для вас), это оказывалось (для него) жутким оскорблением.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="31">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">In reviewing his Russian friends throughout Europe and the United States, Timofey Pahlch could easily count at least sixty dear people whom he had intimately known since, say, 1920, and whom he never called anything but Vadim Vadimich, Ivan Hristoforovich, or Samuil Izrailevich, as the case might be, and who called him by his name and patronymic with the same effusive sympathy, over a strong warm handshake, whenever they met: 'Ah, Timofey Pahlch!</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Перебирая своих русских друзей - по всей Европе и Соединенным Штатам, - Тимофей Палыч мог легко насчитать по малости шестьдесят близких ему людей, с которыми он был накоротке знаком года, скажем, с 1920-го и которых никогда не называл иначе, как Вадим Вадимыч, Иван Христофорович или Самуил Израелевич, - каждого по-своему, разумеется, - и они, столь же тепло к нему расположенные, называли его по имени-отчеству, крепко пожимая при встрече руку: "А-а, Тимофей Палыч!</se>
  </para>
  <para id="32">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Nu kak?</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Ну как?</se>
  </para>
  <para id="33">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">(Well how?) A vГЇ, baten'ka, zdorovo postareli (Well, well, old boy, you certainly don't look any younger)!'</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">А вы, батенька, здорово постарели!".</se>
  </para>
  <para id="34">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Pnin talked.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Пнин говорил.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="35">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">His talk did not amaze Victor, who had heard many Russians speak English, and he was not bothered by the fact that Pnin pronounced the word 'family' as if the first syllable were the French for 'woman'.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Виктора его говор не удивлял, - он слышал немало русских, говоривших по-английски, и не смущался тем, что Пнин произносит слово "family"3 так, словно первый его слог это "женщина" по-французски.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="36">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'I speak in French with much more facility than in English,' said Pnin, 'but you вЂ” vous comprenez le franГ§ais?</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">- Мне по-французски легче говорить, чем по-английски, • сказал Пнин, - а ты, vous comprenez le franзais?</se>
  </para>
  <para id="37">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Bien?</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Bien?</se>
  </para>
  <para id="38">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Assez bien?</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Assez bien?</se>
  </para>
  <para id="39">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Un peu?'</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Un peu?4</se>
  </para>
  <para id="40">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'TrГЁs un peu,' said Victor.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">- Trиs un peu5, - сказал Виктор.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="41">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'Regrettable, but nothing to be done.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">- Жаль, но ничего не поделаешь.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="42">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">I will now speak to you about sport.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Теперь я тебе расскажу про спорт. Первое в русской литературе описание бокса мы находим в стихотворении Михаила Лермонтова, родившегося в 1814-м году и убитого в 1841-м, - очень легко запомнить.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="43">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">The first description of box in Russian literature we find in a poem by Mihail Lermontov, born 1814, killed 1841 вЂ” easy to remember.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Напротив, первое описание тенниса можно обнаружить в романе Толстого "Анна Каренина", оно относится к 1875 году.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="44">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">The first description of tennis, on the other hand, is found in Anna Karenina, Tolstoy's novel, and is related to year 1875. In youth one day, in the Russian countryside, latitude of Labrador, a racket was given to me to play with the family of the Orientalist Gotovtsev, perhaps you have heard, It was, I recollect, a splendid summer day and we played, played, played until all the twelve balls were lost.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Однажды, в пору моей юности, - это было в России, в сельской местности, на широте Лабрадора, - мне дали ракетку, чтобы я поиграл с семьей ("family") востоковеда Готовцева, ты, может быть, слышал о нем. Стоял, помнится, чудный летний день, мы играли, играли, играли, пока не потеряли все двенадцать мячей.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="45">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">You also will recollect the past with interest when old.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Тебе тоже, когда ты состаришься, интересно будет вспомнить о прошлом.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="46">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'Another game,' continued Pnin, lavishly sugaring his coffee, 'was naturally kroket.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">- Другой игрой, - продолжал Пнин, обильно подслащивая свой кофе, - был, натурально, крокет.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="47">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">I was a champion of kroket.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Я был чемпионом крокета.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="48">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">However, the favourite national recreation was so-called gorodki, which means "little towns".</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Впрочем, любимой народной потехой были так называемые "городки", что означает "маленькие города".</se>
  </para>
  <para id="49">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">One remembers a place in the garden and the wonderful atmosphere of youth: I was strong, I wore an embroidered Russian shirt, nobody plays now such healthy games.'</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Помню площадку в саду и чудесное ощущение юности: я был крепок, ходил в вышитой русской рубахе, теперь никто не играет в такие здоровые игры.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="50">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He finished his cutlet and proceeded with the subject:</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Он покончил с отбивной и продолжил изложение своего предмета.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="51">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'One drew,' said Pnin, 'a big square on the ground, one placed there, like columns, cylindrical pieces of wood, you know, and then from some distance one threw at them a thick stick, very hard, like a boomerang, with a wide, wide development of the arm вЂ” excuse me вЂ” fortunately it is sugar, not salt.'</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">- На земле, - рассказывал Пнин, - рисовали большой квадрат и устанавливали в нем такие цилиндрические деревянные плашки, вроде колонн, представляешь? - а потом с некоторого расстояния метали в них толстую палку, с силой, как бумеранг, - таким широким взмахом руки, - извини меня, - к счастью это не соль, а сахар.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="52">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'I still hear,' said Pnin, picking up the sprinkler and shaking his head a little at the surprising persistence of memory, 'I still hear the trakh! the crack when one hit the wooden pieces and they jumped in the air.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">- Я и теперь еще слышу, - говорил Пнин, поднимая дырчатую сахарницу и покачивая головой в удивлении перед упорством памяти, - и теперь еще слышу "трах!", когда кто-нибудь попадал по деревяшкам, и они взлетали на воздух.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="53">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Will you not finish the meat?</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Ты почему не доедаешь?</se>
  </para>
  <para id="54">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">You do not like it?'</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Не нравится?</se>
  </para>
  <para id="55">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'It's awfully good,' said Victor, 'but I am not very hungry.'</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">- Ужасно вкусно, - сказал Виктор, - но я не голоден.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="56">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'Oh, you must eat more, much more if you want to be a footballist.'</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">- О, ты должен есть больше, гораздо больше, если хочешь стать футболистом.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="57">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'I'm afraid I don't care much for football, In fact, I hate football.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">- Боюсь, я равнодушен к футболу. Вернее, я его терпеть не могу.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="58">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">I'm not very good at any game, really,'</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Сказать по правде, я и в других играх не очень силен.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="59">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'You are not a lover of football?' said Pnin, and a look of dismay crept over his large expressive face.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">- Ты не любишь футбола? - спросил Пнин и на его выразительном лице появилось испуганное выражение.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="60">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He pursed his lips, He opened them вЂ” but said nothing.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Он выпучил губы. Он раскрыл их, - но ничего не сказал.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="61">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">In silence he ate his vanilla ice-cream, which contained no vanilla and was not made of cream.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Молча съел он ванильное сливочное мороженое, в котором ванили не было, да и делали его не из сливок.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="62">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'We will now take your luggage and a taxi,' said Pnin.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">- А теперь мы заберем твой багаж и такси, - сказал Пнин.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="63">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">As soon as they reached the Sheppard House, Pnin ushered Victor into the parlour and rapidly introduced him to his landlord, old Bill Sheppard, formerly superintendent of the college grounds (who was totally deaf and wore a white button in one ear), and to his brother, Bob Sheppard, who had recently come from Buffalo to live with Bill after the latter's wife died.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Как только они достигли Шеппард-хауза, Пнин затащил Виктора в гостиную и торопливо познакомил его с хозяином, старым Биллом Шеппардом, прежним управляющим хозяйством колледжа (совершенно глухим, с кнопкой в ухе), и с его братом, Бобом Шеппардом, приехавшим недавно из Буффало, чтобы жить с Биллом после того, как жена Билла скончалась.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="64">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Leaving Victor with them for a minute, Pnin hastily stomped upstairs.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">На минуту оставив Виктора с ними, Пнин торопливо затопотал наверх.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="65">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">The house was a vulnerable construction, and objects in the rooms downstairs reacted with various vibrations to the vigorous footsteps on the upper landing and to the sudden rasp of a window sash in the guest room.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Дом был легко уязвимым строением, и обстановка внизу отозвалась разнообразными вибрациями на топот вверху и на внезапный скрежет оконной рамы в комнате для гостей.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="66">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'Now that picture there,' deaf Mr Sheppard was saying, pointing with a didactic finger at a large muddy water colour on the wall, 'represents the farm where my brother and I used to spend summers fifty years ago.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">- Или вот эта картина, - говорил глухой мистер Шеппард, тыча нравоучительным пальцем в висящую на стене большую мутную акварель, - тут изображена ферма, на которой мы с братом обычно проводили лето годов, этак, пятьдесят назад.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="67">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">It was painted by my mother's schoolmate, Grace Wells: her son, Charlie Wells, owns that hotel in Waindellville вЂ” I am sure Dr Neen has met him вЂ” a very, very fine man.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Ее написала мамина школьная подруга, Грэйс Уэллс, у ее сына, Чарли Уэллса, отель в Вайнделлвилле, по-моему, доктор Нин его знает • очень, очень хороший человек.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="68">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">My late wife was an artist too.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Покойница-жена тоже рисовала.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="69">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">I shall show you some works of hers in a moment.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Я вам сейчас покажу кое-какие ее работы.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="70">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Well, that tree there, behind that barn вЂ” you can just make it out вЂ”</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Ну, вот хоть это дерево, видите, за амбаром, - его и не углядишь...</se>
  </para>
  <para id="71">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">A terrible clatter and crash came from the stairs: Pnin, on his way down, had lost his footing.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Страшные треск и грохот донеслись с лестницы. Пнин, по пути вниз, оступился.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="72">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'In the spring of 1905,' said Mr Sheppard, wagging his index at the picture, 'under that cottonwood tree вЂ” '</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">- Весной 1905 года, - говорил мистер Шеппард, угрожая картине пальцем, - под этим самым тополем...</se>
  </para>
  <para id="73">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He noticed that his brother and Victor had hurried out of the room to the foot of the stairs.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Он увидел, как брат вместе с Виктором бросились из комнаты к подножию лестницы.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="74">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Poor Pnin had come down the last steps on his back.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Бедный Пнин проехался спиной по последним ступенькам.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="75">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He lay supine for a moment, his eyes moving to and fro.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">С минуту он пролежал навзничь, туда-сюда поводя глазами.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="76">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He was helped to his feet.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Ему помогли подняться.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="77">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">No bones were broken.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Кости остались целы.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="78">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Pnin smiled and said: 'It is like the splendid story of Tolstoy вЂ” you must read one day, Victor вЂ” about Ivan Ilyich Golovin who fell and got in consequence kidney of the cancer.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Улыбнувшись, Пнин сказал: - Совсем как в превосходном рассказе Толстого, - ты должен как-нибудь прочитать его, Виктор, - про Ивана Ильича Головина, который тоже упал и приобрел впоследствии почку рака.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="79">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Victor will now come upstairs with me.'</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Теперь Виктор пойдет со мной наверх.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="80">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Victor followed, with grip.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">С саквояжем в руке Виктор последовал за Пниным.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="81">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">There was a reproduction of Van Gogh's 'La Berceuse' on the landing and Victor, in passing, acknowledged it with a nod of ironic recognition.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">На площадке висела репродукция "La Berceuse"1 Ван-Гога, и Виктор походя приветствовал ее кивком иронического узнавания.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="82">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">The guest room was full of the noise of the rain falling on fragrant branches in the framed blackness of the open window.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Комнату для гостей заполнил шум дождя, лившего по душистым ветвям в черноте, обрамленной раскрытым окном.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="83">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">On the desk lay a wrapped-up book and a ten-dollar bill.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">На столе лежала завернутая книга и десятидолларовая бумажка.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="84">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Victor beamed and bowed to his gruff but kindly host.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Виктор просиял и поклонился хмуроватому, но доброму хозяину.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="85">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'Unwrap,' said Pain.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">"Разверни-ка", - сказал Пнин.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="86">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">With courteous eagerness, Victor obeyed.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">С учтивой готовностью Виктор подчинился.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="87">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Then he sat down on the edge of the bed and, his auburn hair coming down in glossy lanks over his right temple, his striped tie dangling out of the front of his grey jacket, his bulky grey flannelled knees parted, zestfully opened the book.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Он присел на край кровати, - русые волосы лоснистыми прядями упали на правый висок, полосатый галстук повис, выбившись из-под серой куртки, раздвинулись нескладные затянутые серой фланелью колени, - и живо открыл книгу.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="88">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He in. tended to praise it вЂ” first, because it was a gift, and second, because he believed it to be a translation from Pnin's mother tongue.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Он собирался ее похвалить, во-первых, потому что это подарок и, во-вторых, он думал, что книга переведена с родного языка Пнина.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="89">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He remembered there had been at the Psychotherapeutic Institute a Dr Yakov London from Russia.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Он помнил, что в Психометрическом институте работал доктор Яков Лондон, уроженец России.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="90">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Rather unfortunately, Victor lit upon a passage about Zarinska, the Yukon Indian Chief's daughter, and light-heartedly mistook her for a Russian maiden.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">На беду, Виктору подвернулся абзац о Заринске, дочери вождя юконских индейцев, и он с легким сердцем принял ее за русскую барышню.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="91">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'Her great black eyes were fixed upon her tribesmen in fear and in defiance.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">"В больших черных глазах ее, устремленных на сородичей, были и страх и вызов.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="92">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">So extreme the tension, she had forgotten to breathe...'</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Все ее существо напряглось, как натянутая тетива, она даже дышать забывала..."1</se>
  </para>
  <para id="93">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'I think I'm going to like this,' said polite Victor.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">- Я думаю, мне это понравится, - сказал вежливый Виктор.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="94">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'Last summer I read Crime and вЂ” ' A young yawn distended his staunchly smiling mouth.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">- Прошлым летом я читал "Преступление и..." - Молодой зевок растянул стойко улыбавшийся рот.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="95">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">With sympathy, with approval with heartache Pain looked at Liza yawning after one of those long happy parties at the Arbenins' or the Polyanskis' in Paris, fifteen, twenty, twenty-five years ago.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">С приязнью, с одобрением, с болью сердечной смотрел Пнин на Лизу, раззевавшуюся после долгого, счастливого вечера у Арбениных или Полянских, - в Париже, пятнадцать, двадцать, двадцать пять лет назад.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="96">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'No more reading today,' said Pain.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">- Довольно чтения на сегодня, - сказал Пнин.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="97">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'I know that it is a very exciting book but you will read and read tomorrow.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">- Я знаю, это очень увлекательная книга, но ты сможешь читать и читать ее завтра.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="98">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">I wish you good night.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Желаю тебе спокойной ночи.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="99">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">The bathroom is across the landing.'</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Ванная напротив, через площадку.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="100">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He shook hands with Victor and marched to his own room.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">И пожав Виктору руку, он ушел в свою комнату.</se>
  </para>
</body>
</html>
