<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<html>
<head>
</head>
<body>
  <para id="0">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">2</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">2</se>
  </para>
  <para id="1">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He had returned for a spell to the College Home, but so had the pavement drillers, and there had cropped up other nuisances besides.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Он вернулся до поры в Общежитие, однако то же самое сделали и сверлильщики тротуара, да кроме них подоспели и новые неудобства.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="2">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">At present Pnin was still renting the pink-walled, white-flounced second-floor bedroom in the Clements' house, and this was the first house he really liked and the first room he had occupied for more than a year.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Сейчас Пнин все еще снимал розовостенную в белых оборках спальню на втором этаже дома Клементсов, это был первый дом, который ему по-настоящему нравился, и первая комната, в которой он прожил более года.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="3">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">By now he had weeded out all trace of its former occupant; or so he thought, for he did not notice, and probably never would, a funny face scrawled on the wall just behind the headboard of the bed and some half-erased height-level marks pencilled on the doorjamb, beginning from a four-foot altitude in 1940.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">К нынешнему времени он окончательно выполол все следы ее прежней жилицы, во всяком случае, так он полагал, ибо не заметил и, видимо, не заметит уже никогда веселую рожицу, нарисованную на стене как раз за изголовьем кровати, да несколько полустершихся карандашных отметок на дверном косяке, первая из которых - на высоте в четыре фута - появилась в 1940 году.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="4">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">For more than a week now, Pnin had had the run of the house: Joan Clements had left by plane for a Western state to visit her married daughter, and a couple of days later, at the very beginning of his spring course in philosophy, Professor Clements, summoned by a telegram, had flown West too.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Вот уже больше недели Пнин один управлялся в доме: Джоан Клементс улетела в западный штат навестить замужнюю дочь, а два дня спустя, - едва начав весенний курс философии, - улетел на Запад и профессор Клементс, вызванный телеграммой.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="5">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Our friend had a leisurely breakfast, pleasantly based on the milk that had not been discontinued, and at half past nine prepared for his usual walk to the campus.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Наш друг неторопливо съел завтрак, приятную основу коего составило молоко, по-прежнему поступавшее в дом, и в половине девятого был готов к ежедневному походу в кампус.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="6">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">It warmed my heart, the Russian-intelligentski way he had of getting into his overcoat: his inclined head would demonstrate its ideal baldness, and his large, Duchess of Wonderland chin would firmly press against the crossed ends of his green muffler to hold it in place on his chest while, with a jerk of his broad shoulders, he contrived to get into both armholes at once; another heave and the coat was on.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Сердце мое согревает тот российско-интеллигентский способ, посредством которого Пнин попадает внутрь своего пальто: склоненная голова обнаруживает ее совершенную голизну, подбородок, длинный, как у Герцогини из Страны Чудес, крепко прижимает перекрещенные концы зеленого шарфа, удерживая их на груди в требуемом положении, а Пнин тем временем, вскидывая широкие плечи, исхитряется попасть руками в обе проймы сразу, еще рывок, - и пальто надето.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="7">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He picked up his portfel' (brief-case), checked its contents, and walked out.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Он подхватил свой портфель, проверил его содержимое и вышел.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="8">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He was still at a newspaper's throw from his porch when he remembered a book the college library had urgently requested him to return, for the use of another reader.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Уже находясь от крыльца на расстоянии, равном броску газеты, Пнин вдруг вспомнил о книге, которую библиотека колледжа настоятельно просила вернуть, чтобы ею мог воспользоваться другой читатель.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="9">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">For a moment he struggled with himself; he still needed the volume; but kindly Pnin sympathized too much with the passionate clamour of another (unknown) scholar not to go back for the stout and heavy tome: It was Volume 18 вЂ” mainly devoted to Tolstoyana вЂ” of Sovetskiy Zolotoy Fond LiteraturГЇ (Soviet Gold Fund of Literature), Moskva-Leningrad, 1940.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Минуту он боролся с собой, книга была еще нужна ему, однако слишком сильное сочувствие испытывал добрый Пнин к пылкому призыву иного (неведомого ему) ученого, чтобы не вернуться за толстым и увесистым томом: то был том 18-й, - посвященный преимущественно Толстому, - "Советского Золотого Фонда Литературы", Москва-Ленинград, 1940.</se>
  </para>
</body>
</html>
