<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<html>
<head>
</head>
<body>
  <para id="0">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">6</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">6</se>
  </para>
  <para id="1">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">This being Tuesday, he could walk over to his favourite haunt immediately after lunch and stay there till dinner time.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Поскольку был вторник, он мог сразу же после обеда отправиться в излюбленное свое прибежище и оставаться там до самого ужина.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="2">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">No gallery connected Waindell College Library with any other buildings, but it was intimately and securely connected with Pnin's heart.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Не существовало галереи, которая соединяла бы библиотеку Уэйндельского университета с его прочими зданиями, зато она самыми надежными и прочными узами соединена была с сердцем Пнина.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="3">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He walked past the great bronze figure of the first president of the college, Alpheus Frieze, in sports cap and knickerbockers, holding by its horns the bronze bicycle he was eternally about to mount, judging by the position of his left foot, forever glued to the left pedal.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Он прошел мимо огромной бронзовой фигуры первого президента университета Альфеуса Фриза, облаченного в спортивную кепку и бриджи, держащего за рога бронзовый велосипед и вечно намеревавшегося вскочить в седло, если судить по положению его левой ноги, навсегда прилепившейся к левой педали.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="4">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">There was snow on the saddle and snow in the absurd basket that recent pranksters had attached to the handle bars.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Снег лежал на седле велосипеда, снег заполнял и нелепую корзинку, которую какие-то проказники недавно прицепили к велосипедному рулю.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="5">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'HuliganГЇ' fumed Pnin, shaking his head вЂ” and slipped slightly on a flag of the path that meandered down a turfy slope among the leafless elms.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">"Huligani", — качая головой, скорбно посетовал Пнин — и поскользнулся слегка на плитах дорожки, которая спускалась вниз, петляя по травянистому склону средь безлистых уже вязов.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="6">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Besides the big book under his right arm, he carried in his left hand his brief-case, an old, Central European-looking, black portfel', and this he swung rhythmically by its leathern grip as he marched to his books, to his scriptorium in the stacks, to his paradise of Russian lore.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Кроме толстой книги, зажатой под мышкой, он нес в другой руке свой старый, среднеевропейского вида, черный port- fel', который он держал за кожаную ручку и которым он помахивал в такт, вышагивая к своим книгам, к своей келье монастырского переписчика, к раю русской учености.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="7">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">An elliptic flock of pigeons, in circular volitation, soaring grey, flapping white, and then grey again, wheeled across the limpid, pale sky, above the College Library.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Эллиптическая голубиная стая в своем настойчивом круговращенье, то вдруг воспаряя серо, то трепеща белизной, то снова отливая серым, появлялась и исчезала в бледном прозрачном небе над зданием библиотеки.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="8">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">A train whistled afar as mournfully as in the steppes.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Гудок поезда прозвучал вдали со степной печалью.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="9">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">A skimpy squirrel dashed over a patch of sunlit snow, where a tree trunk's shadow, olive-green on the turf, became greyish blue for a stretch, while the tree itself, with a brisk, scrabbly sound, ascended, naked, into the sky, where the pigeons swept by for a third and last time.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Тощий бельчонок метнулся через солнечное пятно на снегу, туда, где тень ствола, оливково-зеленая на траве, становилась на время серовато-синей, а сам ствол, с царапучим и шустрым скрипом, возносил свои голые сучъя в небо, где в третий, и в последний, раз пронеслись голуби.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="10">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">The squirrel, invisible now in a crotch, chattered, scolding the delinquents who would pot him out of his tree.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Бельчонок, скрытый теперь в каком-то развилке, сердито стрекотал, брюзжа на хулиганов, выживших его с дерева.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="11">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Pnin, on the dirty black ice of the flagged path, slipped again, threw up one arm in an abrupt convulsion, regained his balance, and, with a solitary smile, stooped to pick up Zol.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">На черном, грязном льду, покрывавшем мощенную плитами дорожку, Пнин поскользнулся снова, судорожно выбросил вперед руку, но, едва восстановив равновесие, улыбнулся тайной улыбкой и наклонился, чтоб подобрать с земли том Zol.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="12">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Fond Lit., which lay wide open to a snapshot of a Russian. pasture with Lyov Tolstoy trudging across it toward the camera and some long-maned horses behind him, their innocent heads turned toward the photographer too.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Fond Lit., раскрывшийся на фотографии русского луга, по которому прямо на фотокамеру брел Лев Толстой, а за его спиной — какието долгогривые лошади, тоже обратившие к фотографу свои невинные морды.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="13">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">V boyu li, v stranstvii, v volnah?</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">V boyu li, v stranstvii, v volnah?</se>
  </para>
  <para id="14">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">In fight, in travel, or in waves?</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">В бою ли, в странствии, в волнах?</se>
  </para>
  <para id="15">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Or on the Waindell campus?</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Или в уэйндельском кампусе?</se>
  </para>
  <para id="16">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Gently champing his dentures, which retained a sticky layer of cottage cheese, Pnin went up the slippery library steps.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Осторожно чмокая вставными зубами, к которым пристал липучий прессованный творог, Пнин поднялся по скользким ступеням библиотеки.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="17">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Like so many ageing college people, Pnin had long ceased to notice the existence of students on the campus, in the corridors, in the library вЂ” anywhere, in brief, save in functional classroom concentrations.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Как многие стареющие преподаватели, Пнин давно уже перестал замечать студентов на территории кампуса, в коридорах, в библиотеке — короче, везде, кроме собственных уроков, где от него требовалось специальное к ним внимание.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="18">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">In the beginning, he had been much upset by the sight of some of them, their poor young heads on their forearms, fast asleep among the ruins of knowledge; but now, except for a girl's comely nape here and there, he saw nobody in the Reading Room.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Вначале он очень огорчался, видя, как иные из них, опустив на скрещенные руки свои бедные головы, мгновенно засыпают за столом среди обломков учености; теперь же, если не считать какой-нибудь симпатичной девичьей шейки здесь или там, он вообще никого не замечал в читальном зале.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="19">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Mrs Thayer was at the circulation desk.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Миссис Тэйер дежурила за столом выдачи.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="20">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Her mother and Mrs Clements' mother had been first cousins.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Ее мать и матушка миссис Клементс были двоюродные сестры.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="21">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'How are you today, Professor Pnin?'</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">— Как поживаете, профессор Пнин?</se>
  </para>
  <para id="22">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'I am very well, Mrs Fire.'</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">— Я поживаю очень хорошо, миссис Файэр.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="23">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'Laurence and Joan aren't back yet, are they?'</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">— Лоренс и Джоун еще не вернулись?</se>
  </para>
  <para id="24">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'No.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">— Нет.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="25">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">I have brought this book back because I received this card вЂ” '</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Я приносил назад эту книгу, потому что я получал открытку...</se>
  </para>
  <para id="26">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'I wonder if poor Isabel will really get divorced.'</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">— Неужели бедная Изабел в самом деле с ним разойдется?</se>
  </para>
  <para id="27">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'I have not heard. Mrs Fire, permit me to ask вЂ” '</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">— Я не услышал, миссис Файэр, разрешите мне спрашивать...</se>
  </para>
  <para id="28">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'I suppose we'll have to find you another room, if they bring her back with them.'</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">— Вероятно, нам придется подыскать вам другую комнату, если они ее с собой привезут.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="29">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'Mrs Fire, permit me to ask something or other.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">— Миссис Файэр, разрешите мне спрашивать коекакое.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="30">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">This card which I received yesterday вЂ” could you maybe tell me who is the other reader?'</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Эта открытка, которую я вчера получал — может, вы могли бы мне говорить, кто этот другой читатель?</se>
  </para>
  <para id="31">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'Let me check.'</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">— Сейчас проверим.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="32">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">She checked.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Она проверила.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="33">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">The other reader proved to be Timofey Pnin; Volume 18 had been requested by him the Friday before.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Другим читателем оказался Тимофей Пнин; он затребовал 18-й том в прошлую пятницу.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="34">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">It was also true that this Volume 18 was already charged to this Pnin, who had had it since Christmas and now stood with his hands upon it, like an ancestral picture of a magistrate.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Правда, этот же самый 18-й том был записан за этим же самым Пниным, который держал его с самого Рождества, а теперь стоял, возложив на него руки, точно судья на парадном портрете.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="35">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'It can't be!' cried Pnin.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">— Не может бывать! — вскричал Пнин.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="36">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'I requested on Friday Volume 19, year 1947, not 18, year 1940'</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">— Я потребовал в пятницу том девятнадцатый, год 1947-й, а не том восемнадцатый, год 1940-й.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="37">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'But look вЂ” you wrote Volume 18. Anyway, 19 is still being processed.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">— Но сами взгляните — вы написали "том 18". Так или иначе, 19-й том еще в обработке.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="38">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Are you keeping this?'</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Оставите этот?</se>
  </para>
  <para id="39">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'18, 19,' muttered Pnin.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">— Восемнадцатый, девятнадцатый, — бормотал Пнин.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="40">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'There is not great difference!</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">— Не есть много разницы!</se>
  </para>
  <para id="41">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">I put the year correctly, that is important!</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Год я ставил правильно, это есть главное!</se>
  </para>
  <para id="42">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Yes, I still need 18 вЂ” and send to me a more effishant card when 19 available.'</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Да, я еще нуждаюсь в восемнадцатом — пошлите мне более вразумительную открытку, когда том девятнадцатый достижим.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="43">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Growling a little, he took the unwieldy, abashed book to his favourite alcove and laid it down there, wrapped in his muffler.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Все еще ворча немного, он унес неуклюжий и пристыженный том в свой излюбленный альков и уложил его там, завернув в свой шарф.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="44">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">They can't read, these women.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Они просто читать не умеют, эти женщины.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="45">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">The year was plainly inscribed.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Год был ясно обозначен.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="46">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">As usual he marched to the Periodicals Room and there glanced at the news in the latest (Saturday, February 12 вЂ” and this was Tuesday, O Careless Reader!) issue of the Russian-language daily published, since 1918, by an Г©migrГ© group in Chicago.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Как всегда, он проследовал в зал периодики и там проглядел новости в последнем номере (суббота, 12 февраля — а на дворе уже был вторник, о, Беспечный Читатель!) ежедневной русскоязычной газеты, выпускаемой с 1918 года какой-то emigre группой в Чикаго.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="47">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">As usual, he carefully scanned the advertisements.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Как всегда, внимательно проглядел объявления.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="48">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Dr Popov, photographed in his new white smock, promised elderly people new vigour and joy.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Доктор Попов, который тут же и был сфотографирован в новом белом халате, сулил пожилым людям новый прилив силы и радости.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="49">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">A music corporation listed Russian phonograph records for sale, such as 'Broken Life, a Waltz' and 'The Song of a Front-Line Chauffeur'.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Музыкальная ассоциация перечисляла имеющиеся в продаже русские патефонные пластинки вроде вальса "Разбитая жизнь" и "Песенки фронтового шофера".</se>
  </para>
  <para id="50">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">A somewhat Gogolian mortician praised his hearses de luxe, which were also available for picnics.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Какойто гоголевского типа похоронщик расхваливал свои похоронные экипажи de luxe, которые можно было также использовать для выезда на пикник.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="51">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Another Gogolian person, in Miami, offered 'a two-room apartment for non-drinkers (dlya trezvГЇh), among fruit trees and flowers', while in Hammond a room was wistfully being let' in a small quiet family' вЂ” and for no special reason the reader suddenly saw, with passionate and ridiculous lucidity, his parents, Dr Pavel Pnin and Valeria Pnin, he with a medical journal, she with a political review, sitting in two armchairs, facing each other in a small, cheerfully lighted drawing room on Galernaya Street, St Petersburg, forty years ago.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Другой гоголевский персонаж, уже в Майами, предлагал "двухкомнатную квартиру для непьющих (dlya trezvih), среди фруктовых деревьев и цветов", а какие-то люди из Хэммонда с грустью предлагали сдать комнату "в небольшой и тихой семье", — и тут, без особой к тому причины, читатель объявлений вдруг с пронзительной и нелепой отчетливостью увидел своих родителей, Павла Пнина и Валерию Пнину — он читает медицинский журнал, она политический обзор, оба сидят в креслах друг против друга в маленькой, ярко освещенной гостиной на Галерной улице, Санкт-Петербург, сорок лет тому назад.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="52">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He also perused the current item in a tremendously long and tedious controversy between three Г©migrГ© factions.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Пнин внимательно ознакомился также с развитием бесконечно долгой и нудной полемики между тремя эмигрантскими фракциями.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="53">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">It had started by Faction A's accusing Faction B of inertia and illustrating it by the proverb.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Начало ей положила фракция А, обвинившая фракцию Б в бездействии и для наглядности проиллюстрировавшая ее пословицей: "Хочет на елку влезть, да ляжки боится окарябать".</se>
  </para>
  <para id="54">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'He wishes to climb the fir tree but is afraid to scrape his shins.' This had provoked an acid Letter to the Editor from' An Old Optimist', entitled 'Fir Trees and Inertia' and beginning: 'There is an old American saying "He who lives in a glass house should not try to kill two birds with one stone".' In the present issue, there was a two-thousand-word feuilleton contributed by a representative of Faction C and headed 'On Fir Trees, Glass Houses, and Optimism', and Pnin read this with great interest and sympathy.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Это побудило некоего Старого Оптимиста написать язвительное "Письмо к редактору", озаглавленное "О елках и о бездействии" и начинавшееся так: "Есть старая американская поговорка: "В доме повешенного не убивают двух зайцев одним выстрелом". В свежем номере газеты был напечатан feuilleton длиной в две тысячи слов, присланный представительной фракцией В и озаглавленнный "О елках, о домах повешенного и оптимизме", Пнин прочел его с большим интересом и с чувством солидарности.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="55">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He then returned to his carrell for his own research.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Потом он вернулся к себе в келью, к теме своего исследования.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="56">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He contemplated writing a Petite Histoire of Russian culture, in which a choice of Russian Curiosities, Customs, Literary Anecdotes, and so forth would be presented in such a way as to reflect in miniature la Grande Histoire вЂ” Major Concatenations of Events.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Он задумывал написать Petite Histoire русской культуры, в которой отбор русских обычаев, редкостей, литературных анекдотов и тому подобного сделан был бы таким образом, что отражал бы в миниатюре La Grande Histoire(*1) — Великую Взаимосвязь Событий.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="57">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He was still at the blissful stage of collecting his material; and many good young people considered it a treat and an honour to see Pnin pull out a catalogue drawer from the comprehensive bosom of a card cabinet and take it, like a big nut, to a secluded corner and there make a quiet mental meal of it, now moving his lips in soundless comment, critical, satisfied, perplexed, and now lifting his rudimentary eyebrows and forgetting them there, left high upon his spacious brow where they remained long after all trace of displeasure or doubt had gone.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Пнин находился еще на блаженной стадии сбора материалов; и многие молодые люди почитали за честь и за удовольствие наблюдать, как Пнин извлекает ящик с карточками из обширной груды каталога и, точно огромный орех, уносит его в укромный уголок и там в тиши наслаждается этой умственной пищей, беззвучно шевелит губами, критически, одобрительно или озадаченно комментируя прочитанное, а то вдруг высоко поднимет свои зачаточные брови, да так и забудет их там, в вышине, на обширном лбу, где они еще долго маячат после того, как все прочие следы неудовольствия или сомнения исчезнут с его лица.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="58">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He was lucky to be at Waindell.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Ему повезло в Уэйнделе.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="59">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Sometime in the nineties the eminent bibliophile and Slavist John Thurston Todd (his bearded bust presided over the drinking fountain) had visited hospitable Russia, and after his death the books he had amassed there quietly chuted into a remote stack.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Когда-то, еще в девяностые годы, знаменитый библиофил и славист Джон Терстон Тодд (его бородатый бюст возвышался над питьевым фонтанчиком) посетил гостеприимную Россию, а после его смерти книги, которые он там насобирал, безропотно удалились на дальний стеллаж.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="60">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Wearing rubber gloves so as to avoid being stung by the amerikanski electricity in the metal of the shelving, Pnin would go to those books and gloat over them: obscure magazines of the Roaring Sixties in marbled boards; century-old historical monographs, their somnolent pages foxed with fungus spots; Russian classics in horrible and pathetic cameo bindings, whose moulded profiles of poets reminded dewy-eyed Timofey of his boyhood, when he could idly palpate on the book cover Pushkin's slightly chafed side whisker or Zhukovski's smudgy nose.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">В резиновых перчатках, чтоб избежать при соприкосновении с железной полкой удара электричества, Пнин добирался до этих книг и наслаждался их лицезрением: забытые журналы Ревущих Шестидесятых в переплетах под мрамор; исторические монографии вековой давности, их сонные страницы покрыты бурыми пятнами плесени; русские классики в ужасных и трогательно-жалких переплетах с камеями поэтических профилей, глядя на которые Пнин с увлажненными глазами вспоминал свое детство, когда он мог подолгу бесцельно гладить на обложке то слегка ободранный бакенбард Пушкина, то грязный нос Жуковского. (*1) большая (великая) история (фр.).</se>
  </para>
  <para id="61">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Today from Kostromskoy's voluminous work (Moscow, 1855) on Russian myths вЂ” a rare book, not to be removed from the library вЂ” Pnin, with a not unhappy sigh, started to copy out a passage referring to the old pagan games that were still practised at the time, throughout the woodlands of the Upper Volga, in the margins of Christian ritual.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Сегодня из обширного труда Костромского (Москва, 1855 год) о русских мифах — редкая книга, выносить из библиотеки воспрещается — Пнин со вздохом, отнюдь не печальным, начал переписывать отрывок, в котором говорилось о древних языческих играх, в те времена еще бытовавших в лесах Верхней Волги, за рамками христианского обряда.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="62">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">During a festive week in May вЂ” the so-called Green Week which graded into Whitsuntide вЂ” peasant maidens would make wreaths of buttercups and frog orchises; then, singing snatches of ancient love chants, they hung these garlands on riverside willows; and on Whit Sunday the wreaths were shaken down into the river, where, unwinding, they floated like so many serpents while the maidens floated and chanted among them.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Во время майских празднеств — так называемой Зеленой недели, постепенно переродившейся в неделю Пятидесятницы, — крестьянские девушки сплетали венки из лютиков и ятрышника; потом, распевая старинные любовные песни, они вешали эти гирлянды и венки на приречные ивы; а в воскресенье на Троицу венки эти сбрасывали в воду, и они плыли, разворачиваясь в воде, как змеи, между тем как девушки плескались и плавали среди них с песнопеньями.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="63">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">A curious verbal association struck Pnin at this point; he could not catch it by its mermaid tail but made a note on his index card and plunged back into Kostromskoy.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">В этом месте в голове у Пнина стала возникать любопытная словесная ассоциация; он не сумел, впрочем, ухватить ее за русалочий хвост, однако сделал пометку на карточке и снова нырнул в Костромского.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="64">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">When Pnin raised his eyes again, it was dinner-time.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Когда Пнин оторвался от книги, уже пора было идти на ужин.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="65">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Doffing his spectacles, he rubbed with the knuckles of the hand that held them his naked and tired eyes and, still in thought, fixed his mild gaze on the window above, where, gradually, through his dissolving meditation, there appeared the violet-blue air of dusk, silver-tooled by the reflection of the fluorescent lights of the ceiling, and, among spidery black twigs, a mirrored row of bright book spines.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Сняв очки, он потер неприкрытые усталые глаза костяшками руки, в которой зажаты были очки, и в задумчивости задержал свой кроткий взгляд на стеклах верхнего окна, где мало-помалу, проступая сквозь дымку его раздумий, стали возникать сине-фиолетовые сумерки, посеребренные отблеском сияющих ламп с потолка, и отражение длинного ряда ярких книжных корешков в паутине черных сучьев.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="66">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Before leaving the library, he decided to look up the correct pronunciation of 'interested', and discovered that Webster, or at least the battered 1930 edition lying on a table in the Browsing Room, did not place the stress accent on the third syllable, as he did.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Прежде чем покинуть библиотеку, он решил посмотреть, как произносится interested ("заинтересован"), и обнаружил, что словарь Вебстера, во всяком случае, тот затрепанный том издания 1930 года, что лежал на столе в Зале Перелистывания, вовсе не рекомендует ставить ударение на третьем слоге, как это всегда делал Пнин.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="67">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He sought a list of errata at the back, failed to find one, and, upon closing the elephantine lexicon, realized with a pang that he had immured somewhere in it the index card with notes that he had been holding all this time.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Он поискал в конце книги список опечаток, но не нашел его и, захлопывая слоноподобный лексикон, осознал вдруг, понял, ощутив при этом болезненный укол, что где-то в его толще захоронил справочную карточку, которую все время держал в руке.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="68">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Must now search and search through 2,500 thin pages, some torn!</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Теперь надо бесконечно долго искать ее между 2500 тончайшими страницами, иные из которых к тому же еще и порваны!</se>
  </para>
  <para id="69">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">On hearing his interjection, suave Mr Case, a lank, pink-faced librarian with sleek white hair and a bow-tie, strolled up, took up the colossus by both ends, inverted it, and gave it a slight shake, whereupon it shed a pocket comb, a Christmas card, Pnin's notes, and a gauzy wraith of tissue paper, which descended with infinite listlessness to Pnin's feet and was replaced by Mr Case on the Great Seals of the United States and Territories.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Услышав его восклицание, обходительный мистер Кэйс, долговязый, розовощекий библиотекарь с прилизанными седыми волосами и галстуком-бабочкой, подошел к Пнину, поднял гиганта за обе крышки, перевернул его и слегка встряхнул, в результате чего словарь просыпал расческу, рождественскую открытку, пнинскую карточку и прозрачный призрак из папиросной бумаги, который с бесконечным безразличием опустился у ног Пнина и был снова водворен мистером Кэйсом на изображение Больших государственных печатей Соединенных Штатов и Территорий.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="70">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Pnin pocketed his index card and, while doing so, recalled without any prompting what he had not been able to recall a while ago:</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Пнин засунул карточку в карман и, совершая эту операцию, вспомнил вдруг без всякой подсказки то, чего только что никак не мог припомнить:</se>
  </para>
  <para id="71">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">...plГЇla i pela, pela i plГЇla...</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">"...plila i pela, pela i plila</se>
  </para>
  <para id="72">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">...she floated and she sang, she sang and floatedвЂ¦</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">...плыла и пела, пела и плыла..."</se>
  </para>
  <para id="73">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Of course!</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Ну, конечно!</se>
  </para>
  <para id="74">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Ophelia's death!</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Смерть Офелии!</se>
  </para>
  <para id="75">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Hamlet!</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">"Гамлет"!</se>
  </para>
  <para id="76">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">In good old Andrey Kroneberg's Russian translation, 1844 вЂ” the joy of Pain's youth, and of his father's and grandfather's young days!</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">В старом добром русском переводе Андрея Кронеберга, год издания 1844-й — утеха его юности, а также юных дней его отца и деда!</se>
  </para>
  <para id="77">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">And here, as in the Kostromskoy passage, there is, we recollect, also a willow and also wreaths.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Здесь, как и в том отрывке из Костромского, присутствует, как мы можем убедиться, та же самая ива, те же присутствуют венки.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="78">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">But where to check properly?</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Но где бы проверить точнее?</se>
  </para>
  <para id="79">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Alas, 'Gamlet' Vil'yama Shekspira had not been acquired by Mr Todd, was not represented in Waindell College Library, and whenever you were reduced to look up something in the English version, you never found this or that beautiful, noble, sonorous line that you remembered all your life from Kroneberg's text in Vengerov's splendid edition.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Увы, "Gamlet" Vil'yama Shekspira не был приобретен мистером Тоддом, и его не было в Университетской библиотеке Уэйндела, а если нужда заставляет вас прибегать к английской версии того же произведения, вам никогда не найти ту или иную прекрасную, благородную, благозвучную строку, которая на всю жизнь запомнилась по переводу Кронеберга в великолепном издании Венгерова.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="80">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Sad!</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Печально!</se>
  </para>
  <para id="81">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">It was getting quite dark on the sad campus.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">На просторах печального кампуса становилось совсем темно.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="82">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Above the distant, still sadder hills there lingered, under a cloud bank, a depth of tortoise-shell sky.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Над дальними холмами, что были еще печальней, под берегом облаков, темнела черепаховая глубь неба.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="83">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">The heart-rending lights of Waindellville, throbbing in a fold of those dusky hills, were putting on their usual magic, though actually, as Pnin well knew, the place, when you got there, was merely a row of brick houses, a service station, a skating rink, a supermarket.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">В складке сумеречных холмов дрожали, надрывая сердце, огни Уэйнделвилла, являя, как всегда, волшебное зрелище, хотя Пнину доподлинно было известно, что при ближайшем рассмотрении городок этот не являл взору ничего, кроме вереницы кирпичных домов, бензоколонки, катка да большого магазина самообслуживания.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="84">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">As he walked to the little tavern in Library Lane for a large portion of Virginia ham and a good bottle of beer, Pnin suddenly felt very tired.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">По дороге в маленькую харчевню на Библиотечной аллее, где Пнин намеревался съесть большую порцию виргинской ветчины и выпить бутылку пива, он ощутил вдруг сильную усталость.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="85">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Not only had the Zol.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">И не только в том дело, что томина Zol.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="86">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Fond tome become even heavier after its unnecessary visit to the library, but something that Pnin had half heard in the course of the day, and had been reluctant to follow up, now bothered and oppressed him, as does, in retrospection, a blunder we have made, a piece of rudeness we have allowed ourselves, or a threat we have chosen to ignore.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Fond стал еще тяжелее после ненужного визита в библиотеку, но и в чем-то еще таком, что Пнин прослушал сегодня вполуха, а дослушать до конца не захотел, но что беспокоило и угнетало его теперь, как порой угнетают нас задним числом, в воспоминании, совершенная нами ошибка, или невольная грубость, или угроза, которою мы предпочли пренебречь.</se>
  </para>
</body>
</html>
