<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<html>
<head>
</head>
<body>
  <para id="0">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">13</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">13</se>
  </para>
  <para id="1">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">From the sideboard and dining-room table Pnin removed to the kitchen sink the used china and silverware.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Пнин собрал с буфета и со стола грязную посуду, ложки, ножи и вилки и снес их в кухонную раковину.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="2">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He put away what food remained into the bright Arctic light of the refrigerator.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Оставшуюся еду он сунул в яркий арктический свет холодильника.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="3">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">The ham and tongue had all gone, and so had the little sausages; but the vinaigrette had not been a success, and enough caviare and meat tarts were left over for a meal or two tomorrow.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Ветчина и язык исчезли, как, впрочем, и маленькие сосиски; однако винегрет не пользовался успехом, а также остались на завтра икра и пирожки с мясом, чтобы подкрепиться раз или два.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="4">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'Boom-boom-boom,' said the china closet as he passed by.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">"Бум-бум-бум", — сказал буфет, когда Пнин проходил мимо него.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="5">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He surveyed the living-room and started to tidy it up.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Он оглядел гостиную и начал уборку.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="6">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">A last drop of Pnin's Punch glistened in its beautiful bowl Joan had crooked a lipstick-stained cigarette butt in her saucer; Betty had left no trace and had taken all the glasses back to the kitchen.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">В красивой чаше блистала последняя капля пнинского пунша. Джоун придавила в своем блюдечке измазанный помадой окурок; Кэти не оставила от себя никаких следов и снесла все стаканы в кухню.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="7">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Mrs Thayer had forgotten a booklet of pretty multi-coloured matches on her plate, next to a bit of nougat.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Миссис Тэйер оставила на своей тарелке, рядом с кусочком нуги, книжечку симпатичных разноцветных спичек.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="8">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Mr Thayer had twisted into all kinds of weird shapes half a dozen paper napkins; Hagen had quenched a messy cigar in an uneaten bunchlet of grapes.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Мистер Тэйер, скрутив полдюжины бумажных салфеток, придал им какие-то причудливые очертания; Гаген загасил грязную сигару в нетронутом блюде виноградных гроздей. (*1) Бедный малый, бедняга (нем.).</se>
  </para>
  <para id="9">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">In the kitchen, Pnin prepared to wash up the dishes.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Перейдя на кухню, Пнин изготовился к мытью посуды.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="10">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He removed his silk coat, his tie, and his dentures.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Он снял шелковую куртку, галстук и зубные протезы.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="11">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">To protect his shirt front and tuxedo trousers, he donned a soubrette's dappled apron.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Чтобы не испачкать грудь сорочки и брюки от смокинга, он надел пестрый субреточный фартук.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="12">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He scraped various titbits off the plates into a brown paper bag, to be given eventually to a mangy little white dog, with pink patches on its back, that visited him sometimes in the afternoon вЂ” there was no reason a human's misfortune should interfere with a canine's pleasure.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Соскреб с тарелок в коричневый бумажный пакет всякие лакомые объедки, чтоб отдать их при случае запаршивевшей белой собачонке с розовыми пятнами на спине, которая прибегала иногда в послеобеденное время — нет смысла в том, чтобы она лишалась своих собачьих радостей по причине человеческого несчастья.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="13">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He prepared a bubble bath in the sink for the crockery, glass, and silverware, and with infinite care lowered the aquamarine bowl into the tepid foam.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">В раковине Пнин приготовил пузырчатую ванну для посуды, ножей и вилок, потом с бесконечной осторожностью опустил в эту теплую пену аквамариновую чашу.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="14">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Its resonant flint glass emitted a sound full of muffled mellowness as it settled down to soak.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">При погружении звонкий английский хрусталь издал приглушенный и мягкий звон.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="15">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He rinsed the amber goblets and the silverware under the tap, and submerged them in the same foam.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Ополоснув янтарные стаканы, ножи и вилки под краном, он опустил их в пену.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="16">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Then he fished out the knives, forks, and spoons, rinsed them, and began to wipe them.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Потом выудил оттуда ножи, вилки и ложки, ополоснул их и стал вытирать.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="17">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He worked very slowly, with a certain vagueness of manner that might have been taken for a mist of abstraction in a less methodical man.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Работал он очень медленно, с каким-то отсутствующим видом, что в человеке менее методическом могло быть принято за некоторую рассеянность.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="18">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He gathered the wiped spoons into a posy, placed them in a pitcher which he had washed but not dried, and then took them out one by one and wiped them all over again.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Он собрал вытертые ложки в букет, поставил их в кувшин, который он предварительно вымыл, но не протер насухо, потом вынул их одну за другой и протер заново.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="19">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He groped under the bubbles, around the goblets, and under the melodious bowl, for any piece of forgotten silver вЂ” and retrieved a nutcracker.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Потом стал шарить под пенной поверхностью, среди стаканов, под мелодичною чашей, ища, не осталось ли там ножей или вилок, — и извлек щипцы для орехов.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="20">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Fastidious Pnin rinsed it, and was wiping it, when the leggy thing somehow slipped out of the towel and fell like a man from a roof.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Дотошный Пнин ополоснул щипцы и уже начал их протирать, когда эта ногастая штука вдруг каким-то непонятным образом выскользнула из полотенца и стала падать вниз, как человек, сорвавшийся с крыши.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="21">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He almost caught it вЂ” his fingertips actually came into contact with it in mid-air, but this only helped to propel it into the treasure-concealing foam of the sink, where an excruciating crack of broken glass followed upon the plunge.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Пнин почти что успел изловить щипцы — его кончики пальцев успели коснуться их на лету, но это лишь точнее направило их полет к пенной поверхности, скрывавшей сокровища, оттуда тотчас же за всплеском раздался душераздирающий треск разбитого стекла.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="22">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Pnin hurled the towel into a comer and, turning away stood for a moment staring at the blackness beyond the threshold of the open back door.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Пнин отшвырнул полотенце в угол и, отвернувшись, стоял какое-то мгновенье, глядя в черноту за порогом распахнутой кухонной двери.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="23">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">A quiet, lacy-winged little green insect circled in the glare of a strong naked lamp above Pnin's glossy bald head.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Крошечная зеленая букашка с кружевными крылышками беззвучно летала вокруг ослепительной голой лампочки над блестящей лысой головой Пнина.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="24">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He looked very old, with his toothless mouth half open and a film of tears dimming his blank, unblinking eyes.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Он выглядел сейчас очень старым, с его полуоткрытым беззубым ртом и пеленою слез, замутивших невидящий, немигающий взгляд.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="25">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Then, with a moan of anguished anticipation, he went back to the sink and, bracing himself, dipped his hand deep into the foam.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Наконец, со стоном болезненного предчувствия, он повернулся к раковине и, набравшись духу, глубоко погрузил руку в мыльную пену.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="26">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">A jagger of glass stung him.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Укололся об осколок стекла.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="27">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Gently he removed a broken goblet.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Осторожно вынул разбитый стакан.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="28">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">The beautiful bowl was intact.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Прекрасная чаша была цела.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="29">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He took a fresh dish towel and went on with his household work.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Он взял чистое кухонное полотенце и снова взялся за свою работу.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="30">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">When everything was clean and dry, and the bowl stood aloof and serene on the safest shelf of a cupboard, and the little bright house was securely locked up in the large dark night. Pnin sat down at the kitchen table and, taking a sheet of yellow scrap paper from its drawer, unclipped his fountain pen and started to compose the draft of a letter:</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Когда все было перемыто и протерто, и чаша стояла отрешенная и безмятежная, на самой недоступной из буфетных полок, и маленький нарядный домик был надежно заперт в огромной черной ночи, Пнин уселся за кухонный стол и, достав из ящика лист желтой почтовой бумаги, отвинтил колпачок авторучки и принялся сочинять черновик своего письма.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="31">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'Dear Hagen,' he wrote in his clear firm hand, 'permit me to recaputilate (crossed out) recapitulate the conversation we had tonight.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">"Дорогой Гаген, — писал он своим четким и твердым почерком, — разрешите мне резюмировать (вычеркнуто) резюмировать разговор, который мы имели вчера.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="32">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">It, I must confess, somewhat astonished me.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Он, я должен признаться, несколько меня удивлял.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="33">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">If I had the honour to correctly understand you, you said вЂ” '</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Если я имел честь вас правильно понимать, вы сказали..."</se>
  </para>
</body>
</html>
