<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<html>
<head>
</head>
<body>
  <para id="0">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">4</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">4</se>
  </para>
  <para id="1">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Cook's Castle was a three-storey brick-and-timber mansion built around 1860 and partly rebuilt half a century later, when Susan's father purchased it from the Dudley-Greene family in order to make of it a select resort hotel for the richer patrons of the curative Onkwedo Springs.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Куков замок представлял собой трехэтажное здание из кирпича и бревен, построенное примерно в 1860 году и частично перестроенное полвека спустя, когда отец Сьюзен купил его у семейства Дадли-Грин, чтобы превратить в отель для избранной публики, а именно для самых богатых посетителей целебных Онкведских источников.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="2">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">It was an elaborate and ugly building in a mongrel style, with the Gothic bristling through remnants of French and Florentine, and when originally designed might have belonged to the variety which Samuel Sloan, an architect of the time, classified as An Irregular Northern Villa 'well adapted to the highest requirements of social life' and called' Northern' because of 'the aspiring tendency of its roof and towers'.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Это был вычурный и уродливый образец ублюдочной эклектики, в котором готика щетинилась среди остатков французского и флорентийского стилей; что же до первоначального замысла, здание должно было представлять собой ту разновидность строений, которую архитектор того времени Сэмюел Слоун определил как "оригинальную северную виллу", "наилучшим образом приспособленную для самых высоких требований социальной жизни" и названную "северной" из-за тенденции к "устремленности в небо ее крыши и башен".</se>
  </para>
  <para id="3">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">The piquancy of these pinnacles and the merry, somewhat even inebriated air the mansion had of having been composed of several smaller Northern Villas, hoisted into mid air and knocked together anyhow, with parts of unassimilated roofs, half-hearted gables, cornices, rustic quoins, and other projections sticking out on all sides, had, alas, but briefly attracted tourists.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Пикантность всех этих остроконечных башенок и веселый, даже как бы разухабистый вид всего сооружения, происходивший от того, что оно было скомпоновано из нескольких "северных вилл" поменьше, поднятых в небо и кое-как сколоченных вместе, причем детали несовпадающих по уровню крыш, неуверенно поднятых в небо коньков, карнизов, углов, сложенных из грубого камня, и прочие, самые разнообразные выступы торчали вкривь и вкось повсеместно, — все эти особенности хоть, увы, и недолго, а все же привлекали сюда туристов.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="4">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">By 1920, the Onkwedo waters had mysteriously lost whatever magic they had contained, and after her father's death Susan had vainly tried to sell The Pines, since they had another more comfortable house in the residential quarter of the industrial city where her husband worked.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">К 1920 году Онкведские воды загадочным образом утратили какие бы то ни было чудодейственные свойства, и после смерти отца Сьюзен тщетно пыталась продать Сосны, поскольку у них был другой дом, в городе, где работал ее муж.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="5">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">However, now that they had got accustomed to use the Castle for entertaining their numerous friends, Susan was glad that the meek beloved monster had found no purchaser.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Однако теперь, когда у них вошло в привычку принимать в Замке своих многочисленных друзей, Сьюзен рада была, что на их кроткое возлюбленное страшилище не нашлось покупателя.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="6">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Within, the diversity was as great as without.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Внутри дома разнобой был столь же велик, как снаружи.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="7">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Four spacious rooms opened from the large hall that retained something of its hostelic stage in the generous dimensions of the grate.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Четыре просторные комнаты выходили в огромный холл, который, даже в размахе гигантской каминной решетки, сохранял еще кое-что от былой отельной поры.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="8">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">The hand rail of the stairs, and at least one of its spindles, dated from 1720, having been transferred to the house, while it was being built, from a far older one, whose very site was no longer exactly known.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Лестничные перила, по крайней мере одна из их опор, относились к 1720 году и были перенесены сюда при постройке из какого-то более старого здания, самое местонахождение которого не было ныне точно известно.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="9">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Very ancient, too, were the beautiful sideboard panels of game and fish in the dining-room.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Очень старыми были также красивые буфетные панели в столовой с изображениями дичи и рыб.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="10">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">In the half a dozen rooms of which each of the upper floors consisted, and in the two wings in the rear, one could discover, among disparate pieces of furniture, some charming satinwood bureau, some romantic rosewood sofa, but also all kinds of bulky and miserable articles, broken chairs, dusty marble-topped tables, morose Г©tagГЁres with bits of dark-looking glass in the back as mournful as the eyes of old apes.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">В полдюжине комнат на каждом из верхних этажей, а также в двух боковых приделах здания среди разрозненной мебели можно было обнаружить несколько прелестных бюро из сатинового дерева, несколько романтических кушеток из розового дерева, но также и самые разнообразные громоздкие и убогие предметы, вроде поломанных стульев, пыльных столиков с мраморной столешницей, мрачных etageres с осколками темного зеркала в задней стенке, печальными, как глаза старых обезьян.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="11">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">The chamber Pnin got was a pleasant south-east one on the upper floor: it had remnants of gilt paper on the walls, an army cot, a plain washstand, and all kinds of shelves, brackets, and scrollwork mouldings.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Пнину досталась приятная комната на верхнем этаже в юго-восточном крыле здания, на стенах которой сохранились остатки золоченых обоев: здесь стояли армейская койка и простой умывальник и виднелись в изобилии разнообразные выступы, консоли и лепные завитки.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="12">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Pnin shook open the casement, smiled at the smiling forest, again remembered a distant first day in the country, and presently walked down, clad in a new navy-blue bathrobe and wearing on his bare feet a pair of ordinary rubber over-shoes, a sensible precaution if one intends to walk through damp and, perhaps, snake-infested grass.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Пнин распахнул окна, улыбнулся улыбчивой лесной чаще, снова вспомнил далекий свой первый день в деревне и вскоре спустился вниз, переодетый в новый темно-синий купальный халат и самые обыкновенные резиновые галоши на босу ногу, что было разумной предосторожностью на случай, если придется идти по сырой траве или, что тоже вполне возможно, по траве, где водятся змеи.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="13">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">On the garden terrace he found Chateau.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">На садовой террасе он увидел Шато.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="14">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Konstantin Ivanich Chateau, a subtle and charming scholar of pure Russian lineage despite his surname (derived, I am told, from that of a Russianized Frenchman who adopted orphaned Ivan), taught at a large New York university and had not seen his very dear Pnin for at least five years.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Константин Иванович Шато, тонкий и обаятельный ученый чисто русского происхождения (несмотря на свою фамилию, которую, как мне говорили, он унаследовал от обрусевшего француза, который усыновил сироту Ивана), преподавал в огромном Нью-Йоркском университете, и оттого они не виделись с его любезным другом Пниным по меньшей мере лет пять.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="15">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">They embraced with a warm rumble of joy.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Они обнялись с сердечным рыком радости.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="16">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">I confess to have been myself, at one time, under the spell of angelic Konstantin Ivanich, namely, when we used to meet every day in the winter of 1935 or 1936 for a morning stroll under the laurels and nettle trees of Grasse, southern France, where he then shared a villa with several other Russian expatriates.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Признаюсь, я и сам находился под обаянием божественного Константина Ивановича в какой-то период своей жизни, а именно зимой 1935 или 1936 года, когда мы имели с ним обыкновение встречаться каждое утро для прогулки под лавровыми и каркасными деревьями Граса, на юге Франции, где он снимал тогда виллу вместе с несколькими другими русскими изгнанниками.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="17">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">His soft voice, the gentlemanly St Petersburgan burr of his r's, his mild, melancholy caribou eyes, the auburn goatee he continuously twiddled, with a shredding motion of his long, frail fingers вЂ” everything about Chateau (to use a literary formula as old-fashioned as he) produced a rare sense of well-being in his friends.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Его мягкий голос, аристократическое санкт-петербургское картавое "р", кроткий, печальный взгляд его оленьих глаз, его темнорыжая эспаньолка, которую он беспрестанно теребил и дергал своими длинными, хрупкими пальцами, — все в нем (пользуясь литературной формулой, столь же старомодной, как и он сам) вызывало в его друзьях редкое чувство благополучия.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="18">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Pnin and he talked for a while, comparing notes.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Они с Пниным поговорили некоторое время, обмениваясь мнениями.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="19">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">As not unusual with firm-principled exiles, every time they met after a separation they not only endeavoured to catch up with a personal past, but also to sum up by means of a few rapid passwords вЂ” allusions, intonations impossible to render in a foreign language вЂ” the course of recent Russian history, thirty-five years of hopeless injustice following a century of struggling justice and glimmering hope.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Как это нередко ведется среди убежденных изгнанников, всякий раз, когда они встречались после разлуки, они не только пытались восстановить упущенные подробности личной судьбы, но также и подытожить при помощи нескольких произносимых скороговоркой ключевых слов, намеков, а также оттенков интонации, совершенно не поддающихся передаче на иностранном языке, развитие новейшей русской истории, те тридцать пять лет безнадежной несправедливости, которые наступили вслед за целым столетием пробивавшейся к свету справедливости и мерцавшей во тьме надежды.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="20">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Next, they switched to the usual shop talk of European teachers abroad, sighing and shaking heads over the ' typical American college student' who does not know geography, is immune to noise, and thinks education is but a means to get eventually a remunerative job.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Потом они перешли к обычным профессиональным разговорам, какие ведут европейские преподаватели за границей, вздыхая и качая головами по поводу "типичного американского студента", который не знает географии, обожает шум и считает, что образование не более, чем средство приобрести когда-нибудь хорошо оплачиваемую должность.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="21">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Then they inquired about each other's work in progress, and both were extremely modest and reticent about their respective researches.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Потом они расспросили друг друга, как движется работа, и оба проявили исключительную скромность и сдержанность, говоря о своих научных изысканиях.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="22">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Finally, as they walked along a meadow path, brushing against the golden rod, toward the wood where a rocky river ran, they spoke of their healths: Chateau, who looked so jaunty, with one hand in the pocket of his white flannel trousers and his lustring coat rather rakishly opened on a flannel waistcoat, cheerfully said that in the near future he would have to undergo an exploratory operation of the abdomen, and Pnin said, laughing, that every time he was X-rayed, doctors vainly tried to puzzle out what they termed' a shadow behind the heart'.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">В конце концов, двинувшись по луговой тропке, где цветы золотарника мягко шлепали их по ногам, в сторону леса, туда, где в скалистых берегах текла речка, они заговорили каждый о своем здоровье: Шато, который так лихо держал руку в кармане белых фланелевых штанов под щегольски распахнутым на белой фланелевой жилетке блестящим пиджаком с искрой, бодро сообщил, что в скором будущем ему предстоит операция с целью обследования брюшной полости, а Пнин сказал, улыбаясь, что всякий раз, когда он проходит рентген, врачи тщетно пытаются понять, что означает эта его, как они выражаются, "тень за сердцем".</se>
  </para>
  <para id="23">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'Good title for a bad novel,' remarked Chateau.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">— Хорошее название для плохого романа, — заметил Шато.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="24">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">As they were passing a grassy knoll just before entering the wood, a pink-faced venerable man in a seersucker suit, with a shock of white hair and a tumefied purple nose resembling a huge raspberry, came striding toward them down the sloping field, a look of disgust contorting his features.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Когда они шли по заросшему травой холму, уже приближаясь к лесу, какой-то почтенный розовощекий господин в полосатом льняном костюме, с копной седых волос и алым опухшим носом, похожим на огромную малиновую ягоду, стал крупными шагами спускаться им навстречу по склону холма с выражением крайнего неудовольствия, совершенно искажавшим его черты.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="25">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'I have to go back for my hat,' he cried dramatically as he drew near.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">— Мне придется вернуться за шляпой, — воскликнул он совершенно трагически, подойдя к ним ближе.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="26">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'Are you acquainted?' murmured Chateau, fluttering his hands introductively 'Timofey Pavlich Pnin, Ivan Ilyich Gramineev.'</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">— Вы не знакомы? — проворковал Шато и слегка вскинул руки, представляя их друг другу. — Тимофей Павлыч Пнин, Иван Ильич Граминеев.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="27">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'Moyo pochtenie (My respects),' said both men, bowing to each other over a powerful handshake.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">— Moyo pochtenie (Мое почтение), — произнесли они, поклонившись друг другу и обменявшись крепким рукопожатием.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="28">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'I thought,' resumed Gramineev, a circumstantial narrator, 'that the day would continue as overcast as it had begun.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">— Я-то думал, — продолжил обстоятельный Граминеев, — что и весь день будет такой же облачный, как утро.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="29">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">By stupidity (po gluposti) I came out with an unprotected head.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">По глупости (ро gluposti) я вышел с непокрытой головой.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="30">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Now the sun is' roasting my brains.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">А теперь солнце просто мозги прожаривает.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="31">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">I have to interrupt my work.'</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Пришлось прервать работу.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="32">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He gestured toward the top of the knoll.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Он указал на вершину холма.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="33">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">There his easel stood in delicate silhouette against the blue sky.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Там стоял его мольберт, изящно вырисовываясь на фоне синего неба.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="34">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">From that crest he had been painting a view of the valley beyond, complete with quaint old barn, gnarled apple tree, and kine.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">С этой вершины он писал вид, открывавшийся в долину за холмом, дополненный старым странным сараем, искривленной яблоней и млечной коровой.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="35">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'I can offer you my panama,' said kind Chateau, but Pnin had already produced from his bathrobe pocket a large red handkerchief: he expertly twisted each of its corners into a knot.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">— Могу предложить вам свою панаму, — сказал добряк Шато, но Пнин уже извлек из кармана своего халата большой красный платок: он искусно завязал узелками его углы.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="36">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'Admirable....</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">— Чудесно...</se>
  </para>
  <para id="37">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Most grateful,' said Gramineev, adjusting this headgear.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Премного благодарен, — сказал Граминеев, прилаживая это приспособленье.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="38">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'One moment,' said Pnin.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">— Минуточку, — сказал Пнин.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="39">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'You must tuck in the knots.'</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">— Надо подоткнуть узелки.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="40">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">This done, Gramineev started walking up the field toward his easel.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Покончив с этим, Граминеев зашагал через поле к своему мольберту.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="41">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He was a well-known, frankly academic painter, whose soulful oils вЂ” 'Mother Volga', 'Three Old Friends' (lad, nag, dog), 'April Glade', and so forth-still graced a museum in Moscow.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Он был известный, откровенно академический художник, чьи душевные пейзажи маслом — "Матушка-Волга", "Три старых друга" (мальчик, кляча и собачка), "Апрельская полынья" и тому подобное — все еще украшали музей в Москве.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="42">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'Somebody told me,' said Chateau, as he and Pnin continued to progress riverward, 'that Liza's boy has an extraordinary talent for painting.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">— Кто-то мне говорил, — сказал Шато, когда они снова двинулись по направлению к реке, — что у Лизиного мальчика необычайный талант к живописи.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="43">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Is that correct?'</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Это правда?</se>
  </para>
  <para id="44">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'Yes,' answered Pnin.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">— Да, — сказал Пнин.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="45">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'All the more vexing (tem bolee obidno) that his mother, who I think is about to marry a third time, took Victor suddenly to California for the rest of the summer, whereas if he had accompanied me here, as had been planned, he would have had the splendid opportunity of being coached by Gramineev.'</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">— И тем более обидно, что его мать, которая, я полагаю, намерена в третий раз выйти замуж, вдруг решила забрать его до конца лета в Калифорнию, хотя если б он поехал со мной сюда, как мы планировали, у него была бы роскошная возможность поучиться у Граминеева.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="46">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'You exaggerate the splendour,' softly rejoined Chateau.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">— Вы преувеличиваете эту роскошь, — мягко отозвался Шато.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="47">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">They reached the bubbling and glistening stream.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Они подошли к кипящему и сверкающему речному потоку.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="48">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">A concave ledge between higher and lower diminutive cascades formed a natural swimming pool under the alders and pines.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Впадина в скалистом выступе между двумя маленькими водопадами образовала под сенью ольхи и сосен естественный плавательный водоем.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="49">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Chateau, a non-bather, made himself comfortable on a boulder.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Шато, который не купался, устроился поудобней на камне.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="50">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Throughout the academic year Pnin had regularly exposed his body to the radiation of a sun lamp; hence when he stripped down to his bathing trunks, he glowed in the dappled sunlight of the riverside grove with a rich mahogany tint.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">На протяжении всего учебного года Пнин с регулярностью подставлял свое тело под лучи загарной лампы; поэтому теперь, когда он остался в одних плавках, кожа его отливала в пестром солнечном трепещущем свете приречной рощи самым густым из оттенков красного дерева.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="51">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He removed his cross and his rubbers.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Он снял свой крест и свои галоши.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="52">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'Look, how pretty,' said observant Chateau.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">— Посмотрите, какая красота, — сказал внимательный Шато.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="53">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">A score of small butterflies, all of one kind, were settled on a damp patch of sand, their wings erect and closed, showing their pale undersides with dark dots and tiny orange-rimmed peacock spots along the hindwing margins; one of Pnin's shed rubbers disturbed some of them and, revealing the celestial hue of their upper surface, they fluttered around like blue snow-flakes before settling again.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Две дюжины крошечных бабочек, все одного вида, уселись на полоске мокрого песка, сложив свои прямые крылышки и обнажив бледный их испод с черными крапинками и маленькими павлиньими пятнышками, а также с оранжевым ободком по краям заднего крыла; часть из них была обеспокоена упавшей с ноги Пнина галошей, и, обнажив небесную синеву с наружной стороны крылышек, они некоторое время, точно синие хлопья снежинок, порхали над пляжем, пока не опустились снова.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="54">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'Pity Vladimir Vladimirovich is not here,' remarked Chateau.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">— Жаль, нет Владимира Владимировича, — сказал Шато.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="55">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'He would have told us all about these enchanting insects.'</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">— Он бы все нам рассказал об этих волшебных существах.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="56">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'I have always had the impression that his entomology was merely a pose.'</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">— У меня всегда было впечатление, что его увлечение энтомологией просто поза.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="57">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'Oh no,' said Chateau.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">— О нет, — сказал Шато.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="58">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'You will lose it some day,' he added, pointing to the Greek Catholic cross on a golden chainlet that Pnin had removed from his neck and hung on a twig.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">— Вы так его потеряете когда-нибудь, — добавил он, указывая на православный крест с золотой цепочкой, который Пнин, сняв с шеи, повесил на сучок.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="59">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Its glint perplexed a cruising dragonfly.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Его сиянье смущало кружившую над ним стрекозу.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="60">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'Perhaps I would not mind losing it,' said Pnin.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">— Может, я и не имел бы ничего против того, чтоб его потерять, — сказал Пнин.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="61">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'As you well know, I wear it merely from sentimental reasons.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">— Как вам хорошо известно, я ношу его только по сантиментальным причинам.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="62">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">And the sentiment is becoming burdensome.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">И эти сантименты становятся для меня обременительными.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="63">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">After all, there is too much of the physical about this attempt to keep a particle of one's childhood in contact with one's breast bone.'</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Строго говоря, есть нечто слишком материальное в этой попытке держать частичку своего детства в соприкосновении с грудной клеткой.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="64">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">'You are not the first to reduce faith to a sense of touch,' said Chateau, who was a practising Greek Catholic and deplored his friend's agnostic attitude.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">— Вы не первый, кто сводит веру к чувству осязания, — сказал Шато, который посещал православную церковь и сожалел об агностицизме своего друга.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="65">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">A horsefly applied itself, blind fool, to Pnin's bald head, and was stunned by a smack of his meaty palm.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Слепень в ослеплении глупости сел на лысую голову Пнина и был оглушен шлепком его мясистой ладони.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="66">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">From a smaller boulder than the one upon which Chateau was perched, Pnin gingerly stepped down into the brown and blue water.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">С булыжника, что был размером поменьше того, на котором сидел Шато, Пнин осторожно вступил в коричневую и синюю воду.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="67">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He noticed he still had his wrist-watch вЂ” removed it and left it inside one of his rubbers.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Он заметил, что часы еще оставались у него на руке, — снял их и положил в одну из галош.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="68">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Slowly swinging his tanned shoulders, Pnin waded forth, the loopy shadows of leaves shivering and slipping down his broad back.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Медленно поводя загорелыми плечами, Пнин брел по воде, и петляющие тени листьев дрожали, сползая по его широкой спине.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="69">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He stopped and, breaking the glitter and shade around him, moistened his inclined head, rubbed his nape with wet hands, soused in turn each armpit, and then, joining both palms, glided into the water, his dignified breast-stroke sending off ripples on either side.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Он остановился, потом, разом расколов блистанье и тени, смочил склоненную голову, потер мокрыми руками шею, смочил по очереди каждую из подмышек, а потом, сложив ладони, скользнул в воду и поплыл, распространяя своим неторопливым, степенным брассом мелкую рябь по воде.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="70">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Around the natural basin, Pnin swam in state.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Пнин совершил торжественный круг вдоль края естественного водоема.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="71">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">He swam with a rhythmical splutter вЂ” half gurgle, half puff.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Он плыл с ритмическим клекотом — то булькая, то пыхтя.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="72">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Rhythmically he opened his legs and widened them out at the knees while flexing and straightening out his arms like a giant frog.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Ритмически раздвигал ноги, раскидывал их от коленей, сгибая и разгибая руки, точно гигантская лягушка.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="73">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">After two minutes of this, he waded out and sat on the boulder to dry.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Поплавав так две минуты, он выбрел на берег и сел на камень, чтобы обсохнуть.</se>
  </para>
  <para id="74">
    <se lang="uk" variant_id="0">Then he put on his cross, his wrist-watch, his rubbers, and his bathrobe.</se>
    <se lang="ru" variant_id="1">Потом надел крест, часы, галоши и купальный халат.</se>
  </para>
</body>
</html>
